<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="lawyer">
  <title>Lawyer's office</title>
  <section id="lawyer:start">
	<title>Initial situation</title>
	<para>
	  Hemmerlein &amp; Sons lawyer's office has a total of ten employees. The employees work
	  predominantly with office applications and a legal workflow management system, which is only
	  available for Microsoft Windows. Windows 10 is employed as the client operating system. All the
	  data are to be stored centrally on a server and backed up. As there is only limited technical
	  expertise available and it is not viable to finance an in-house administrator team, particular
	  value is placed on simple administration. The administrative duties described below can be
	  configured completely via simple-to-use, web-based interfaces after a successful initial
	  installation.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The company has a total of three laser printers (two identical black/white models and one
	  color laser printer), which are all installed in a central office. Large documents with high
	  volumes are printed often.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:services">
	<title>Systems and services</title>
	<para>
	  UCS offers the required services and applications ``out of the box'' as a complete solution. A
	  single UCS system is used, which provides the logon and file services for the Windows clients,
	  administrates the printers and automates the data backup.
	</para>

	  <figure id="kanzlei">
		<title>System overview of the lawyer's office Hemmerlein and Sons</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/kanzlei_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:users">
	<title>Management of user accounts</title>
	<para>
        User accounts for the ten employees are created in the &ucsUMC; web
        interface. Each employee can set the password with the Self Service App
        from the App Center. Like all user data the password is save to a LDAP
        directory server and requested when logging on to the Windows client.
    </para>

	  <figure id="umc-anlegen">
		<title>Creating a user in Univention Directory Manager</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/umc-benutzeranlegen_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:windows">
	<title>Managing the Windows computers</title>
	<para>
	  Samba 4 is used on the UCS system for the integration of Microsoft Windows clients. Samba 4
	  offers domain, directory and authentication services which are compatible with Microsoft
	  Active Directory. These also allow the use of the tools provided by Microsoft for the
	  management of group policies (GPOs).
	</para>

	<para>
	  Microsoft Windows clients can join the Active Directory-compatible domain provided by UCS and
	  can be centrally configured via group policies. From the client point of view, the domain join
	  procedure is identical to joining a Microsoft Windows-based domain.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:storage">
	<title>Storage management</title>
	<para>
	  Samba provides every user with a home directory on the UCS system as a file share via the CIFS
	  protocol. The user thus always receives the same data irrespective of the computer he is
	  logged in to. In addition, the central file storage allows central backups.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Moreover, there is a central share with legal literature, which is mounted on every client.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Similar to users, shares can also be created and managed web-based in the &ucsUMC;.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:sso">
  	<title>Single sign-on with a specialist legal application</title>
  	<para>
	  The chambers access a web-based legal service. This service has its own user administration
	  system. To avoid having to take care of the user identities and password twice, the UCS SAML
	  Identity Provider is used. SAML (Security Assertion Markup Language) is an XML-based standard
	  for exchanging authentication information, which allows single sign-on across domain
	  boundaries among other things. The legal service is registered with a cryptographic
	  certificate and then trusted by the UCS Identity Provider. The user then only needs to
	  authenticate himself in UCS and can use the legal service without renewed authentication. The
	  SAML Identity Provider can be installed via the Univention App Center.
  	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:print">
	<title>Printer services</title>
	<para>
	  The UCS system provides print services via the CUPS software. Both network-capable printers
	  and printers connected locally to a computer can be centrally administrated. The three
	  printers can be configured conveniently via the &ucsUMC; and are directly available to the
	  users on their Microsoft Windows clients.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The two black and white laser printers are grouped together in a printer group: this means
	  that, in addition to the targeted selection of a printer, users also have the opportunity of
	  printing on a pseudo-printer. This is where the print jobs are distributed in turn between the
	  two printers in the printer group. If one printers is busy, the free printer is selected
	  instead, which cuts down waiting times.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:groupware">
	<title>Groupware</title>
    <para>
      On the UCS system the groupware solution <emphasis>Kopano</emphasis> is
      installed as app from the App Center.  Kopano accesses the user data of
      the UCS directory service. The administration integrates seamlessly in
      the &ucsUMC;. The employees use the web-based <emphasis>Kopano WebApp</emphasis> for calendaring,
      also available in the App Center.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Virus detection including signature updates and Spam filters are integrated at no additional
	  cost.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:proxy">
	<title>Web proxy and web cache</title>
    <para>
      A web proxy server and web cache based on Squid is available with the app
      <emphasis>proxy server</emphasis> in UCS. Response times for regular calling the same web
      pages is reduced. Likewise, the data transfer volume via Internet access
      can be reduced. Furthermore, the access to Internet content can be
      controlled and managed. For example, it can be defined, which users or
      user groups access which websites.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:backup">
	<title>Backup</title>
	<para>
	  All files (both the users' files in the home directory and the legal literature files in the
	  central share) are stored on the UCS system and can thus be centrally saved on a tape
      drive. The App Center in UCS offers several solutions like for example
      Bareos Backup Server and SEP sesam Backup Server that can be used
      flexibly for different backup and archiving strategies.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:outlook">
	<title>Outlook</title>
	<para>
	  With regard to a planned merger of another office in Munich, it will be simple to install a
	  further UCS system in this branch. All LDAP data are then automatically transferred to the
	  site server allowing the employees to logon at on-site meetings in Munich with their standard
	  user credentials.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The existing Active Directory installation at the Munich office can be migrated to the UCS
	  domain fully automated using Univention AD Takeover.
	</para>

  </section>

  <section id="lawyer:ref">
	<title>References</title>
	<itemizedlist>
      <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual-4.4.html"/> (UCS manual)</simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/kopano-core"/> (<application>Kopano Core</application>)</simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/kopano-webapp"/> (<application>Kopano WebApp</application>)</simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/squid/"/> (<application>Proxyserver / Webcache (Squid)</application>)</simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/sep-sesam"/> (<application>SEP sesam Backup Server</application>)</simpara></listitem>
      <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/bareos"/> (<application>Bareos Backup Server</application>)</simpara></listitem>
	  <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual-4.4.html#windows:adtakeover"/></simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
