<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="engineering">
  <title>Medium-sized mechanical engineering company</title>
  <section id="engineering:start">
	<title>Initial situation</title>
	<para>
	  Ganupa Technologies is one of the leading manufacturers of rolled steel mills. At the company
	  headquarters in Germany, 260 people are employed in Production, Administration, Design and
	  Sales. In addition, there are also local offices in the USA, Argentina and India, each with
	  5-10 employees.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Linux is predominantly used on the desktops. The employees from Design
	  and Development are dependent on Linux software and require a freely
	  configurable desktop.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The employees from Administration and Sales will only be offered an
	  office suite, an e-mail client and a web browser.
	</para>

	<para>
	  An accounting software required by some users is only available for
	  Microsoft Windows. Part of the design process is performed with a CAD software,
	  which is only available for Oracle Solaris.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The administration of the computers should be as central as
	  possible. Whilst there are two IT technicians in the headquarters,
	  there are no technical personnel at the other three branch offices.
	</para>

	<para>
	  To avoid non-productive times caused by malfunctions, the majority of
	  the offered services must be provided redundantly.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A proxy server will buffer the network traffic in a cache and provide
	  virus protection.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A groupware solution is required for the coordination of the globally
	  distributed work procedures.
	</para>

	<para>
	  All user data are centrally saved on an Storage Area Network device (SAN).
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:impl">
	<title>Implementation</title>

	  <figure id="mittelstand">
		<title>System overview of Ganupa Technologies headquarters (virtualization is not considered)</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/mittelstand_en.png"/>
	  </figure>

	  <figure id="mittelstand-ueberblick">
		<title>Global organization scheme of Ganupa Technologies</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/mittelstand-ueberblick_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:dc">
	<title>Domain controller / LDAP directory</title>
	<para>
	  The company implements an infrastructure composed of a UCS domain
	  controller master (DC master), a UCS domain controller backup (DC
      backup), several UCS domain controller slaves (DC slaves) and desktop
      systems consisting of desktop computers and notebooks. Microsoft Windows
      and Ubuntu Linux are used on those systems.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC master is the centerpiece of the UCS domain. The central,
	  writable copy of the LDAP directory service is maintained on this
	  system.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC backup largely represents a copy of the DC master. In this
	  way, the important services are available doubled on the network, the
	  availability of the services is thus further increased and the load is
	  distributed between the UCS domain controllers.
	</para>

	<para>
	  If the DC master fails as a result of a hardware defect, the DC backup
	  can be converted to the DC master in a very short time.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC master and DC backup are both installed at the company
	  headquarters. The two UCS systems operate an LDAP server and provide
	  login services for the domains. A DNS and DHCP server maintained with
	  data from the LDAP directory runs on both systems and provides central
	  IP management. A print server is set up on the DC backup.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:virt">
	<title>Virtualization</title>
	<para>
	  All server systems of Ganupa Technologies are virtualized with
	  &ucsUVMM; (UVMM). Only open source software is used.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Virtualization servers based on UCS member servers (UCS servers without a local LDAP server)
	  form the basis for the virtualization. Each of these hosts one or more virtual machines with
	  the KVM virtualization solution. UCS and Microsoft Windows systems are operated
	  paravirtualized, i.e., the direct access of the virtualized systems to the hosts' resources
	  results in better performance. Paravirtualization drivers for KVM are provided by
	  Univention as signed MSI installation packages and, as such, can be installed simply.
	</para>

	  <figure id="uvmm">
		<title>Managing virtual machines with UVMM</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/uvmm_en.png"/>
	  </figure>

	<para>
	  All virtual machines can be created and managed conveniently over the
	  web-based &ucsUVMM;. If maintenance work is necessary on a
	  virtualization server, the virtual machines running on this system can
	  be migrated to another server while still running.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Snapshots allow a simple rollback of updates in the case of error.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:print">
	<title>Print services</title>
	<para>
	  Print jobs are forwarded to the requested printer via a print
	  server. The print servers are realized with CUPS, which manages the
	  different printers in a central spooling.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In some larger offices several printers are grouped together into a
	  printer group; the users simply print on this group, whereby the print
	  jobs are equally distributed and the next free printer is used. This
	  saves the users from having to check whether a particular printer is
	  already in use.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In addition, every printer is assigned a page price. This allows accounting
	  to determine the incurred printing costs per user. This can optionally also be
      connected to limit the number of pages which can be printed. With
      the app <emphasis>Print Server Quota</emphasis> print quotas can be extended to a usergroup
      basis.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:db">
	<title>Integration of Oracle Solaris systems</title>
	<para>
	  A specialist application for CAD design is only available for
	  Oracle Solaris. The name services on the Solaris system have been adapted to
	  query the UCS LDAP for authentication, i.e. users can log in to the
	  Solaris system with their domain user identification and
	  password. This negates the need for the additional maintenance of
	  local Solaris user accounts.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The Solaris system is assigned its IP address from the UCS DHCP
	  servers via DHCP. The files are saved on the UCS file servers via a
	  NFS share.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:storage">
	<title>Data management</title>
	<para>
	  All user data is stored on a central Storage Area Network (SAN) system. The different shares
	  are registered and administrated in the &ucsUMC;. The
	  Linux and Solaris clients access individual shares via the network
	  file system (NFS), the Windows clients via the CIFS protocol.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:groupware">
	<title>Groupware</title>
	<para>
      Ganupa Technologies uses the groupware solution <emphasis>Open-Xchange
      App Suite</emphasis> for arranging meetings and organizing contacts
      and tasks.
	</para>

	<para>
      The groupware server is operated as a &ucsSlave; system on the Amazon EC2
      cloud. This allows flexible scaling of the groupware system to growing
      performance and storage requirements. The installation can be performed
      with a few clicks using the App Center.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The administration of the groupware-related attributes integrates
	  seamlessly in the &ucsUMC;. The employees access the groupware via
	  the OX App Suite web client and Mozilla Thunderbird.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Mobile devices (smartphones and tablets) are integrated via the
	  Microsoft ActiveSync protocol.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Virus detection including signature updates and Spam filters are
	  integrated at no additional cost.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:outlook">
	<title>Outlook</title>
	<para>
      At a later point in time, the plan is to monitor the Internet access
      centrally via a web proxy. For this purpose, UCS provides the app
      <emphasis>Proxy server/ web cache (Squid)</emphasis>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Alternatively, it is also possible to procure a specialized appliance,
	  which can authenticate the users against the UCS-LDAP server.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="engineering:ref">
	<title>References</title>
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual-4.4.html"/> (UCS manual)</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/oxseforucs/"/> (<application>OX App Suite</application>)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/squid/"/> (<application>Proxy server/ web cache (Squid)</application>)</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
