<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="school">
  <title>School board</title>
  <section id="school:start">
	<title>Initial situation</title>
	<para>
	  The administrative district <wordasword>Rechtwede</wordasword> is the school body for a total of
	  eight primary schools, comprehensive schools, vocational schools and
	  grammar schools.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The schools generally have one or two computer rooms with 20-30
	  PCs. The technical vocational school has a total of nine PC pools with
	  260 computers all together.
	</para>

	<para>
	  These PCs are maintained - for example, the installation of
	  software - by interested teachers and to some extent by school computer
	  clubs. Many teachers shy away from using PCs in the classroom, as
	  many students are distracted by Internet access during lessons.
	  Distributing digital teaching materials - for example, a PDF
	  with an exercise - is complicated and overwhelms some teachers.
	</para>

	<para>
	  There is an IT officer in the local education authority, who has to
	  travel to the schools to perform maintenance work and can only be
	  present in the individual schools sporadically due to the size of the
	  administrative district.
	</para>

	<para>
	   On most PCs - which are operated on <systemitem class="osname">Microsoft Windows XP</systemitem> or
	  <systemitem class="osname">Microsoft Windows 7</systemitem> - there is one common user account. The
	  computers are not centrally administrated.
	</para>

	<para>
	  As a result, the pupils do not have personal directories for saving
	  their work which cannot be accessed by others.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Software installation versions are often different on the computers
	  and many computers have viruses and Trojans as security updates are
	  not installed systematically.
	</para>

	<para>
	  An additional aim is to introduce a groupware solution for simpler arrangement
	  of meetings between the teaching staff.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="school:impl">
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>
	  The school board is implementing an environment based on UCS@school, a
	  complete IT solution based on UCS with numerous additional components
	  for the use, operation and management of the schools' IT.
	</para>

	<para>
	  This involves the implementation of an infrastructure composed of a UCS
	  &ucsMaster; (DC master), a &ucsBackup; (DC backup) and several &ucsSlave; (hereinafter
	  called school server) in the individual schools.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For security reasons, the UCS@school concept specifies that the school
	  servers only perform a partial replication of the &ucsMaster;'s
	  LDAP directory. In the default setting they only replicate
	  the parts relevant for themselves (e.g., users and groups of the
	  respective school) and the global structures of the LDAP directory.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC master is the centrepiece of the UCS domain. The central,
	  writable copy of the LDAP directory service is provided on this
	  system.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC backup largely represents a copy of the DC master. In this way,
	  the important services are available doubled on the network, the
	  availability of the services is thus further increased and the load is
	  distributed between the UCS domain controllers. If the DC master fails
	  as a result of a hardware defect, the DC backup can be converted to
	  the DC Master in a very short time.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="schule-schema">
		<title>Structure of the school domain</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="88%" fileref="illustrations40/schultraeger_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="school:user">
	<title>Management of user data</title>
	<para>
	  All school registrations, changes and transfers are managed
	  in the school administration software Magellan by the school administration
	  office. When the school year changes, the school data are imported -
	  in CSV format - into the UCS user administration. Subsequent
	  adjustments can be made via the &ucsUMC;.
	</para>

	<para>
	  There are four different user roles in UCS@school:
	</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara><emphasis>Students</emphasis></simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara><emphasis>Teachers</emphasis> have more permissions than pupils. They can,
		  e.g., reset pupil passwords or block Internet access during a lesson.</simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara><emphasis>School administrators</emphasis> are technically trained
		  teachers who take on extensive administrative tasks, e.g., the administration of computer
		  groups or Internet filters.</simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara><emphasis>Staff</emphasis> are users who are not employed directly at the
		  schools, e.g., in the school administration office.</simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="school:services">
	<title>Services on the school servers</title>
	<para>
	  A local LDAP directory is operated on all school servers and can be
	  accessed by all the other computers at the school. For this purpose,
	  the school server automatically replicates the relevant subset of the LDAP directory of the
	  &ucsMaster; so that all the necessary data are available
	  up-to-date and complete. The operation of the local directory service
	  thus reduces the data volumes to be transferred to the &ucsMaster;
	  and ensures seamless operation, even if the
	  connection between the school server and the central &ucsMaster;
	  system fails.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Samba 4 is used on all the school servers for the integration of
	  Windows clients. Samba 4 offers domain, directory and authentication
	  services which are compatible with Microsoft Active Directory. These
	  also allow the use of the tools provided by Microsoft for the
	  management of group policies (GPOs).
	</para>

	<para>
	  Windows clients can join the Active Directory-compatible domains
	  provided by UCS directly and can be centrally configured via group
	  policies. From the client point of view, the domain join procedure is
	  identical to joining a Windows-based domain.
	</para>

	<para>
	  User data are stored in a home share provided by the school servers.
	  Pupils and teachers alike have their own personal home directory.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The open source software distribution opsi runs on the Windows
	  clients. It allows a largely automated distribution of security
	  updates and service packs to the Windows clients, with the result that
	  all systems can be operated constantly fully protected even without a
	  dedicated administrator. The OPSI4UCS configuration integrates opsi
	  into the UCS management system.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A DNS and DHCP server configured with data from the LDAP directory
	  runs on every school server and provides central IP management.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In addition, there is a print server, which forwards print jobs on to
	  the selected printer. The print servers are realised with CUPS, which
	  integrates the different printers in a central spooling.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="school:modules">
	<title>Tools for using IT-assisted teaching</title>
	<para>
	  &ucsUAS; offers a range of modules for the &ucsUMC; which can be
	  used for IT-supported teaching.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="schule-module">
		<title>Applications related to teaching</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="88%" fileref="illustrations40/schule-module_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Some modules are available to teachers and school administrators,
	  whilst other modules are reserved for school administrators.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <guimenu>Passwords (students)</guimenu> allows teachers to reset pupil
	  passwords. The existing pupil passwords cannot be read in plain text, so if a
	  pupil forgets his password, a new password needs to be entered. This
	  can also be used by school administrators to reset teacher passwords.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="schule-passwoerter">
		<title>Password reset</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations40/schule-benutzer_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <guimenu>Computer room</guimenu> module allows the teacher to control the
	  pupil PCs and Internet access during a lesson. Internet access
	  can be blocked or permitted and individual web pages can be
	  white-listed. If a special software (iTALC) is installed
	  on the pupil PCs, these PCs can also be controlled remotely. For example, the
	  screens can be locked so that, for example in a chemistry lesson, the
	  pupils' undivided attention can be focussed on the experiment.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In addition, the contents of the screen of one PC can also be
	  transferred to other systems. This makes it possible for the
	  teacher to hold a presentation without a projector.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Each school is supported by a help desk. The help desk can, for
	  example, be maintained by a support organisation in the education
	  authority or by technically trained teachers in the
	  schools. The <guimenu>Contacting helpdesk</guimenu> module allows the
	  teachers and school administrators to send a support request.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Every pupil is a member of a class. In addition, there is also
	  the possibility of using the <guimenu>Administrate workgroups</guimenu> module
	  to assign pupils to cross-class workgroups.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The creation of a working group automatically creates a file share on
	  the school server which can be accessed by all the members of the
	  workgroup.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Teachers can add pupils to working groups or remove them, but cannot
	  create any new working groups. This must be done by a school
	  administrator.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="schule-gruppen">
		<title>Group management</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations40/schule-gruppen_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <guimenu>Moderate printers</guimenu> module can also be used to
	  check what the pupils print. The pending print jobs can be checked by
	  the teacher and then either deleted or approved for printing. This can
	  prevent unnecessary or incorrect printing.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="schule-drucker">
		<title>Printer moderation</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations40/schule-drucker_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <guimenu>Distribute materials</guimenu> module simplifies the
	  distribution and collection of teaching materials from classes and
	  working groups. Optionally, it is also possible to set a period for
	  the distribution and collection. This makes it possible to allocate
	  tasks that need to be done by the end of the lesson. Once
	  this period elapses, the distributed materials are then automatically
	  collected back in again and stored in the teacher's home
	  directory.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="schule-material">
		<title>Distribution of teaching material</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="illustrations40/schule-material_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <guimenu>Room management</guimenu> module is used to assign
	  computers to a computer room in a school. These computer rooms can be
	  centrally managed by the teachers, for example as regards permitting
	  Internet access.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A proxy server is used for the filtering of the Internet
	  access and checks if access to a certain web page is allowed when someone
	  attempts to open that site. If this is not the case, an information
	  page is displayed.
	</para>

	<para>
	  For example, if pupils are supposed to research using Wikipedia during a
	  lesson, a rule list can be defined blocking access to all other
	  Internet sites. This rule list can then be activated by the teacher.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The <guimenu>Define internet rules</guimenu> function can be used to
	  administrate the rules.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="school:italc">
	<title>Management of pupil's desktops using iTALC</title>
	<para>
	  iTALC is a didactic software for accessing pupil desktops. iTALC is
	  open source software and is installed on the pupil desktops (in
	  addition to Microsoft Windows, it is also available for Linux).
	</para>

	<para>
	  It offers teachers the following functions among others:
	</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>The teacher can view a pupil's desktop and make supporting adjustments
		  himself if needs be.</simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>The demo mode displays the contents of the teacher's desktop on all pupil
		  desktops. In the same way, the content of one pupil desktop can also be approved for the
		  demo mode.</simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>Screens and input devices can be centrally blocked to gain the full
		  attention of the pupils.</simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>Computers can be centrally turned on and shut down via
		  wake-on-LAN.</simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>Text messages can be sent to pupils.</simpara></listitem>

		</itemizedlist>

	<para>
	  The iTALC settings can be configured in a web assistant for each
	  computer room.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="school:groupware">
	<title>Groupware</title>
	<para>
	  The school board uses the groupware solution Kolab for arranging
	  meetings and organising contacts and tasks among the teachers and
	  school employees. The installation can be performed with a few clicks
	  using the Univention App Center.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The administration of the groupware-relevant attributes integrates
	  seamlessly in the &ucsUMC;. The employees access the groupware via
	  the web client RoundCube.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Mobile devices (smartphones) are integrated via the Microsoft
	  ActiveSync protocol.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="school:ref">
	<title>References</title>
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="http://docs.univention.de/manual.html"/> (UCS manual)</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="http://docs.univention.de/ucsschool-manual.html"/> (UCS@school manuals for administrators (currently only available in German))</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="http://docs.univention.de/ucsschool-teacher-manual.html"/> (UCS@school manuals for teachers (currently only available in German))</simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="http://www.univention.de/en/products/ucs/app-catalogue/app/details/kolab"/> (Kolab)</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
