<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="insurance">
  <title>Heterogeneous enterprise environment in an insurance company</title>
  <section id="insurance:start">
	<title>Initial situation</title>
	<para>
		<foreignphrase>Hanseatische Marineversicherung</foreignphrase> (<acronym>HMV</acronym>) is an insurance company with
		1800 employees specialized in the logistics sector. <acronym>HMV</acronym> is a subsidiary
	  of the Vigil Insurances parent company.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The parent company operates an independent directory service based on
	  Microsoft Active Directory, but the user data of the individual
	  subsidiaries is managed internally.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The employees work at a total of 36 locations across the world with
	  the largest being the company headquarter in Bremen with approximately
	  250 persons. Many of the users work on the move with laptops as
	  salespersons or estimators.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Microsoft Windows 10 is used on all the desktops. Software distribution
	  and the installation of security updates are centralized.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Citrix XenApp needs to be employed in the headquarters because of a
	  superordinate group policy: users should access the terminal services
	  with thin clients.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The groupware Microsoft Exchange is provided centrally by the parent
	  company.
	</para>

	<para>
	  All users, computers and services should be centrally
	  administrable. Critical system status should be reported promptly per
	  e-mail and SMS.
	</para>

	<para>
	  All server systems in the headquarters should be virtualized. The
	  resulting considerable significance of virtualization requires the
	  implementation of an open source solution.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Data backup is performed centrally in Bremen.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Different international compliance requirements from the insurance
	  sector must be satisfied.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:impl">
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>
	  The company implements an infrastructure composed of a &ucsMaster;
	  (DC master), a &ucsBackup; (DC backup), several UCS &ucsSlave; (DC
	  slaves) and 150 thin clients.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC master is the centerpiece of the UCS domain. The central,
	  writable LDAP directory is provided on this system.
	</para>

	  <figure id="versicherung-gesamt">
		<title>General overview (excluded: storage, DNS, DHCP, print services, virtualization, backup)</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/versicherung_en.png"/>
	  </figure>

	<para>
	  The DC backup also largely represents a copy of the DC master. In this
	  way, the important services are available doubled on the network, the
	  availability of the services is thus further increased and the load is
	  distributed between the domain controllers.
	</para>

	<para>
	  If the DC master fails as a result of a hardware defect, the DC backup
	  can be converted to the DC Master in a very short time.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The DC master and DC backup are both installed at the company headquarters.
	  The locations also contain additional &ucsSlave; systems, which
	  provide Windows domain services, print services and software distribution.
	</para>

	  <figure id="versicherung-standort">
		<title>Structure of a location</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations44/versicherung-standort_en.png"/>
	  </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:virt">
	<title>Virtualization</title>
	<para>
	  All server systems in the HMV environment are virtualized with
	  &ucsUVMM; (UVMM). Only open source software is used.
	</para>

	  <figure id="uvmm2">
		<title>Managing virtual machines with UVMM</title>
		<graphic align="center" scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/uvmm_en.png"/>
	  </figure>

	<para>
	  Virtualization servers based on UCS member servers (server installations
	  without a local LDAP server) form the basis for the
	  virtualization. Each of these hosts one or more virtual machines with
	  the KVM virtualization solution. UCS and Windows systems are operated
	  paravirtualized, i.e., the direct access of the virtualized systems to the
	  hosts' resources results in better performance.
	</para>

	<para>
	  All virtual machines can be created and managed conveniently over the
	  web-based &ucsUVMM;. If maintenance work is necessary on a
	  virtualization server, the virtual machines running on this system can
	  be migrated to another server while still running.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:software">
	<title>Software distribution of UCS systems</title>
	<para>
	  Installation profiles have been created for the UCS domain
	  controllers. These profiles can be used to roll out new systems with
	  the Univention Net Installer using PXE or, as required, to restore
	  systems after hardware failure. The installation concludes without
	  further user interaction.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A central package installation source - the repository - is
	  established on a server in the headquarters for the installation of
	  release updates and the subsequent installation of software
	  packages. All installable software packages and updates are provided
	  there.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Policies in the &ucsUMC; can be used to control the software
	  distribution centrally. The updates can be installed or software
	  packages can be subsequently installed at a freely selectable time or
	  when shutting down / starting up the system.
	</para>

	<para>
	  All systems record the installed packages in a central SQL database
	  automatically so that an overview of the software inventory is always
	  available. Security updates for UCS are promptly provided to download
	  and can also be installed automatically.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:windows">
	<title>Connecting Windows clients and Windows software deployment</title>
	<para>
	  Samba 4 is used in the HMV for the integration of Microsoft Windows
	  clients. Samba 4 offers domain, directory and authentication services
	  which are compatible with Microsoft Active Directory. These also allow
	  the use of the tools provided by Microsoft for the management of group
	  policies (GPOs).
	</para>

	<para>
	  Windows clients can join the Active Directory-compatible domains
	  provided by UCS directly and can be centrally configured via group
	  policies. From the client point of view, the domain join procedure is
	  identical to joining a Windows-based domain.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The Open Source software distribution opsi runs on the Windows
	  clients. It allows an extensively automated distribution of security
	  updates and Windows updates as well as the rollout of software
	  packages to the Windows clients.
	</para>

	<para>
	  opsi is also used for the rollout of new Windows systems. These are
	  automatically installed via PXE.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:ad">
	<title>Active Directory synchronization</title>
	<para>
	  The Univention Active Directory connector (AD connector for short)
	  makes it possible to synchronize directory service objects between a
      Microsoft Windows 2008/2012/2016 server with Microsoft Active
	  Directory (AD) and an Open Source LDAP directory service in &ucsUCS;.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The synchronization settings can be specified individually. The
	  administrator thus has the possibility of controlling the
	  synchronization precisely and only synchronizing selected objects and
	  attributes.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The UCS directory service synchronizes with the Microsoft Active
	  Directory of the parent company. The replication encompasses
	  all the containers, organizational units, users and groups. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  The computer accounts are not synchronized, as Windows computers can
	  only be joined in one domain. All Windows clients are joined in the UCS
	  Samba 4 domain.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:groupware">
	<title>Groupware</title>
	<para>
	  The groupware is provided in the form of Exchange Server
	  2016 by the parent company Vigil Insurances, allowing the users to
	  access it using Outlook and Outlook on the web.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The integration of the UCS directory service and the Active Directory
	  of the parent company allows authentication with the same user name /
	  password.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Users can access the services of both environments in a transparent
	  way, as the same user settings apply in both domains. For example, a
	  user can log into both the UCS directory service on his laptop and
	  the Citrix Server in the Microsoft Active Directory with the same user
	  name and password.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:complianc3">
	<title>Compliance requirements</title>
	<para>
	  HMV must satisfy a range of insurance industry compliance
	  requirements.
	</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <simpara>All LDAP write accesses must be verifiable. This is
		  done by means of the Univention Directory Logger. This
		  transcribes each LDAP change in a secure transaction log
		  file, which is protocoled audit-compliantly with
		  checksums.</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>The user data must be available immediately
		for external audit purposes. To do so, Univention Directory
		Reports can be used to create a PDF document or a CSV file of
		all or some users and groups from the
		&ucsUMC;.</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>Quality standards must be established for
		passwords. In UCS, for example, one can set a minimum number
		of lowercase and uppercase characters, symbols or figures for
		passwords. In addition, passwords can be compared against a
		list of unsafe passwords (e.g.,
		<emphasis>secret</emphasis>).</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:monitoring">
	<title>System monitoring with Nagios</title>
	<para>
	  UCS integrates the system monitoring software Nagios, which allows the
	  monitoring of complex IT structures from networks, computers and
	  services. Nagios includes a comprehensive range of monitoring modules,
	  which can also be expanded if necessary.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The Nagios configuration is predominantly performed in the &ucsUMC;.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A web-based interface can be used to check the status of the monitored
	  objects. In addition, Nagios is configured in such a way that the
	  administrators receive e-mails when errors occur. SMS messages are
	  sent for serious errors.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Nagios checks can be chronologically limited so that non-critical
	  values don't trigger logging messages during the night, for example.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:aix">
	<title>Integration of the AIX system</title>
	<para>
	  The insurance policies are administrated with an application which can
	  only be operated on highly available POWER7 systems using IBM AIX.
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the past, all users working on the system were maintained doubly in
	  the local user database of the AIX system. Now only the <systemitem class="service">secldapclntd</systemitem>
	  service runs on the AIX system; it performs all the authentication
	  processes against the UCS LDAP directory.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:terminal">
	<title>Citrix terminal services</title>
	<para>
	  In the headquarters 150 users work with terminal services based on
	  Citrix XenApp. The XenApp terminal server runs on a Windows member server,
	  which joined the local Samba 4 domain.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:backup">
	<title>Backup</title>
	<para>
      <emphasis>SEP sesam backup server</emphasis> from the App Center is
      used for file backup, which can be installed with a few clicks. It offers
      a distributed backup concept with different backup agents, which backup
      both complete systems and data. Special backup agents are available for
      the backup of databases. All data are copied from the standard servers in
      the headquarters and from there saved on tape media.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:crm">
	<title>Integration of SuiteCRM</title>
	<para>
      <emphasis>SuiteCRM</emphasis> is employed as the CRM solution for sales
      personnel. The administration of the SuiteCRM users and roles integrates
      directly in the &ucsUMC;. The installation can be performed with a few
      clicks using the Univention App Center.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The installation is operated as a &ucsSlave; system on the Amazon EC2
	  cloud. This ensures high availability and allows flexible scaling to
	  growing performance and storage requirements.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="insurance:rev">
	<title>References</title>
	  <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual-4.4.html"/> (UCS manual)</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual-4.4.html#domain-ldap:directorylogger"/> (Audit-proof logging of LDAP changes with Univention Directory Logger)</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual-4.4.html#uvmm:chapter"/></simpara></listitem>
		<listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/installation-4.4.html"/> (Extended installation documentation)</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/opsi/"/> (<application>opsi</application>)</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/sep-sesam/"/> (<application>SEP sesam Backup Server</application>)</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara><ulink url="https://www.univention.com/appid/digitec-suitecrm/"/> (SuiteCRM)</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
