<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	%extensions;
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-en-5.0-1">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>UCS 5.0 Release Notes</title>
		<subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 5.0-1</subtitle>

		<legalnotice lang="">
			<para>
				Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
			</para>

			<para>
				(c) 2002-2021 Univention GmbH
			</para>

			<para>
				Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
			</para>

			<para>
				<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
			</para>

			<para lang="de">
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>

			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
		<title>Release Highlights</title>
		<para>
			With &ucsUCS; 5.0-1, the first point release for &ucsUCS; (UCS) 5.0 is now available.
			It provides several feature improvements and extensions, new properties as well as various improvements and bugfixes.
			Here is an overview of the most important changes:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
					UCS 5 light theme design.
					As announced with the release of UCS 5.0-0, in addition to the dark theme, there is also a light theme for UCS 5.0, allowing users of the UCS management system to switch between the two themes.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Scheduled user account activation.
					UCS administrators can create user accounts and define the date and time when they will be activated.
					User account creation can thus be better scheduled and done in advance without the user accounts being active right away.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Numerous improvements to the UCS Portal.
					Users of the UCS Portal can enjoy numerous improvement.
					Worth mentioning here are:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>
							Improvements in the accessibility of the portal, for example, in the operation with the keyboard.
					</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>
							Improved handling of translation in a separate dialog to <wordasword>declutter</wordasword> the editing dialog.
					</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>
							Improved handling of notifications.
					</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>
							The cookie banner layout has been adapted to match the portal layout.
					</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					App Center:
					Several bugfixes in the handling of app settings.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					User creation wizard: display attributes marked as required.
					UCR variables can be used to configure which user attributes have which default values and are visible when a user account is created.
					This allows an administrator to specify, for example, which parameters must be explicitly set and contain values in any case when creating a user account, e.g. the email address, which is not required by default.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					This &ucsUCS; release is based on Debian 10.11 <wordasword>Buster</wordasword>.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Various security updates have been integrated into UCS 5.0-1, for example for <application>Samba4</application>, OpenSSL, PHP and the Linux kernel.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:update">
		<title>Notes about the update</title>
		<para>
			During the update some services in the domain may not be available temporarily, that is why the update should occur in a maintenance window.
			It is recommended to test the update in a separate test environment prior to the actual update.
			The test environment should be identical to the production environment.
			Depending on the system performance, network connection and the installed software the update will take between 20 minutes and several hours.
			In large environments it may be useful to consult the <biblioref linkend="ucs-performance-guide"/>.
		</para>

		<section id="relnotes:order">
			<title>Recommended update order for environments with more than one UCS server</title>
			<para>
				In environments with more than one UCS system, the update order of the UCS systems must be borne in mind:
			</para>
			<para>
				The authoritative version of the LDAP directory service is maintained on the &ucsPrimaryDN; (formerly referred to as &ucsMaster;) and replicated to all the remaining LDAP servers of the UCS domain.
				As changes to the LDAP schema can occur during release updates, the &ucsPrimaryDN; must always be the first system to be updated during a release update.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:32bit">
			<title>UCS only available for 64 bit</title>
			<para>
				UCS 5 is only provided for the x86 64 bit architecture (amd64).
				Existing 32 bit UCS systems cannot be updated to UCS 5.
			</para>
		</section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:bootloader">
		<title>Simultaneous operation of UCS and Debian on UEFI systems</title>
		<para>
			Please note that simultaneous operation of UCS and Debian on a UEFI system starting with UCS 5.0 is not supported.
		</para>
		<para>
			The reason for this is the GRUB boot loader of &ucsUCS;, which partly uses the same configuration files as Debian.
			An already installed Debian leads to the fact that UCS cannot be booted (any more) after the installation of or an update to UCS 5.0.
			A subsequent installation of Debian will also result in UCS 5.0 not being able to boot.
		</para>
		<para>
			At the following help article further hints to this topic are collected:
			<ulink url="https://help.univention.com/t/17768">https://help.univention.com/t/17768</ulink>
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:localrepo">
		<title>Local package repository</title>
		<para>
			This section is relevant for environments where a <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">local repository</ulink> is set up.
			The installed (major) version of UCS determines which packages a local repository provides.
			A repository running on a UCS server with version 4.x will only provide packages up to UCS 4.x, a repository server running on UCS 5 will only provide packages for UCS 5 and newer versions.
			To upgrade systems to UCS 5 in an environment with a local repository, the following are some of the options.
			First, a local UCS 5 repository server must be set up.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
					A new UCS 5 system is installed as a &ucsPrimaryDN; from the DVD or from a virtualized base image.
					Then <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">a local repository is set up on this system as described in the UCS 5 manual</ulink>.
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
					A new UCS 5 system is installed with the system role &ucsBackupDN;, &ucsReplicaDN; or &ucsManagedNode; from the DVD or from a virtualized base image.
					In system setup, select that the system will not join a domain.
					Then <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">set up a local repository on this system as described in the UCS 5 manual</ulink>.
					After the &ucsPrimaryDN; used in the domain is upgraded to UCS 5, the UCS 5 repository server can join the domain via <command>univention-join</command>.
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			To upgrade a system in the domain to UCS 5, the server should first be upgraded to the latest package level available for UCS 4.x.
			Then the repository server used by the system is switched to the local UCS 5 repository by changing the &ucsUCRV; <envar>repository/online/server</envar>.
			The system can now be upgraded to UCS 5 via the &ucsUMC; or via the command line.
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>
		<para>
			Manually crafted Python code needs to be checked for compatibility with Python 3.7 before the Update and adjusted accordingly.
			This includes &ucsUCR; templates containing Python code.
			Customized AD-Connector mapping templates are an example for this.
			See also the <biblioref linkend="developer-reference"/> for advice.
		</para>
		<para>
			It must be checked whether sufficient disk space is available.
			A standard installation requires a minimum of 6-10 GB of disk space.
			The update requires approximately 1-2 GB additional disk space to download and install the packages, depending on the size of the existing installation.
		</para>
		<para>
			For the update, a login should be performed on the system's local console as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, and the update should be initiated there.
			Alternatively, the update can be conducted using &ucsUMC;.
		</para>
		<para>
			Remote updating via SSH is not recommended as this may result in the update procedure being canceled, e.g., if the network connection is interrupted.
			In consequence, this can affect the system severely.
			If updating should occur over a network connection nevertheless, it must be verified that the update continues in case of disconnection from the network.
			This can be achieved, e.g., using the tools <command>tmux</command>, <command>screen</command> and <command>at</command>.
			These tools are installed on all UCS system roles by default.
		</para>
		<para>
			Univention provides a script that checks for problems which would prevent the successful update of the system.
			Prior to the update, this script can be downloaded and executed on the UCS system.
		</para>
		<screen><![CDATA[
# download
curl -OOf https://updates.software-univention.de/download/univention-update-checks/pre-update-checks-5.0-1{.gpg,}

# verify and run script
apt-key verify pre-update-checks-5.0-1{.gpg,} &&
  bash pre-update-checks-5.0-1

...

Starting pre-update checks ...

Checking app_appliance ...                        OK
Checking block_update_of_NT_DC ...                OK
Checking cyrus_integration ...                    OK
Checking disk_space ...                           OK
Checking hold_packages ...                        OK
Checking ldap_connection ...                      OK
Checking ldap_schema ...                          OK
...
		]]></screen>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:post">
		<title>Postprocessing of the update</title>
		<para>
			Following the update, new or updated join scripts need to be executed.
			This can be done in two ways:
			Either using the UMC module <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> or by running the command <command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Subsequently the UCS system needs to be restarted.
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:packages">
		<title>Notes on selected packages</title>

		<section id="relnotes:network">
			<title>Network configuration</title>
			<para>
				Support for <package>ifplugd</package> has been removed.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:usage">
			<title>Collection of usage statistics</title>
			<para>
				Anonymous usage statistics on the use of &ucsUMC; are collected when using the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis>.
				The modules opened get logged to an instance of the web traffic analysis tool Piwik.
				This makes it possible for Univention to tailor the development of &ucsUMC; better to customer needs and carry out usability improvements.
			</para>
			<para>
				This logging is only performed when the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis> license is used.
				The license status can be verified via the menu entry <guimenu>License &ar; License information</guimenu> of the user menu in the upper right corner of &ucsUMC;.
				If <guimenu>UCS Core Edition</guimenu> is listed under <guimenu>License type</guimenu>, this version is in use.
				When a regular UCS license is used, no usage statistics are collected.
			</para>
			<para>
				Independent of the license used, the statistics generation can be deactivated by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>umc/web/piwik</envar> to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:browsers">
			<title>Recommended browsers for the access to &ucsUMC;</title>
			<para>
				&ucsUMC; uses numerous JavaScript and CSS functions to display the web interface.
				Cookies need to be permitted in the browser.
				The following browsers are recommended:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Chrome as of version 85</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Firefox as of version 78</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Safari and Safari Mobile as of version 13</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Microsoft Edge as of version 88</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				Users running older browsers may experience display or performance issues.
			</para>
		</section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
		<title>Changelog</title>
		<para>
			Listed are the changes since UCS <productnumber>4.4-8</productnumber>:
		</para>
		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-5.0-1.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>

	<bibliography id="bibliography">
		<bibliomixed id="ucs-performance-guide"/>
		<bibliomixed id="developer-reference"/>
	</bibliography>

</book>
<!-- vim:set ft=docbk fdm=syntax fdl=1 ts=2 sw=2 noet: -->
