<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-en-4.4-3">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>UCS 4.4 Release Notes</title>
		<subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 4.4-3</subtitle>

		<legalnotice lang="">
			<para>
				Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
			</para>

			<para>
				(c) 2002-2019 Univention GmbH
			</para>

			<para>
				Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
			</para>

			<para>
				<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
			</para>

			<para lang="de">
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>

			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
		<title>Release Highlights</title>

		<para>
			With &ucsUCS; 4.4-3, the third point release of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 4.4 is now available.
			It provides several feature improvements and extensions, new properties as well as various improvements and bugfixes.
			Here is an overview of the most important changes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
					Several details of the &ucsUMC; have been improved:
					The size of the RAM is now already checked during the installation.
					A new document exists for setting up printer drivers, which is directly linked.
					Searching for IPv4 addresses and the configuration of mail distribution lists has been simplified.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					The &ucsS4C; has received many small improvements, e.g. when renaming host and DNS entries, a fix for account expiry dates in certain time zones, and for exceptional cases when objects are restored in &ucsUAS; environments.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					A crash issue in OpenLDAP and a problem when accessing shares with Windows Explorer has been fixed.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Most packages have been converted from <package>python-support</package> to <package>dh_python2</package> in preparation for the switch from Python 2 to Python 3.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Various security updates have been integrated into UCS 4.4-3, e.g. Samba, the Linux kernel and Dovecot.
					A complete list of security and package updates is available in <xref linkend="relnotes:changelog"/>.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:update">
		<title>Notes about the update</title>
		<para>
			During the update some services in the domain may not be available temporarily, that is why the update should occur in a maintenance window.
			It is recommended to test the update in a separate test environment prior to the actual update.
			The test environment should be identical to the production environment.
			Depending on the system performance, network connection and the installed software the update will take between 20 minutes and several hours.
		</para>

		<section id="relnotes:order">
			<title>Recommended update order for environments with more than one UCS server</title>
			<para>
				In environments with more than one UCS system, the update order of the UCS systems must be borne in mind:
			</para>

			<para>
				The authoritative version of the LDAP directory service is maintained on the &ucsMaster; and replicated to all the remaining LDAP servers of the UCS domain.
				As changes to the LDAP schema can occur during release updates, the &ucsMaster; must always be the first system to be updated during a release update.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:32bit">
			<title>UCS installation DVD only available for 64 bit</title>
			<para>
				Starting with UCS 4.0, installation DVD are only provided for the x86 64 bit architecture (amd64).
				Existing 32 bit UCS 3 systems can still be updated to UCS 4.0 through the online repository or by using update DVD.
				The 32 bit architecture will be supported over the entire UCS 4 maintenance period.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>

		<para>
			It must be checked whether sufficient disk space is available.
			A standard installation requires a minimum of 10 GB of disk space.
			The update requires approximately 4 GB additional disk space to download and install the packages, depending on the size of the existing installation.
		</para>

		<para>
			For the update, a login should be performed on the system's local console as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, and the update should be initiated there.
			Alternatively, the update can be conducted using &ucsUMC;.
		</para>

		<para>
			Remote updating via SSH is not recommended as this may result in the update procedure being canceled, e.g., if the network connection is interrupted.
			In consequence, this can affect the system severely.
			If updating should occur over a network connection nevertheless, it must be verified that the update continues in case of disconnection from the network.
			This can be achieved, e.g., using the tools <command>screen</command> and <command>at</command>.
			These tools are installed on all UCS system roles by default.
		</para>

		<para>
			Univention provides a script that checks for problems which would prevent the successful update of the system.
			Prior to the update, this script can be downloaded and executed on the UCS system.
			<screen><![CDATA[
# download
curl -OOs https://updates.software-univention.de/download/univention-update-checks/pre-update-checks-4.4{,.gpg}

# run script
gpgv --keyring /usr/share/keyrings/univention-archive-key-ucs-4x.gpg \
        pre-update-checks-4.4.gpg pre-update-checks-4.4 && bash pre-update-checks-4.4

...

Starting pre-update checks ...

Checking app_appliance ...                        OK
Checking block_update_of_NT_DC ...                OK
Checking cyrus_integration ...                    OK
Checking disk_space ...                           OK
Checking hold_packages ...                        OK
Checking ldap_connection ...                      OK
Checking ldap_schema ...                          OK
...
			]]></screen>
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:post">
		<title>Postprocessing of the update</title>

		<para>
			Following the update, new or updated join scripts need to be executed.
			This can be done in two ways:
			Either using the UMC module  <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> or by running the command
			<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
		</para>

		<para>
			Subsequently the UCS system needs to be restarted.
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:packages">
		<title>Notes on selected packages</title>

		<section id="relnotes:usage">
			<title>Collection of usage statistics</title>
			<para>
				Anonymous usage statistics on the use of &ucsUMC; are collected when using the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis>.
				The modules opened get logged to an instance of the web traffic analysis tool Piwik.
				This makes it possible for Univention to tailor the development of &ucsUMC; better to customer needs and carry out usability improvements.
			</para>
			<para>
				This logging is only performed when the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis> license is used.
				The license status can be verified via the menu entry <guimenu>License &ar; License information</guimenu> of the user menu in the upper right corner of &ucsUMC;.
				If <guimenu>UCS Core Edition</guimenu> is listed under <guimenu>License type</guimenu>, this version is in use.
				When a regular UCS license is used, no usage statistics are collected.
			</para>
			<para>
				Independent of the license used, the statistics generation can be deactivated by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>umc/web/piwik</envar> to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:secbrowsers">
			<title>Scope of security support for WebKit, Konqueror and QtWebKit</title>
			<para>
				WebKit, Konqueror and QtWebKit are shipped in the maintained branch of the UCS repository, but not covered by security support.
				WebKit is primarily used for displaying HTML help pages etc.
				Firefox should be used as web browser.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:browsers">
			<title>Recommended browsers for the access to &ucsUMC;</title>

			<para>
				&ucsUMC; uses numerous JavaScript and CSS functions to display the web interface.
				Cookies need to be permitted in the browser.
				The following browsers are recommended:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Chrome as of version 71</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Firefox as of version 60</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Safari and Safari Mobile as of version 12</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Microsoft Edge as of version 18</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				As of this release Internet Explorer is not supported by &ucsUMC; anymore.
			</para>
			<para>
				Users running older browsers may experience display or performance issues.
			</para>
		</section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
		<title>Changelog</title>
		<para>
			Listed are the changes since UCS <wordasword>4.4-2</wordasword>:
		</para>

		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-4.4-3.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>
</book>
<!-- vim: set ts=4 sw=4 noet: -->
