<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
  <!ENTITY bibliography SYSTEM "../stylesheets/bibliography-en.xml">
  <!ENTITY changelog SYSTEM "changelog-4.0-1.xml">

  %entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-4.0-1-en">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>UCS 4.0-1 Release Notes</title>
		<subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 4.0-1</subtitle>
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>4.0-1</revnumber>
				<date>January 2015</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>

		<legalnotice>
			<para>
				Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
			</para>

			<para>
				(c) 2002-2015 Univention GmbH
			</para>

			<para>
				Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
			</para>

			<para>
				<ulink url="mailto:feedback@univention.de">feedback@univention.de</ulink>
			</para>

			<para>
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>

			<para>
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
		<title>Release highlights</title>

		<para>
		  With &ucsUCS; 4.0-1, the first point release of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 4.0 is
		  now available.  It provides various improvements and
		  bugfixes. An overview of the most important changes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><para>
			The Debian Wheezy point update 7.8 has been integrated.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			The <emphasis>Free for personal use edition</emphasis> license has been extended to 50 users
			and 50 clients.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			Improvements in the appliance mode allow a simpler system installation and setup of
			cloud instances.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			Joining an Active Directory domain has been simplified.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			Multiple bugfixes and improvements related to Samna, e.g. in the printer support and
			when using  Microsoft Sharepoint.
		  </para></listitem>

		  <listitem><para>
			Several enhancements and bugfixes in design and usability of the &ucsUMC;.
		  </para></listitem>


		</itemizedlist>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:update">
		<title>Notes on the update</title>
		<para>
		  During the update some services in the domain may not be available, i.e. the update should
		  occur in a maintenance window. It is recommended to test the update in a separate test
		  environment prior to the actual update. The test environment should be identical to the
		  production environment. Depending on the system performance, network connection and the
		  installed software the update takes between 20 minutes and several hours.
		</para>

		<section id="relnotes:order">
		  <title>Recommended update order for environments with more than one UCS server</title>
		  <para>
			In environments with more than one UCS system, the update order of the UCS systems must
			be borne in mind:
		  </para>

		  <para>
			The authoritative version of the LDAP directory service is maintained on the &ucsMaster;
			and replicated on all the remaining LDAP servers of the UCS domain. As changes to the
			LDAP schemes can occur during release updates, the &ucsMaster; must always be the first
			system to be updated during a release update.
		  </para>
		</section>

		<!-- <section id="relnotes:apps"> -->
		<!--   <title>Univention App Center</title> -->
		<!--   <para> -->
		<!-- 	If applications have been installed from the Univention App Center, the update can only -->
		<!-- 	be performed once all installed applications are available in a compatible -->
		<!-- 	version. Some applications are updated to newer versions during the update. If an -->
		<!-- 	application is not yet available for UCS 4.0, the release date can be -->
		<!-- 	obtained from the application vendor. -->
		<!--   </para> -->
		<!-- </section> -->

		<section id="relnotes:32bit">
			<title>UCS installation DVDs only available for 64 bit</title>
			<para>
			  Starting with UCS 4.0 UCS, installation DVDs are only provided for the x86 64 bit
			  architecture (amd64). Existing 32 bit UCS 3 systems can still be updated to UCS 4.0 through the
			  online repository or by using update DVDs. The 32 bit architectur will be supported
			  over the entire UCS 4 maintenance.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>

		<para>
		  It must be checked whether sufficient disk space is available. A standard installation
		  requires a minimum of 6 GB of disk space. Depending on the scope of the existing installation,
		  the update will require about another 2 GB of disk space for downloading and
		  installing all packages.
		</para>

		<para>
		  For the update, a login should be performed on the system's local console as user
		  <emphasis>root</emphasis>, and the update should be initiated there. Alternatively, the
		  update can be conducted using &ucsUMC;.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Remote updating via SSH is not recommended as this may result in the update procedure
		  being cancelled, e.g., if the network connection is interrupted. In consequence, this can affect
		  the system severely. If updating should occur over a network connection nevertheless, it must be
		  verified that the update continues despite disconnection from the network. This can be
		  done, e.g., using the tools <command>screen</command> and <command>at</command>.
		  These tools are installed on all system roles by default.
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:post">
		<title>Postprocessing of the update</title>

		<para>
		  Following the update, new or updated join scripts need to be executed. This can be done in
		  two ways: Either using the UMC module  <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> or by running the
		  command <command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> as user
		  <emphasis>root</emphasis>.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The configuration of the UCS DNS name server BIND was prone to open resolver attacks,
		  which are used to launch Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attacks against other hosts
		  of the internet. To prevent such abuse the default configuration will be changed to allow
		  'recursive queries' only from IP addresses of the private address ranges, link-local
		  address ranges, localhost and local networks. If the name servers need to be queried from
		  any other hosts outside those network, they must be configured using the Univention
		  Configuration Registry variable 'dns/allow/query/cache'. This change gets only applied for
		  newly installed domain controllers. See <ulink url="http://sdb.univention.de/1298"/> for
		  additional details to convert existing installations.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Subsequently the UCS system needs to be restarted.
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:packages">
	  <title>Further notes on selected packages</title>

	  <section id="relnotes:instprofil">
		<title>Network-based installation of UCS</title>
		<para>
		  The profile-based UCS network installation is not yet available in UCS 4.0-1. It will be
		  provided at a later date. Please refer to our issue tracker for further details:
		  <ulink url="&ucsbug;35537">Bug 35537</ulink>.
		</para>
	  </section>

	  <section id="relnotes:usage">
		<title>Collection of usage statistics</title>
		<para>
		  Anonymous usage statistics on the use of &ucsUMC; are collected when using the <emphasis>free for
		  personal use</emphasis> version of UCS (which is generally used for evaluating UCS). The modules
		  opened are logged in an instance of the web traffic analysis tool Piwik. This makes it
		  possible for Univention to tailor the development of &ucsUMC; better to customer needs
		  and carry out usability improvements.
		</para>
		<para>
		  This logging is only performed when the <emphasis>free-for-personal-use
		  license</emphasis> is used. The license status can be verified via the
		  menu entry <guimenu>License &ar; License information</guimenu> of the user
		  menu in the upper right corner of &ucsUMC;.  If <guimenu>Free for personal
		  use edition</guimenu> is listed under <guimenu>LDAP base</guimenu>,
		  this version is in use. When a regular UCS license is used, no usage
		  statistics are collected.
		</para>
		<para>
		  Independent of the license used, the statistics generation can be deactivated by setting the
		  &ucsUCRV; <envar>umc/web/piwik</envar> to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
		</para>
	  </section>

	  <section id="relnotes:secbrowsers">
		<title>Scope of security support for Webkit, Konqueror und QtWebKit</title>
		<para>
		  Webkit, Konqueror and QtWebkit are shipped in the maintained branch of the UCS repository,
		  but not covered with security support. Webkit is primarily used for displaying HTML help
		  pages etc. Firefox should be used as web browser.
		</para>

	  </section>

	  <section id="relnotes:browsers">
		<title>Recommeded browsers for the access to Univention Management Console</title>

		<para>
		  &ucsUMC; uses numerous Javascript and CSS functions to display the web interface. Cookies
		  need to be permitted in the browser. The following browsers are recommended:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
			<para>Chrome as of version 33</para>
		  </listitem>

		  <listitem>
			<para>Firefox as of version 24</para>
		  </listitem>
		  
		  <listitem>
			<para>Internet Explorer as of version 9</para>
		  </listitem>
		  
		  <listitem>
			<para>Safari and Safari Mobile as of version 7</para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>
		  Users with older browsers may experience display or performance problems.
		</para>
	  </section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
		<title>Changelog</title>
		<para>
		  Listed are the changes since UCS 4.0-0:
		</para>

		&changelog;
	</chapter>

	<bibliography id="relnotes:bibliography">
		<bibliomixed id="ucs-handbuch"/>
		<bibliomixed id="ext-doc-uvmm"/>
		<bibliomixed id="ucs-uvmm-profile"/>
		<bibliomixed id="ucs-performance-guide"/>
	</bibliography>

	<?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwik.html"?>
</book>
