<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-4.3-0-en">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>UCS 4.3 Release Notes</title>
		<subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 4.3</subtitle>

		<legalnotice lang="">
			<para>
				Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
			</para>

			<para>
				(c) 2002-2018 Univention GmbH
			</para>

			<para>
				Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
			</para>

			<para>
				<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
			</para>

			<para lang="de">
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>

			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
		<title>Release Highlights</title>

		<para>
			With Univention Corporate Server 4.3, the third minor release of Univention Corporate Server (UCS) 4 is now
			available. It provides several feature improvements and extensions, new properties as well as
			various improvements and bugfixes. Here is an overview of the most important changes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
				UCS 4.3 is based on Debian GNU/Linux 9 (Stretch). More than 20,000 source packages have
				been updated and and some have been adapted to the needs of UCS users. The Linux kernel of Debian GNU/Linux is
				now used unmodified. This greatly improves compatability to hardware and software which has been certified for
				Debian 9. Also new in UCS 4.3 are e.g. MariaDB and Nagios 4.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
				The portal pages introduced with the UCS 4.2 give users a simple way to access applications relevant to them. With UCS 4.3,
				administrators can easily build and manage these portals in visual composer mode and via drag and drop.
				It is now also possible to show different content to different users, depending on their group membership, permissions,
				department, branch or school.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
 				With UCS 4.3, SAML authentication is linked to the Kerberos login. Users logged in to Windows or
				Linux (Ubuntu) can access Web applications that support SAML without reauthentication.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
				The different account types for users have been simplified. There are now three different account types with UCS 4.3:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem><para>
						Normal accounts containing all features.
					</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						Simple authentication accounts, these can only connect to LDAP servers, but have no possibility to log in elsewhere.
					</para></listitem>
					<listitem><para>
						Address book entries for maintaining contact information.
					</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
				Samba has been updated to version 4.7. This new Samba release contains important enhancements to the Active Directory
				domain controller. For example, the multi process implementation of the Samba LDAP server will significantly improve
				performance. Additionally, replicating group memberships now uses significantly fewer resources.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:update">
		<title>Notes about the update</title>
		<para>
			During the update some services in the domain may not be available temporarily, that is why the update should occur in a maintenance window.
			It is recommended to test the update in a separate test environment prior to the actual update.
			The test environment should be identical to the production environment.
			Depending on the system performance, network connection and the installed software the update will take between 20 minutes and several hours.
		</para>

		<section id="relnotes:order">
			<title>Recommended update order for environments with more than one UCS server</title>
			<para>
				In environments with more than one UCS system, the update order of the UCS systems must be borne in mind:
			</para>

			<para>
				The authoritative version of the LDAP directory service is maintained on the &ucsMaster; and replicated to all the remaining LDAP servers of the UCS domain.
				As changes to the LDAP schema can occur during release updates, the &ucsMaster; must always be the first system to be updated during a release update.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:32bit">
			<title>UCS installation DVD only available for 64 bit</title>
			<para>
				Starting with UCS 4.0, installation DVD are only provided for the x86 64 bit architecture (amd64).
				Existing 32 bit UCS 3 systems can still be updated to UCS 4.0 through the online repository or by using update DVD.
				The 32 bit architecture will be supported over the entire UCS 4 maintenance period.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>

		<para>
			It must be checked whether sufficient disk space is available.
			A standard installation requires a minimum of 6 GB of disk space.
			Depending on the scope of the existing installation, the update will require about another 2 GB of disk space for download and installation all packages.
		</para>

		<para>
			For the update, a login should be performed on the system's local console as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, and the update should be initiated there.
			Alternatively, the update can be conducted using &ucsUMC;.
		</para>

		<para>
			Remote updating via SSH is not recommended as this may result in the update procedure being canceled, e.g., if the network connection is interrupted.
			In consequence, this can affect the system severely.
			If updating should occur over a network connection nevertheless, it must be verified that the update continues in case of disconnection from the network.
			This can be achieved, e.g., using the tools <command>screen</command> and <command>at</command>.  These tools are installed on all UCS system roles by default.
		</para>

		<para>
			With UCS 4.3, Univention provides a script that checks for problems which would prevent the successful update of the system. Prior to the update, this script
			can be downloaded and executed on the UCS system.
			<screen><![CDATA[
# download
-> curl -OOs http://updates.software-univention.de/download/univention-update-checks/pre-update-checks-4.3{,.gpg}

# run script
-> gpgv --keyring /usr/share/keyrings/univention-archive-key-ucs-4x.gpg pre-update-checks-4.3.gpg pre-update-checks-4.3 && bash pre-update-checks-4.3

gpgv: Signature made Wed Mar  7 12:09:25 2018 CET using RSA key ID 6B8BFD3C
gpgv: Good signature from "Univention Corporate Server 4.x <packages@univention.de>"

Starting pre-update checks (Di 6. Mär 13:07:33 CET 2018):

Checking app_appliance ...                        OK
Checking block_update_of_NT_DC ...                OK
Checking cyrus_integration ...                    OK
Checking disk_space ...                           OK
Checking hold_packages ...                        OK
Checking ldap_connection ...                      OK
Checking ldap_schema ...                          OK
...
			]]></screen>
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:post">
		<title>Postprocessing of the update</title>

		<para>
			Following the update, new or updated join scripts need to be executed.
			This can be done in two ways:
			Either using the UMC module  <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> or by running the command
			<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
		</para>

		<para>
			Subsequently the UCS system needs to be restarted.
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:packages">
		<title>Further notes on selected packages</title>

		<section id="relnotes:mariadb">
			<title>MariaDB replaces MySQL</title>
			<para>
				UCS 4.3 replaces MySQL with MariaDB.
				The new package <package>univention-mariadb</package> provides the integration into UCS.
				The package <package>univention-mysql</package> is now a meta package and installs <package>univention-mariadb</package>.
				Existing data is migrated without user interaction when updating to UCS 4.3.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:mariadb">
			<title>Unification of user options</title>
			<para>
				Previously, UMC administrators could assign certain properties to users. That were e.g. Samba, Kerberos, POSIX and Mail.
				With UCS 4.3, the existing users will be migrated into three different user types:
                 1. Normal full-fledged users, these have all the features.
                 2. Simple authentication accounts, these can only connect to LDAP, but can't log in elsewhere.
                 3. Address book entries, internal or external identities can be maintained here, e.g. to create address lists.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:cyrus">
			<title>Cyrus IMAPd</title>
			<para>
				The integration of the Cyrus IMAP and POP3 server has been removed from UCS.
				The integration of Dovecot will be the only one supported from UCS 4.3 on.
				If you are using Cyrus on UCS 4.2 and wish to upgrade to UCS 4.3, please refer to the article <ulink url="https://help.univention.com/t/7957" />.
				The article includes a link to instructions for migrating from Cyrus to Dovecot.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:nt">
			<title>Samba as Windows NT DC</title>
			<para>
				Support for <literal>NT style domain control</literal> has been removed from UCS 4.3. The update for
				these domains is blocked and the domain needs to be migrated to <literal>Samba/AD</literal>
				following the update guide <ulink url="https://wiki.univention.de/index.php/Migration_from_Samba_3_to_Samba_4">Migration from Samba 3 to Samba 4</ulink>.
				See also <ulink url="https://wiki.univention.de/index.php/Best_Practice_Samba_4_Migration">Best practices for Samba 4 Migration</ulink> .
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:usage">
			<title>Collection of usage statistics</title>
			<para>
				Anonymous usage statistics on the use of &ucsUMC; are collected when using the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis>.
				The modules opened are logged in an instance of the web traffic analysis tool Piwik.
				This makes it possible for Univention to tailor the development of &ucsUMC; better to customer needs and carry out usability improvements.
			</para>
			<para>
				This logging is only performed when the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis> license is used.
				The license status can be verified via the menu entry <guimenu>License &ar; License information</guimenu> of the user menu in the upper right corner of &ucsUMC;.
				If <guimenu>UCS Core Edition</guimenu> is listed under <guimenu>License type</guimenu>, this version is in use.
				When a regular UCS license is used, no usage statistics are collected.
			</para>
			<para>
				Independent of the license used, the statistics generation can be deactivated by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>umc/web/piwik</envar> to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:secbrowsers">
			<title>Scope of security support for WebKit, Konqueror and QtWebKit</title>
			<para>
				WebKit, Konqueror and QtWebKit are shipped in the maintained branch of the UCS repository, but not covered by security support.
				WebKit is primarily used for displaying HTML help pages etc.
				Firefox should be used as web browser.
			</para>

		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:browsers">
			<title>Recommended browsers for the access to Univention Management Console</title>

			<para>
				&ucsUMC; uses numerous JavaScript and CSS functions to display the web interface.
				Cookies need to be permitted in the browser.
				The following browsers are recommended:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Chrome as of version 37</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Firefox as of version 38</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Internet Explorer as of version 11</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Safari and Safari Mobile as of version 9</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				Users with older browsers may experience display or performance issues.
			</para>
		</section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
		<title>Changelog</title>
		<para>
			Listed are the changes since UCS <wordasword>4.2-3</wordasword>:
		</para>

		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-4.3-0.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>
</book>
<!-- vim: set ts=4 sw=4 noet: -->
