<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-en-5.0-0">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>UCS 5.0 Release Notes</title>
		<subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 5.0-0</subtitle>

		<legalnotice lang="">
			<para>
				Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
			</para>

			<para>
				(c) 2002-2021 Univention GmbH
			</para>

			<para>
				Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
			</para>

			<para>
				<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
			</para>

			<para lang="de">
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>

			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
		<title>Release Highlights</title>

		<para>
			With &ucsUCS; 5.0-0, the fifth major release of &ucsUCS; (UCS) is now available.
			It provides several feature improvements and extensions, new properties as well as various improvements and bugfixes.
			Here is an overview of the most important changes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
					UCS 5 is based on Debian 10 Buster.
					Only architecture amd64 is supported.
					Architecture i386 is no longer supported.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					In the area of cryptography this raises the minimal TLS protocol version to 1.2.
					For <literal>OpenSSL</literal> this is enforced by the parameter <literal>MinProtocol</literal>
					in <filename>/etc/ssl/openssl.cnf</filename>. As a consequence, TLS connections to external systems
					should be checked for TLS 1.2 support before updating to UCS 5.0, as they are likely to fail after
					the update.
					This affects AD-Connector setups synchronizing UCS with Microsoft Server versions older than
					<literal>2012R2</literal>, if they are configured to use an encrypted connection.
					Additionally the OpenSSL default <literal>CipherString</literal> configuration is <literal>DEFAULT@SECLEVEL=2</literal>
					in UCS 5.0.
					This additionally restricts the available ciphers for communication, which rules out <literal>SHA1</literal> in particular.
					E.g. Windows Server 2012 supports less ciphers that Windows Server 2012R2 by default.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Many components of UCS have already been converted to run with Python 3.7.
					Python 2.7 is still supported with UCS 5.0, but will be removed with UCS 5.1.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Several components haven been removed: &ucsUVMM;, Nagios, Desktop, …
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					System roles have been renamed: Master → Primary, Backup → …, Slave → ...
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					FIXME
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:update">
		<title>Notes about the update</title>
		<para>
			During the update some services in the domain may not be available temporarily, that is why the update should occur in a maintenance window.
			It is recommended to test the update in a separate test environment prior to the actual update.
			The test environment should be identical to the production environment.
			Depending on the system performance, network connection and the installed software the update will take between 20 minutes and several hours.
		</para>

		<section id="relnotes:order">
			<title>Recommended update order for environments with more than one UCS server</title>
			<para>
				In environments with more than one UCS system, the update order of the UCS systems must be borne in mind:
			</para>

			<para>
				The authoritative version of the LDAP directory service is maintained on the &ucsPrimaryDN; (formerly referred to as &ucsMaster;) and replicated to all the remaining LDAP servers of the UCS domain.
				As changes to the LDAP schema can occur during release updates, the &ucsPrimaryDN; must always be the first system to be updated during a release update.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:32bit">
			<title>UCS only available for 64 bit</title>
			<para>
				UCS 5 is only provided for the x86 64 bit architecture (amd64).
				Existing 32 bit UCS 3 systems cannot be updated to UCS 5.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:removals">
			<title>Component removals</title>
			<para>
				For UCS 5 several integration packages have been removed.
			</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>&ucsUVMM;</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kvm-virtio</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-novnc</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-virtual-machine-manager-daemon</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-virtual-machine-manager-node</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-virtual-machine-manager-schema</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							UCS 5 no longer contains the graphical user interface for running virtual machines, but UCS still can be run virtualized on multiple hypervisors.
							The Debian packages <package>libvirt</package> and <package>qemu</package> are still available.
							The update to UCS 5 is blocked until the integration packages are removed.
							All entries in LDAP for <classname>uvmm/profile</classname> and <classname>uvmm/info</classname> should be removed.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Bacula</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-bacula</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration for Bacula backup has been removed.
							Bacula and Bareos are both still available as Debian packages and also from the App Center.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><package>src:univention-doc</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The Python API documentation is now available <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/ucs-python-api/">online</ulink>.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>MRTG</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-mrtg</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							MRTG has been removed.
							For a replacement a similar function is provided by the UCS Dashboard app.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><package>src:univention-java</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package has been removed.
							The Debian provided OpenJDK can still be used and installed via the packages <package>default-jdk</package> or <package>default-jre</package>.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>KDE</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kde</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package for the graphical K Desktop Environment (KDE) has been removed.
							The Debian provided packages are still available.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><package>src:univention-ftp</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package for FTP has been removed.
							The Debian provided packages for <application>ProFTPd</application> and other FTP servers are still available.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>MySQL</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-mysql</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package for MySQL has been removed.
							Support is provided for MariaDB instead.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>PyKota</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-printserver-quota</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Support for the printer quota system PyKota has been removed as the important is no longer maintained upstream.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>DansGuardian</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-dansguardian</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Support for the Content filter DansGuardian has been removed as the implementation is no longer maintained upstream.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Samba 4 WINS</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-samba4wins</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Windows NT support has been removed from the Samba.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Linux Kernel</term>
					<term>GRUB</term>
					<term>SHIM</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kernel-image</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kernel-image-signed</package></term>
					<term><package>src:shim-signed</package></term>
					<term><package>src:grub-efi-amd64-signed</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Support for UEFI Secure Boot is already provided by Debian.
							The UCS specific packages have been removed.
							The latest Linux kernel is pulled in via the package <package>linux-image-amd64</package>.
							The header files of the latest Linux kernel can be pulled in via the package <package>linux-headers-amd64</package>.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:ubuntuclient">
			<!-- Bug 53025 -->
			<title>Notes about the Univention Domain Join Assistant for Ubuntu clients</title>
			<para>
				Univention provides the Univention Domain Join Assistant for integrating Ubuntu clients into a UCS domain.
				At the time of UCS 5.0-0 release, the Domain Join Assistant is not yet compatible with UCS 5 and joining of clients will fail.
				This issue will be fixed as part of a UCS 5 errata or via an update for the Univention Domain Join Assistant.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:joinscript-password">
			<!-- Bug 31996 -->
			<title>Notes about credentials passed to join scripts</title>
			<para>
				Join scripts are now always executed with the safe option <option>--bindpwdfile</option> instead of passing the credentials directly.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:bootloader">
        <title>Simultaneous operation of UCS and Debian on UEFI systems</title>
		<para>
			Please note that simultaneous operation of UCS and Debian on a UEFI system starting with UCS 5.0-0 is not supported.
		</para>
		<para>
			The reason for this is the GRUB boot loader of &ucsUCS;, which partly uses the same configuration files as Debian.
			An already installed Debian leads to the fact that UCS cannot be booted (any more) after the installation of or an update to UCS 5.0.
			A subsequent installation of Debian will also result in UCS 5.0 not being able to boot.
		</para>
		<para>
			At the following help article further hints to this topic are collected:
			<ulink url="https://help.univention.com/t/17768">https://help.univention.com/t/17768</ulink>
		</para>
	</chapter>

	 <chapter id="relnotes:localrepo">
        <title>Local package repository</title>

        <para>
            This section is relevant for environments where a <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-4.4.html#software::createrepo">local repository</ulink> is set up.
            The installed (major) version of UCS determines which packages a local repository provides.
			A repository running on a UCS server with version 4.x will only provide packages up to UCS 4.x, a repository server running on UCS 5 will only provide packages for UCS 5 and newer versions.
			To upgrade systems to UCS 5 in an environment with a local repository, the following are some of the options.
            First, a local UCS 5 repository server must be set up.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
					<para>
						A new UCS 5 system is installed as a &ucsPrimaryDN; from the DVD or from a virtualized base image.
						Then <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">a local repository is set up on this system as described in the UCS 5 manual</ulink>.
					</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
					<para>
						A new UCS 5 system is installed with the system role &ucsBackupDN;, &ucsReplicaDN; or &ucsManagedNode; from the DVD or from a virtualized base image.
						In system setup, select that the system will not join a domain.
						Then <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">set up a local repository on this system as described in the UCS 5 manual</ulink>.
						After the &ucsPrimaryDN; used in the domain is upgraded to UCS 5, the UCS 5 repository server can join the domain via <command>univention-join</command>.
					</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            To upgrade a system in the domain to UCS 5, the server should first be upgraded to the latest package level available for UCS 4.x.
            Then the repository server used by the system is switched to the local UCS 5 repository by changing the &ucsUCRV; <envar>repository/online/server</envar>.
            The system can now be upgraded to UCS 5 via the &ucsUMC; or via the command line.
        </para>
    </chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>

		<para>
			Manually adjusted Python code needs to be checked for compatibility with Python 3.7 before the Update and adjusted accordingly.
			This includes &ucsUCR; templates containing Python code. Customized AD-Connector mapping templates are an example for this.
			See also https://docs.software-univention.de/developer-reference-4.4.html for advice.
		</para>
		<para>
			It must be checked whether sufficient disk space is available.
			A standard installation requires a minimum of FIXME GB of disk space.
			The update requires approximately FIXME GB additional disk space to download and install the packages, depending on the size of the existing installation.
		</para>

		<para>
			For the update, a login should be performed on the system's local console as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, and the update should be initiated there.
			Alternatively, the update can be conducted using &ucsUMC;.
		</para>

		<para>
			Remote updating via SSH is not recommended as this may result in the update procedure being canceled, e.g., if the network connection is interrupted.
			In consequence, this can affect the system severely.
			If updating should occur over a network connection nevertheless, it must be verified that the update continues in case of disconnection from the network.
			This can be achieved, e.g., using the tools <command>screen</command> and <command>at</command>.
			These tools are installed on all UCS system roles by default.
		</para>

		<para>
			Univention provides a script that checks for problems which would prevent the successful update of the system.
			Prior to the update, this script can be downloaded and executed on the UCS system.
			<screen><![CDATA[
# download
curl -OOs https://updates.software-univention.de/download/univention-update-checks/pre-update-checks-5.0-0{,.gpg}

# run script
gpgv --keyring /usr/share/keyrings/univention-archive-key-ucs-5x.gpg pre-update-checks-5.0-0.gpg \
        pre-update-checks-5.0-0 && bash pre-update-checks-5.0-0

...

Starting pre-update checks ...

Checking app_appliance ...                        OK
Checking block_update_of_NT_DC ...                OK
Checking cyrus_integration ...                    OK
Checking disk_space ...                           OK
Checking hold_packages ...                        OK
Checking ldap_connection ...                      OK
Checking ldap_schema ...                          OK
...
			]]></screen>
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:post">
		<title>Postprocessing of the update</title>

		<para>
			Following the update, new or updated join scripts need to be executed.
			This can be done in two ways:
			Either using the UMC module  <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> or by running the command
			<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
		</para>

		<para>
			Subsequently the UCS system needs to be restarted.
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:packages">
		<title>Notes on selected packages</title>

		<section id="relnotes:network">
			<title>Network configuration</title>
			<para>
				Support for <package>ifplugd</package> has been removed.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:usage">
			<title>Collection of usage statistics</title>
			<para>
				Anonymous usage statistics on the use of &ucsUMC; are collected when using the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis>.
				The modules opened get logged to an instance of the web traffic analysis tool Piwik.
				This makes it possible for Univention to tailor the development of &ucsUMC; better to customer needs and carry out usability improvements.
			</para>
			<para>
				This logging is only performed when the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis> license is used.
				The license status can be verified via the menu entry <guimenu>License &ar; License information</guimenu> of the user menu in the upper right corner of &ucsUMC;.
				If <guimenu>UCS Core Edition</guimenu> is listed under <guimenu>License type</guimenu>, this version is in use.
				When a regular UCS license is used, no usage statistics are collected.
			</para>
			<para>
				Independent of the license used, the statistics generation can be deactivated by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>umc/web/piwik</envar> to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:secbrowsers">
			<title>Scope of security support for WebKit, Konqueror and QtWebKit</title>
			<para>
				WebKit, Konqueror and QtWebKit are shipped in the maintained branch of the UCS repository, but not covered by security support.
				WebKit is primarily used for displaying HTML help pages etc.
				Firefox should be used as web browser.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:browsers">
			<title>Recommended browsers for the access to &ucsUMC;</title>

			<para>
				&ucsUMC; uses numerous JavaScript and CSS functions to display the web interface.
				Cookies need to be permitted in the browser.
				The following browsers are recommended:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Chrome as of version FIXME</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Firefox as of version FIXME</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Safari and Safari Mobile as of version FIXME</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Microsoft Edge as of version FIXME</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				Users running older browsers may experience display or performance issues.
			</para>
		</section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
		<title>Changelog</title>
		<para>
			Listed are the changes since UCS <wordasword>4.4-8</wordasword>:
		</para>

		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-5.0-0.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>
</book>
<!-- vim: set ts=4 sw=4 noet: -->
