<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="releasenotes-en-5.0-0">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>UCS 5.0 Release Notes</title>
		<subtitle>Release notes for the installation and update of &ucsUCS; (UCS) 5.0-0</subtitle>

		<legalnotice lang="">
			<para>
				Alle Rechte vorbehalten. / All rights reserved.
			</para>

			<para>
				(c) 2002-2021 Univention GmbH
			</para>

			<para>
				Mary-Somerville-Straße 1, 28359 Bremen, Deutschland/Germany
			</para>

			<para>
				<email>feedback@univention.de</email>
			</para>

			<para lang="de">
				Jede aufgeführte Marke und jedes Warenzeichen steht im Eigentum ihrer jeweiligen eingetragenen Rechtsinhaber.
				Linux ist ein eingetragenes Warenzeichen von Linus Torvalds.
			</para>

			<para lang="en">
				The mentioned brand names and registered trademarks are owned by the respective legal owners in each case.
				Linux is a registered trademark of Linus Torvalds.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="relnotes:highlights">
		<title>Release Highlights</title>

		<para>
			With &ucsUCS; 5.0-0, the fifth major release of &ucsUCS; (UCS) is now available.
			It provides several feature improvements and extensions, new properties as well as various improvements and bugfixes.
			Here is an overview of the most important changes:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>
					This new major &ucsUCS; release is based on Debian 10.9 <wordasword>Buster</wordasword>.
					A lot of packages have been updated from upstream.
					This includes for example the Linux Kernel (4.19), PostgreSQL (11), Python 3 (3.7) and Samba (4.13.7).
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					The portal has been updated to become the central hub for &ucsUCS; users.
					Apps and web pages can be opened as inline frames (<literal>iframe</literal>) within the portal.
					This enables users to quickly open and switch apps.
					Organizations are given the ability to strengthen their identity by having their apps on a central page.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					With Python as the language of choice for many &ucsUCS; components, most have been converted to run with Python 3.7.
					Python 2.7 is still supported with UCS 5.0, but will be removed with UCS 5.1.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					The &ucsUMC; now uses a dark colored theme.
					A light colored theme will be added as an update at a later date.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					The system roles have been renamed.
					"&ucsMaster;" is renamed to "&ucsPrimaryDN;", "&ucsBackup;" to "&ucsBackupDN;", "&ucsSlave;" to "&ucsReplicaDN;" and "&ucsMember;" to "&ucsManagedNode;".
					This is an ongoing process, in this release the documentation and <literal>UI</literal> texts have been adjusted.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Software installation is now done exclusively via the App Center.
					The Software Selection during the initial Configuration of a &ucsUCS; node has been removed.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Multiple apps can now be installed in a single step which simplifies app management.
					Dependencies between apps will now be be automatically resolved by installing multiple apps if necessary.
					The functionality to install multiple apps at once through the App Center replaces the Software Selection during the setup process.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					To determine if a &ucsUCS; is ready to upgrade from 4.4 to 5.0 can be checked by using this <ulink url="https://updates.software-univention.de/download/univention-update-checks/pre-update-checks-5.0-0">script</ulink>.
					<package>univention-upgrade</package> will not proceed with the upgrade if these checks are not successful.
					See also <xref linkend="relnotes:prepare"/> for a more in depth manual about the preparation for the upgrade.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					The &ucsUCS; package sources have been reduced to a fixed number of two, one for the release and one for errata updates.
					This speeds up updating the <package>apt</package> package meta data cache especially for upcoming UCS 5 releases.
					Due to some necessary changes on the Univention repository server, a local UCS 4.x repository will not be able to serve UCS 5.x packages, please check <xref linkend="relnotes:localrepo"/>.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					&ucsUCRV;s can now have a default value which is returned if the variable is unset.
					Please note that not all packages have been updated to use this feature and still define default values in templates.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					The Linux Kernel, including the signed version for UEFI secure boot, shipped with &ucsUCS; 5 is now identical with the Kernel in Debian.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					A new welcome module has been added to the &ucsUMC; to guide administrators through the first steps of using &ucsUCS; like requesting a license or installing apps.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					For easier and a more uniform service management the services <systemitem class="service">&ucsUDL;</systemitem>, <systemitem class="service">&ucsUDN;</systemitem> and <systemitem class="service">univention-dhcp</systemitem> have been converted from <package>runit</package> services to native <package>systemd</package> services.
			</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					A thorough list of changes and fixes included in this release can be found in <xref linkend="relnotes:changelog"/> at the end of this document.
			</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:update">
		<title>Notes about the update</title>
		<para>
			Prerequisite for updating is at least UCS <productnumber>4.4-8</productnumber> with <u:erratum release="4.4-8">972</u:erratum>.
			Only then the available update will be shown.
			Is is recommended to install all other pending errata too before the update is started.
		</para>
		<para>
			If the update is started via &ucsUMC;:
			Before the actual update starts, some tests are performed, e.g. if all installed Apps would be available on UCS <productnumber>5.0</productnumber>.
			At this point, the web interface is already in maintenance mode and nothing is shown but a progress bar.
			If one test fails, the update will be canceled and a message is written to <filename>/var/log/univention/updater.log</filename>.
			To read these in the web frontend, log in to &ucsUMC;, open the <guimenu>Software update</guimenu> module and click on "View log file".
		</para>
		<para>
			During the update some services in the domain may not be available temporarily, that is why the update should occur in a maintenance window.
			It is recommended to test the update in a separate test environment prior to the actual update.
			The test environment should be identical to the production environment.
			Depending on the system performance, network connection and the installed software the update will take between 20 minutes and several hours.
			In large environments it may be useful to consult the <biblioref linkend="ucs-performance-guide"/>.
		</para>

		<section id="relnotes:order">
			<title>Recommended update order for environments with more than one UCS server</title>
			<para>
				In environments with more than one UCS system, the update order of the UCS systems must be borne in mind:
			</para>

			<para>
				The authoritative version of the LDAP directory service is maintained on the &ucsPrimaryDN; (formerly referred to as &ucsMaster;) and replicated to all the remaining LDAP servers of the UCS domain.
				As changes to the LDAP schema can occur during release updates, the &ucsPrimaryDN; must always be the first system to be updated during a release update.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:32bit">
			<title>UCS only available for 64 bit</title>
			<para>
				UCS 5 is only provided for the x86 64 bit architecture (amd64).
				Existing 32 bit UCS systems cannot be updated to UCS 5.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:removals">

			<title>Component removals</title>
			<para>
				For UCS 5 several integration packages have been removed.
			</para>

			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>&ucsUVMM;</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kvm-virtio</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-novnc</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-virtual-machine-manager-daemon</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-virtual-machine-manager-node</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-virtual-machine-manager-schema</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							UCS 5 no longer contains the graphical user interface for running virtual machines,
							but UCS can still run KVM virtualized guests
							and UCS can still be run virtualized on multiple hypervisors.
							The Debian packages <package>libvirt</package> and <package>qemu</package> are still available.
							The update to UCS 5 is blocked until the integration packages are removed.
							All LDAP objects with <literal>univentionObjectType</literal> of type <classname>uvmm/profile</classname> and <classname>uvmm/info</classname> should be removed.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Bacula</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-bacula</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The direct integration for Bacula backup has been removed.
							Bacula and Bareos are both still available as Debian packages and also from the App Center.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><package>src:univention-doc</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The Python API documentation is now available <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/ucs-python-api/">online</ulink>.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>MRTG</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-mrtg</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							MRTG has been removed.
							For a replacement a similar function is provided by the UCS Dashboard app.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><package>src:univention-java</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package has been removed.
							The Debian provided OpenJDK can still be used and installed via the packages <package>default-jre</package> or <package>default-jdk</package>.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>KDE</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kde</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package for the graphical K Desktop Environment (KDE) has been removed.
							The Debian provided packages are still available.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term><package>src:univention-ftp</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package for FTP has been removed.
							The Debian provided packages for <application>ProFTPd</application> and other FTP servers are still available.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>MySQL</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-mysql</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							The integration package for MySQL has been removed.
							Support is provided for MariaDB instead.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>PyKota</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-printserver-quota</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Support for the printer quota system PyKota has been removed as it is no longer maintained upstream.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>DansGuardian</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-dansguardian</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Support for the Content filter DansGuardian has been removed as the implementation is no longer maintained upstream.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Samba 4 WINS</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-samba4wins</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Windows NT support has been removed from the Samba.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Linux Kernel</term>
					<term>GRUB</term>
					<term>SHIM</term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kernel-image</package></term>
					<term><package>src:univention-kernel-image-signed</package></term>
					<term><package>src:shim-signed</package></term>
					<term><package>src:grub-efi-amd64-signed</package></term>
					<listitem>
						<simpara>
							Support for UEFI Secure Boot is already provided by Debian itself.
							The UCS specific packages have been removed.
							The latest Linux kernel for Debian is pulled in via the package <package>linux-image-amd64</package>.
							The header files of the latest Linux kernel can be pulled in via the package <package>linux-headers-amd64</package>.
						</simpara>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:tls">
			<title>Increased minimal TLS protocol version</title>
			<para>
				In the area of cryptography the minimal TLS protocol version has been raised to 1.2.
				For <literal>OpenSSL</literal> this is enforced by the parameter <literal>MinProtocol</literal> in <filename>/etc/ssl/openssl.cnf</filename>.
				As a consequence, TLS connections to external systems should be checked for TLS 1.2 support before updating to UCS 5.0, as they are likely to fail after the update.
				This affects AD-Connector setups synchronizing UCS with Microsoft Server versions older than <literal>2012R2</literal>, if they are configured to use an encrypted connection.
				Additionally the OpenSSL default <literal>CipherString</literal> configuration is <literal>DEFAULT@SECLEVEL=2</literal> in UCS 5.0.
				This additionally restricts the available ciphers for communication, which rules out <literal>SHA1</literal> in particular.
				E.g. Windows Server 2012 supports less ciphers that Windows Server 2012R2 by default.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:samba">
			<title>Samba changes</title>
				<para>
					Samba has been updated to version 4.13.7 and also includes the patch for the security issue CVE-2021-20254 from 4.13.8.
					More details about this and the following points can be found in the changelog below.
				</para>
				<para>
					During updates to UCS 5 Samba will convert the database to a new index format.
					Since this is a transaction based operation the required storage capacity of the <literal>sam.ldb</literal> files will double temporarily for this operation.
					By default Samba uses the TDB key value database format as backing store, which is limited to a size of 4GB.
					Before the UCS update, a check is performed, if any of the five database backing files is already close to half of that size.
					In that case, the update is blocked to avoid non-functional Services for Windows after the update,
					and a link to a migration guide will be shown.
				</para>
				<para>
					Support for the SMB1 protocol variant is disabled by default as it is insecure for todays standards.
				</para>
				<para>
					Support for <literal>DES</literal> Kerberos encryption types has been removed.
				</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:defaultmasterpkg">
			<title>Notes about default master packages</title>
			<para>
				Apps like <application>UCC</application> and <application>Open-Xchange</application> used to install special packages on &ucsPrimaryDN; and &ucsBackupDN; to extend the LDAP server with schema and ACL rules.
				These packages are not needed anymore, these extensions are now distributed via &ucsUDL;.
				The packages should be removed before the upgrade is started to avoid incompatibilities with Python 3.
				Packages that are known to be incompatible are: <package>univention-corporate-client-schema</package>, <package>univention-ox-dependencies-master</package> and <package>univention-ox-directory-integration</package>.
				The system will also be checked for incompatible package as a preparation for the upgrade, see also <xref linkend="relnotes:prepare"/>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:joinscript-password">
			<!-- Bug 31996 -->
			<title>Notes about credentials passed to join scripts</title>
			<para>
				Join scripts are now always executed with the safe option <option>--bindpwdfile</option> instead of passing the credentials directly as command line option.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:bootloader">
		<title>Simultaneous operation of UCS and Debian on UEFI systems</title>
		<para>
			Please note that simultaneous operation of UCS and Debian on a UEFI system starting with UCS 5.0-0 is not supported.
		</para>
		<para>
			The reason for this is the GRUB boot loader of &ucsUCS;, which partly uses the same configuration files as Debian.
			An already installed Debian leads to the fact that UCS cannot be booted (any more) after the installation of or an update to UCS 5.0.
			A subsequent installation of Debian will also result in UCS 5.0 not being able to boot.
		</para>
		<para>
			At the following help article further hints to this topic are collected:
			<ulink url="https://help.univention.com/t/17768">https://help.univention.com/t/17768</ulink>
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:localrepo">
		<title>Local package repository</title>

		<para>
			This section is relevant for environments where a <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-4.4.html#software::createrepo">local repository</ulink> is set up.
			The installed (major) version of UCS determines which packages a local repository provides.
			A repository running on a UCS server with version 4.x will only provide packages up to UCS 4.x, a repository server running on UCS 5 will only provide packages for UCS 5 and newer versions.
			To upgrade systems to UCS 5 in an environment with a local repository, the following are some of the options.
			First, a local UCS 5 repository server must be set up.
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A new UCS 5 system is installed as a &ucsPrimaryDN; from the DVD or from a virtualized base image.
						Then <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">a local repository is set up on this system as described in the UCS 5 manual</ulink>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A new UCS 5 system is installed with the system role &ucsBackupDN;, &ucsReplicaDN; or &ucsManagedNode; from the DVD or from a virtualized base image.
						In system setup, select that the system will not join a domain.
						Then <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/handbuch-5.0.html#software::createrepo">set up a local repository on this system as described in the UCS 5 manual</ulink>.
						After the &ucsPrimaryDN; used in the domain is upgraded to UCS 5, the UCS 5 repository server can join the domain via <command>univention-join</command>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			To upgrade a system in the domain to UCS 5, the server should first be upgraded to the latest package level available for UCS 4.x.
			Then the repository server used by the system is switched to the local UCS 5 repository by changing the &ucsUCRV; <envar>repository/online/server</envar>.
			The system can now be upgraded to UCS 5 via the &ucsUMC; or via the command line.
		</para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:portal">
		<title>Portal</title>
	  <para>
      The design and functionality of the portal in UCS 5 has been fundamentally revised. Adjustments may need to be made to the portal configuration after the update to UCS 5.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By default, single sign-on is not used when logging in to the portal. Details on enabling single sign-on are <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual/5.0/en/central-management-umc/login.html#central-management-umc-login">described in the manual</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The portal used or displayed by a server is determined by the &ucsUCRV; <envar>portal/default-dn</envar> in UCS 5. After a change, the service <systemitem class="service">univention-portal-server</systemitem> must be restarted.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A design customized for the UCS 4 portal using CSS needs to be <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual/5.0/en/central-management-umc/introduction.html#central-theming">reworked</ulink> for the UCS 5 portal.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Portal content management will be done via <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/manual/5.0/en/central-management-umc/portal.html#central-portal">new &ucsUDM; modules</ulink>, the settings existing under UCS 4 will be migrated during the update.
          </para>
        </listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
    </para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:prepare">
		<title>Preparation of update</title>

		<para>
			Manually crafted Python code needs to be checked for compatibility with Python 3.7 before the Update and adjusted accordingly.
			This includes &ucsUCR; templates containing Python code.
			Customized AD-Connector mapping templates are an example for this.
			See also the <biblioref linkend="developer-reference"/> for advice.
		</para>
		<para>
			It must be checked whether sufficient disk space is available.
			A standard installation requires a minimum of 6-10 GB of disk space.
			The update requires approximately 1-2 GB additional disk space to download and install the packages, depending on the size of the existing installation.
		</para>

		<para>
			For the update, a login should be performed on the system's local console as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>, and the update should be initiated there.
			Alternatively, the update can be conducted using &ucsUMC;.
		</para>

		<para>
			Remote updating via SSH is not recommended as this may result in the update procedure being canceled, e.g., if the network connection is interrupted.
			In consequence, this can affect the system severely.
			If updating should occur over a network connection nevertheless, it must be verified that the update continues in case of disconnection from the network.
			This can be achieved, e.g., using the tools <command>tmux</command>, <command>screen</command> and <command>at</command>.
			These tools are installed on all UCS system roles by default.
		</para>

		<para>
			Univention provides a script that checks for problems which would prevent the successful update of the system.
			Prior to the update, this script can be downloaded and executed on the UCS system.
		</para>
		<screen><![CDATA[
# download
curl -OOf https://updates.software-univention.de/download/univention-update-checks/pre-update-checks-5.0-0{.gpg,}

# verify and run script
apt-key verify pre-update-checks-5.0-0{.gpg,} &&
  bash pre-update-checks-5.0-0

...

Starting pre-update checks ...

Checking app_appliance ...                        OK
Checking block_update_of_NT_DC ...                OK
Checking cyrus_integration ...                    OK
Checking disk_space ...                           OK
Checking hold_packages ...                        OK
Checking ldap_connection ...                      OK
Checking ldap_schema ...                          OK
...
		]]></screen>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:post">
		<title>Postprocessing of the update</title>

		<para>
			Following the update, new or updated join scripts need to be executed.
			This can be done in two ways:
			Either using the UMC module <guimenu>Domain join</guimenu> or by running the command
			<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> as user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem>.
		</para>

		<para>
			Subsequently the UCS system needs to be restarted.
		</para>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:packages">
		<title>Notes on selected packages</title>

		<section id="relnotes:network">
			<title>Network configuration</title>
			<para>
				Support for <package>ifplugd</package> has been removed.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:usage">
			<title>Collection of usage statistics</title>
			<para>
				Anonymous usage statistics on the use of &ucsUMC; are collected when using the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis>.
				The modules opened get logged to an instance of the web traffic analysis tool Piwik.
				This makes it possible for Univention to tailor the development of &ucsUMC; better to customer needs and carry out usability improvements.
			</para>
			<para>
				This logging is only performed when the <emphasis>UCS Core Edition</emphasis> license is used.
				The license status can be verified via the menu entry <guimenu>License &ar; License information</guimenu> of the user menu in the upper right corner of &ucsUMC;.
				If <guimenu>UCS Core Edition</guimenu> is listed under <guimenu>License type</guimenu>, this version is in use.
				When a regular UCS license is used, no usage statistics are collected.
			</para>
			<para>
				Independent of the license used, the statistics generation can be deactivated by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>umc/web/piwik</envar> to <emphasis>false</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="relnotes:browsers">
			<title>Recommended browsers for the access to &ucsUMC;</title>

			<para>
				&ucsUMC; uses numerous JavaScript and CSS functions to display the web interface.
				Cookies need to be permitted in the browser.
				The following browsers are recommended:
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Chrome as of version 85</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Firefox as of version 78</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Safari and Safari Mobile as of version 13</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
					<para>Microsoft Edge as of version 88</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				Users running older browsers may experience display or performance issues.
			</para>
		</section>

	</chapter>

	<chapter id="relnotes:changelog">
		<title>Changelog</title>
		<para>
			Listed are the changes since UCS <productnumber>4.4-8</productnumber>:
		</para>

		<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="changelog-5.0-0.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/chapter/section)"/>
	</chapter>

	<bibliography id="bibliography">
		<bibliomixed id="ucs-performance-guide"/>
		<bibliomixed id="developer-reference"/>
	</bibliography>

</book>
<!-- vim:set ft=docbk ts=2 sw=2 noet: -->
