<chapter>
	<title>Apps and Univention App Center</title>
		<para>
			Univention App Center provides a platform for software vendors and an easy-to-use entry point
			for Univention Corporate Server (UCS) users to extend their IT environment with business software.
			The App Center is part of the web-based UCS management system and gives an overview of available and
			installed apps. Its purpose is to present available business applications for UCS and simplify their
			installation. This allows their easy evaluation and fosters the purchase decision.
		</para>

		<para>
			Apps are the content of the App Center and they consist of the business software and
			some meta data about the presentation in the App Center. Most of them come with an integration into
			UCS, e.g. the management system or the mailstack. The purpose of an app is to provide the business
			solution in a way that it is ready to use after the installation and that comes with a decent
			default configuration to offer a satisfying impression of the solution. The installation is
			non-interactive and is done by just a click. Furthermore, an app utilizes the benefits of UCS and
			the business solution.
		</para>

		<para>
			The App Center infrastructure consists of two parts: The already mentioned frontend as
			part of the web-based UCS management system and the server side component that stores the app meta
			data and the app software packages in their own respective repositories. The server side
			infrastructure is operated by Univention. The technological basis for installation and updates of
			the apps is Apt, the well known advanced package tool from Debian. Therefore, the app needs to
			consist of so-called debian packages. The App Center frontend is responsible for the app's
			presentation. As soon as an app is clicked to be installed or updated, the App Center activates the
			respective repository and the further process is handed over to apt which takes care of the rest
			like for example dependency resolution.
		</para>

		<para>
			The next sections explain how to prepare your business solution as app for UCS. It also
			outlines the integration possibilities and describes what to do by example. Let's go!
		</para>
</chapter>

<!-- vim:set ts=2 sw=2 tw=100 noet ft=docbk:-->
