<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="prepare">
		<title> Prepare the environment</title>
		<para>
			Before you can start with the creation of an app for Univention App Center, you'll need to
			prepare your UCS environment. This section guides you through the necessary steps.
		</para>

		<section id="prepare:download">
			<title>Download</title>
			<para>
				First of all, get yourself a copy of UCS free of charge at the <ulink
				url="https://www.univention.com/downloads/ucs-download/">Univention Website</ulink>. You can
				choose between an ISO image or a pre-installed virtual machine.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="prepare:setup">
			<title>Initial setup </title>
			<para>
				Please refer to the <ulink url="http://docs.univention.de/quickstart-en.html" lang="">UCS Quickstart
				Guide</ulink> for the steps about installation and initial setup.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="prepare:unmaintained">
			<title>Activate the unmaintained repository</title>
			<para>
				UCS is a Linux distribution derived from Debian GNU/Linux. It behaves very similar
				and therefore software is installed from software repositories. UCS comes with the same packages as
				Debian (except the packages from the games section). The packages are provided through two
				repositories: maintained and unmaintained. Only the maintained repository is always activated by
				default.
			</para>

			<para>
				To install your solution, you may need packages that are in the unmaintained repository. Please activate it:
			</para>

			<programlisting language="sh">
ucr set repository/online/unmaintained='yes'
			</programlisting>

			<note><para>
				Please remember the packages you need from unmaintained repository and provide the
				list later with your upload. Univention will copy those packages besides your app packages and make
				sure that the package dependencies from the unmaintained repository are met without prior activation
				by the user.
			</para></note>
		</section>

		<section id="prepare:dependencies">
			<title>Install required packages for App development</title>

			<para>
				To build your software on UCS you will need to install build tools for Debian
				packages. The corresponding package can be installed with
			</para>

			<programlisting language="sh">
univention-install build-essential debhelper
			</programlisting>

			<para>
				Depending on your app you may furthermore require several development libraries
				(e.g. <package>libc-dev</package>, <package>php5-dev</package>). For UCS integration packages, we recommend
			</para>

			<programlisting language="sh">
# ucslint checks for common mistakes in a variety of files if enabled
# in debian/rules
#  see http://docs.univention.de/developer-reference.html#misc:ucslint
univention-install ucslint
			</programlisting>

			<programlisting language="sh">
# univention-config-dev takes care of installing and registering UCR
# variables if enabled in debian/rules
#   see http://docs.univention.de/developer-reference.html#chap:ucr
univention-install univention-config-dev
			</programlisting>

			<programlisting language="sh">
# If you are developing a UMC module to extend the management console,
# you will need
univention-install univention-management-console-dev
			</programlisting>

			<para>
				If you already have a source directory with working code
			</para>

			<programlisting language="sh">
dpkg-checkbuilddeps
			</programlisting>

			<para>
				should list the missing build dependencies, if any.
			</para>
		</section>
</chapter>

<!-- vim:set ts=2 sw=2 tw=100 noet ft=docbk:-->
