<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >

  %entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="installation-4.0">
<bookinfo>
  <title>Univention Corporate Server</title>
  <subtitle>Extended installation documentation</subtitle>
  <revhistory>
     <revision>
        <revnumber>4.0-0</revnumber>
        <date>16 Oct 2014</date>
     </revision>
  </revhistory>
</bookinfo>

<chapter id="profile:intro"><title>Profile-based installation</title>

<para>
  In addition to the interactive installation described in the UCS
  manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>, profile-based installation of UCS is also
  possible. In this method, the settings for the UCS installer are
  specified in a profile file. If all the required settings are included
  in the installation profile, it is possible to perform the
  installation fully unattended. <xref linkend="profile:variables"/>
  describes the structure of the profile file and the variables used in
  it.
</para>
<para>
  Profile-based installations can be performed in two ways:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><simpara>Installation from a DVD: The profile settings can then be
  imported from a floppy disk or a USB storage device or alternatively
  stored on the installation DVD. How to perform a profile-based
  installation from a DVD is described in
  <xref linkend="profile:dvdinstaller"/>.
  </simpara></listitem>
  <listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>Univention Net Installer</emphasis> can be used to perform
  network-based installations automatically via PXE. The profile
  settings used are identical. The PXE-based installations are
  documented in <xref linkend="profile:netinstaller"/>.</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<section id="profile:structure">
	<title>Structure of profile files</title>
<para>
An installation profile is a normal text file which can be edited with
any editor. Installation profiles must be saved in UTF-8.
The settings must be entered in the following format:
</para>
<programlisting>
Variable='Value1 Value2'
</programlisting>
<para>
Multiple values for one variable are separated by blank spaces. Lines
are commented out with #.
</para>
<para>
	It is not necessary to write an installation profile from scratch every time:
	The settings performed in the Univention Installer are saved in the file <filename>/etc/univention/installation_profile</filename> (with the exception of the root password).
	This file can be used as a template for an installation profile.
	Note that the partitioning information from that file is hardware specific and probably needs to be specified as
documented in <xref linkend="profile:variables:part"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="profile:example">
	<title>Example installation profile</title>
<para>
The following installation profile installs a &ucsMaster;
with English language and country settings on which the complete hard
drive is managed in an LVM. Samba 4 is installed.
</para>
<programlisting>
#### UCS-Profile ####

# [Time zone]
timezone='Europe/London'
locale_default='en_GB.UTF-8:UTF-8'
locales='en_GB.UTF-8:UTF-8'

# [Language]
language='en'

# [System role]
system_role='domaincontroller_master'

# [Settings]
domainname='company.example'
hostname='master'
ldap_base='dc=company,dc=example'
windows_domain='COMPANY'
root_password='secret'

# [Source device]
cdrom_device='/dev/sr0'

# [Partitioning]
create_partitiontable='/dev/sda'
disks='/dev/sdb /dev/sda'
partitiontable_type='gpt'
auto_part='yes'
bootloader_record='/dev/sda'
boot_partition='/dev/sda1'

# [Keyboard]
keymap='uk'

# [Software]
packages='univention-s4-connector univention-samba4'

# [Network]
nameserver_1='192.0.2.3'
eth0_broadcast='192.0.2.255'
dns_forwarder_1='192.0.2.3'
eth0_netmask='255.255.255.0'
eth0_network='192.0.2.0'
gateway='192.0.2.240'
eth0_ip='192.0.2.134'
</programlisting>
<para>
	Additional templates are included on the installation medium in the directory <filename class="directory">profiles/</filename>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="profile:variables">
	<title>Overview of profile variables</title>

<section id="profile:variables:general">
	<title>Profile variables - Installer</title>
<para>
The following profile variables are used to control the progress of
the installation. For example, it is possible to include a password
prompt, run programs before and after the installation or allow the
entry of the value for individual variables during the installation.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - Installer</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>profile_password</varname></entry>
<entry>
Here one can specify the password that
must be entered when the installation profile is used. This is not
a security feature as the password is saved in the profile in plain
text. However, a password can serve as a safe guard mechanism against an
incorrectly selected profile.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>to_check</varname></entry>
<entry>
Here one can specify variables whose values must
be entered or checked at the beginning of the installation. These
variables can be used to install a large number of computers of the
same type with the same profile in cases where only individual
settings such as IP addresses and the computer name are different. If
more than one value is specified, the values are separated by blank
spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>check</varname></entry>
<entry>
If this variable is used, only the variables listed
are requested. Other missing variables are not taken into
account. <varname>check</varname> supports the
parameter <literal>all</literal>. When <literal>check=all</literal> is used, all profile
variables are requested, even those already set (same as interactive
installation). If more than one value is specified, the values are
separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>scan</varname></entry>
<entry>
This option provides mechanisms with which the values
of the profile variables can be retrieved dynamically during the
installation. At present, <varname>hostname</varname> is the only profile
variable supported. If <literal>scan=hostname</literal> is entered, the
computer name is procured via the computer's IP address by means of
a name server request during the installation. <varname>scan</varname> supports
the parameter <literal>all</literal>. If <literal>scan=all</literal> is used, all the
profile variables supported by <varname>scan</varname> are imported during the
installation. If more than one value is specified, the values are
separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ignore</varname></entry>
<entry>
The value for the <varname>ignore</varname> option can
include profile variables that are not to be checked. If, for
example, <literal>scan=hostname</literal> is set, <literal>ignore=hostname</literal>
must also be set. <varname>ignore</varname> must also be used if system
settings are to be set using scripts
<varname>preinst_hook</varname>, <varname>postinst_hook</varname>). <varname>ignore</varname>
supports the parameter <literal>all</literal>. If <literal>ignore=all</literal> is used, no profile
variables are requested unless they are specifically set. If more than
one value needs to be specified, the values must be separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>cdrom_device</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		The device used to provide the packages during installation, which is normally auto-detected.
		It can either be a local CD-ROM or DVD device (e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/cdrom</filename>) or an NFS share (e.g., <literal>nfs:<replaceable>192.0.2.2</replaceable>:/var/lib/univention-repository</literal>).
		<!--
		Support for Samba-Share (e.g, <literal>smbfs:</literal>) is still in the code, but no longer works, since the "smbfs" filesystem got replaced by "cifs".
		The compatibility package "smbfs" is still available, but not installed in the default installer, so does not work.
		Samba also denies authentication as root and there is no way to specify alternative credentials via "$cdrom_device".
		-->
	</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>premount_hook</varname></entry>
<entry>
	Here one can specify scripts which should be run before the UCS system is boot-strapped.
	The scripts must be provided in the directory <filename class="directory">script/</filename> on the installation medium.
	If more than one script is entered, they must be separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>preinst_hook</varname></entry>
<entry>
	Here one can specify scripts which should be run before the installation of role-specific packages begins.
	The scripts must be provided in the directory <filename class="directory">script/</filename> on the installation medium.
	If more than one script is entered, they must be separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>postinst_hook</varname></entry>
<entry>
	Here one can specify scripts which should be run after the installation but before the final update process.
	The scripts must be provided in the directory <filename class="directory">script/</filename> on the installation medium.
	If more than one script is entered, they must be separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>auto_reboot</varname></entry>
<entry>
	The system is automatically restarted after the installation if the parameter is set to <literal>true</literal> or <literal>yes</literal>.
	This parameter should only be used in network-based installations in combination with the <literal>installation_feedback_host</literal>, as the computer setting <guimenu>(Re-)install on next boot</guimenu> must be reset at the end of the installation.
	The installation would otherwise start from the beginning again the next time the system starts.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>installation_&#x200b;feedback_host</varname></entry>
  <entry>
	If <emphasis>univention-net-installer-daemon</emphasis> has been setup to reset the
	<guimenu>(Re-)install on next boot</guimenu> option in the &ucsUMC; (see <xref
	linkend="profile:assign"/>), this variable specifies the IP address of the host where the daemon is running.
  </entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>installation_&#x200b;feedback_port</varname></entry>
  <entry>
	If the daemon for resetting the <guimenu>(Re-)install on next boot</guimenu> flag has been
	configured (see profile variable <emphasis>installation_feedback_host</emphasis>), this variable
	can be used to specify the port where the daemon is listening for connections. This variable
	only needs to be configured if the daemon is running on a non-default port. If unset, 49173 is
	used.
  </entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="profile:variables:system">
	<title>Profile variables - System properties</title>
<para>
The following profile variables can be used to specify basic
properties of the computer such as the computer name, its role within
the UCS domain and the name of the domain the computer should join.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - System properties</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>system_role</varname></entry>
<entry>
	The system role.
	You may choose from <literal>domaincontroller_master</literal>, <literal>domaincontroller_backup</literal>, <literal>domaincontroller_slave</literal>, <literal>memberserver</literal> and <literal>base</literal>.
	The properties of the system roles are described in the domain services chapter of the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>hostname</varname></entry>
<entry>
	The computer name.
	The name must only contain the letters <literal>a</literal> to <literal>z</literal> in lowercase, the figures <literal>0</literal> to <literal>9</literal> and hyphens.
	Although underscore are allowed as well, they should not be used as they are not supported everywhere.
	The name must begin with a letter.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>domainname</varname></entry>
<entry>
The name of the DNS domain in which the computer is joined.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>fqdn</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		This value only has informative character.
		It is calculated by concatenating the values of the variables <varname>hostname</varname> and <varname>domainname</varname>.
	</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>windows_domain</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		The name of the NetBIOS domain used by Samba.
		This variable should only by defined for the system role &ucsMaster;.
	</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>locales</varname></entry>
<entry>
Localisation packages to be installed (locales). If more than one
locale is specified, the locales are separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>locale_default</varname></entry>
<entry>
The standard locale for the computer, e.g. <literal>en_GB.UTF-8:UTF-8</literal>.
More information on system locales can be found at <biblioref linkend="locales"/>.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>country</varname>, <varname>keymap</varname></entry>
<entry>
The keyboard layout for the computer, specified in the form of an X11
keymap entry, e.g. <literal>de-latin1</literal>.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>timezone</varname></entry>
<entry>
The time zone for the computer,
e.g. <literal>Europe/Berlin</literal>. A complete list of possible
configuration options is shown in the <emphasis>Basic
settings</emphasis> module of the Univention Management Console.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>root_password</varname></entry>
<entry>
The password for the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user for
this computer. On a &ucsMaster;, this password is also used for
the <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis>'s password.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>use_efi</varname></entry>
<entry>
Whether a system is using the Unified Extensible
Firmware Interface (<acronym>UEFI</acronym>) boot mechanism is detected automatically.
This variable can be used to override the automatic
detection. Possible values are <literal>yes</literal> and
<literal>no</literal>.
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="profile:variables:join">
	<title>Profile variables - LDAP settings and domain joins</title>
<para>
The entries <varname>domain_controller_account</varname>
and <varname>domain_controller_password</varname> are essential for computers
intended to join the domain.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - LDAP settings and domain joins</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>auto_join</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		As standard, all computers apart from the base system and &ucsMaster; attempt to join the UCS domain in the course of the installation.
		If this parameter is set to <literal>false</literal>, the automatic domain join is deactivated.
	</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>domain_controller_&#x200b;account</varname></entry>
<entry>
The name of a user authorised to perform the computer's domain
join. In the standard setting this is the user
<literal>Administrator</literal>. The entry is essential on systems
intended to join the UCS domain.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>domain_controller_&#x200b;password</varname></entry>
<entry>
The password for the
<varname>domain_controller_account</varname>. The entry is essential
on systems intended to join the UCS domain.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ldap_base</varname></entry>
<entry>
The base DN of the LDAP domain. In general, the
base DN <literal>dc=company,dc=example</literal> is used in a
domain <literal>company.example</literal>. This variable is only evaluated on the
system role &ucsMaster;.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ldap_position</varname></entry>
<entry>
The position as DN in the LDAP directory at
which the computer object should be saved when joining the domain. If
this variable is not set, the object is saved in the standard
container for computers with its system role.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>call_master_joinscripts</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		If set to <literal>false</literal>, the join-scripts are not executed on the system role &ucsMaster;.
		This is only required for special situations like setting up UCS systems in Appliance mode.
	</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="profile:variables:network">
	<title>Profile variables - Network configuration</title>
<para>
The following profile variables can be used to specify the network
configuration of the computer. There is a restriction on the number of
network cards used. A maximum of four physical network cards can be
used with four virtual interfaces for each physical one.
</para>
<para>
General information on the network configuration and the use of the
name servers can be found in Chapter <emphasis>Network configuration</emphasis>
of the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
</para>
<para>
The <varname>use_external_nameserver</varname> parameter can be used to
suppress the use of the local name server. The external name server
must be specified in the profile with the <varname>nameserver_1</varname>
parameter.
</para>
<para>
The settings for network cards must be performed completely. It is not
possible to leave individual settings blank. For example, if there is
no IP address for the device eth0 in the profile, in addition to the
IP address, the <varname>eth0_netmask</varname> will also be requested.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - Network configuration</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_type</varname></entry>
<entry>
	If this parameter is set to <literal>dynamic</literal> or <literal>dhcp</literal>, the network interface ethN procures its network configuration via DHCP.
	The settings of <varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_ip</varname>, <varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_netmask</varname>, <varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_network</varname>, <varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_broadcast</varname>, <varname>nameserver_<replaceable>N</replaceable></varname> and <varname>gateway</varname> then become optional, but can still be used to over-write the configuration provided by DHCP.
	<!-- PMH: Actually DHCP is skipped as soon as _ip and _netmask are given -->
	If no DHCP offer is received, a random IP address from the link-local network <literal>169.254.<replaceable>x.x</replaceable></literal> is used.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_ip</varname></entry>
<entry>
The IPv4 address of the physical network interface ethN.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_netmask</varname></entry>
<entry>
The network mask of the subnetwork from which the IPv4 address of ethN
originates.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>gateway</varname></entry>
<entry>
The IPv4 address of the gateway which the computer should use as
standard. Alternatively, one can specify the computer name or the FQDN
that can be resolved into the IP address.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_ip6</varname></entry>
<entry>
The IPv6 address of the physical network interface ethN in static
configuration.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_prefix6</varname></entry>
<entry>
The prefix of the IPv6 address of the physical network interface ethN
in static configuration.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>gateway6</varname></entry>
<entry>
The IPv6 address of the gateway which the
computer should use as standard. It is not obligatory to enter a
gateway for IPv6, but recommended. An IPv6 gateway configured here has
preference over router advertisements, which might otherwise be able
to change the route.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_acceptra</varname></entry>
<entry>
If this setting is set to <literal>yes</literal>, the
stateless address auto-configuration (<acronym>SLAAC</acronym>) is used. In this, the IP
address is assigned from the routers of the local network segment. If
the variable is set to <literal>no</literal>, the configuration is performed
statically via <varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_ip6</varname> and <varname>eth<replaceable>N</replaceable>_prefix6</varname> (see
below).
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>use_external_nameserver</varname></entry>
<entry>
If this parameter is set to <literal>true</literal>, the DNS service
automatically installed on every domain controller is not used. Instead, the
variable <varname>nameserver_<replaceable>N</replaceable></varname> is used to specify an external name
server. If the parameter is set to <literal>false</literal> or not set at all, the
internal name server will be used in accordance with the UCS
standard.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>nameserver_1</varname>, <varname>nameserver_2</varname>, <varname>nameserver_3</varname></entry>
<entry>
The IP address of the name server which should perform the name
resolution. It is possible to specify up to three name servers.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>dns_forwarder_1</varname>, <varname>dns_forwarder_2</varname>, <varname>dns_forwarder_3</varname></entry>
<entry>
The IP address of the name server
intended to serve as the forwarder for a locally installed DNS
service. It is possible to specify up to three forwarders.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>proxy_http</varname></entry>
<entry>
The URL of a proxy server to be used when
downloading accessing the Internet. The specified URL is adopted in
the &ucsUCR; variables <envar>proxy/http</envar> and <envar>proxy/ftp</envar>. This setting is only required
if packages are to be installed which download additional packages
from external web servers; e.g., the installation program for the
Flash plugin.
<para>
Example: proxy_http=http://proxy.company.example:8080
</para>
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="profile:variables:software">
  <title>Profile variables - Software selection</title>
<para>
The following profile variables refer to software packages which are
to be installed on the computer.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - Software selection</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>packages</varname></entry>
<entry>
Each system role has a preselection of software
which is installed on the system. This settings names packages which
are additionally installed. If more than one package is specified, the
packages are separated by blank spaces.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>local_repository</varname> (Unused since UCS-3.0)</entry>
<entry>
If this parameter is set to <literal>true</literal>,
a local repository is set up and the contents of the installation DVD
copied (see Chapter <emphasis>Software deployment</emphasis> of the UCS
manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="profile:variables:part">
	<title>Profile variables - Partitioning</title>
<para>
The configuration of the partition settings can be performed
completely profiled-based. Existing partitions can be deleted or
mounted as data partitions without reformatting; new partitions can be
set up in free areas.
</para>
<para>
In contrast to the remaining variables, the profile variables for hard
drive configuration have an extended syntax.
</para>
<para>
<varname>part_delete</varname> causes deletion of
partitions; <varname>lvmlv_delete</varname> can be used to delete LVM logical volumes.
The profile variable <varname>auto_part</varname> activates the automatic
partitioning.
</para>
<para>
    The profile variable <varname>dev_<replaceable>Number</replaceable></varname> specifies whether and how
the partition should be formatted and where the partition should be
mounted in the file system. The names used for the profile variable
must be furnished with running numbers starting with zero (<varname>dev_0</varname>,
<varname>dev_1</varname>, <varname>dev_2</varname>, ...) The profile variable for the configuration of
the partitions has the most extensive syntax. The entry type, device
file, partition type, partition format, file system, start and end
cylinder of the partition, directory under which the partition should
be mounted and additional options parameters must be specified.
</para>
<para>
The first parameter describes the entry type. A difference is made
here between <literal>PHY</literal> for a physical partition and <literal>LVM</literal> for a
LVM logical volume entry. As a second parameter, the device name of the partition
(e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda1</filename>) or the logical volume
(e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/vg_ucs/log_vol_1</filename>) must be entered.
</para>
<para>
The third parameter describes the partition type. For <literal>PHY</literal>
entries, <literal>0</literal> means primary, <literal>1</literal> means logical and <literal>2</literal>
means extended. For <literal>LVM</literal> entries, only the value <literal>LVMLV</literal>
for a LVM logical volume is currently recognised. The fourth parameter
determines whether the partition is formatted during the installation
(value <literal>1</literal>) or not (value <literal>0</literal>). Extended partitions are
assigned the value <literal>0</literal>. If you do not want to format an existing
partition, alternatively, the parameter <literal>only_mount</literal> can be set
on the third position and <literal>0</literal> can be set in the fourth
position. The fifth parameter describes the file system to be
used. You can choose between <literal>ext2</literal>, <literal>ext3</literal>, <literal>ext4</literal>,
<literal>linux-swap</literal> <literal>None</literal> (for extended partitions and partitions
to which no file system is to be ordered) and <literal>xfs</literal>.
</para>
<para>
Parameters six and seven describe the start and end cylinders of the
partition. If <literal>0</literal> is entered as the end cylinder, the partition
is set from the specified start cylinder to the end of the hard
drive. The start and end points of the partition can also be specified
in kilobytes/1024 bytes (<literal>k</literal> or <literal>K</literal>), megabytes/1048576 bytes (<literal>m</literal> or <literal>M</literal>) and
gigabytes/1073741824 bytes (<literal>g</literal> or <literal>G</literal>).
</para>
<para>
The end can be specified relative to the start point (e.g., `10g
+2g'). Bytes and cylinder specifications can be mixed (e.g., `12g
0' for a partition beginning at 12 gigabytes and ending with the last
cylinder). For an <literal>LVM</literal> entry, the start point should always be
set as 0 and its end point should be set to the required size of the
LVM logical volume.
</para>
<para>
The following provides an example:
</para>
<programlisting>
bootloader_record="/dev/sda"
disks="/dev/sda"
part_delete="all"
lvm_delete="/dev/vg_ucs/*"
dev_1="PHY /dev/sda1 0 1 ext3 0.032256M 106.928128M /boot None"
dev_0="LVM /dev/vg_ucs/rootfs LVMLV 1 ext3 0.0M 4000M / None"
dev_4="LVM /dev/vg_ucs/vol2 LVMLV 1 ext3 0 4000M None None"
dev_3="PHY /dev/sda3 0 0 None 633.34656M 0 None lvm"
dev_2="PHY /dev/sda2 0 1 linux-swap 106.92864M 633.346048M None None"
</programlisting>
<para>
The eighth parameter stands for the mount point. For swap partitions and other
partitions without a mount point <literal>None</literal> should be entered.
</para>
<para>
<literal>lvm</literal> can be entered as the ninth parameter to mark the partition
as a LVM physical disk. In all other cases, <literal>None</literal> should be entered.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - Partitioning</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>bootloader_record</varname></entry>
<entry>
The device onto which the bootloader Grub is installed into the master boot record.
It is detected automatically in the basic setting, but if more than one disk is found an interactive selection needs to be made.
This variable can be used to specify the device. Example: <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda</filename>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>boot_partition</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		This variable can be used to specify a partition, into which the bootloader Grub installs its additional modules.
		The partition should be located at the beginning of the first disk to guarantee proper BIOS support.
		Example: <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda1</filename>
	</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>part_delete</varname></entry>
<entry>
The names of the partitions to be deleted
during the installation. The name used by the operating system
(e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda4</filename>) should be entered here. In addition, the
value <literal>all</literal> is supported, which causes the deletion of all the partitions
on all detected hard drives.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>lvm_delete</varname></entry>
<entry>
		The names of the logical volumes to be deleted during the installation.
		Two different spellings can be used in the entry.
		The first is to specify the full device file name (e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/vg_ucs/rootfs</filename>) or just the combination of LVM volume group and LVM logical volume (e.g., <literal>vg_ucs/rootfs</literal>).
		The second is to delete all LVM logical volumes from an LVM volume group by specifying the LVM volume group (e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/vg_ucs/*</filename> or <literal>vg_ucs</literal>).
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>dev_<replaceable>N</replaceable></varname></entry>
<entry>
Information on the partitions in the order
entry type, device file, partition type, formatting yes/no, file
system, start and end point, mount point, additional options.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>partitiontable_type</varname></entry>
  <entry>
	This variable is used to specify the type of the partition table to create.
	If this variable is set to <literal>gpt</literal>, the partitioning is performed using the GUID
	Partition Table standard (<acronym>GPT</acronym>).
	If configured to <literal>mbr</literal> or <literal>msdos</literal>, a master boot record (<acronym>MBR</acronym>) is used (this is deprecated since UCS-3.0).
	The default is still <literal>mbr</literal>.
  </entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>create_partitiontable</varname></entry>
  <entry>
	This variable can be used to specify a space separated list of devices on which a partition table should be created.
	Unpartitioned disks can not be used for installations and are ignored, which causes auto-partition to fail.
  </entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>auto_part</varname></entry>
<entry>
	Depending on <varname>partitiontable_type</varname> different schemes to automatically partition the disks can be selected:
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><literal>full_disk</literal> (supported by <literal>mbr</literal> and <literal>gpt</literal> until UCS-3.1-1)</term>
			<listitem><simpara>All non-USB disks are partitioned and used to create one large logical volume spanning all disks.</simpara></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><literal>full_disk_usb</literal> (supported by <literal>mbr</literal> and <literal>gpt</literal> until UCS-3.1-1)</term>
			<listitem><simpara>Same as <literal>full_disk</literal>, but also includes all USB disks</simpara></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><literal>yes</literal> (supported by <literal>gpt</literal> since UCS-3.2)</term>
			<listitem><simpara>Only the first disk is partitioned and used to create one logical volume spanning only that disk.</simpara></listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>disks</varname></entry>
	<entry>
		A space separated list of disk devices (e.g., <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda</filename>) used for auto-partitioning.
		It is incaompatible with <varname>create_partitiontable</varname>, which superseeds this <varname>disks</varname> setting.
	</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>


<section id="profile:variables:ssl">
	<title>Profile variables - SSL</title>
<para>
A SSL certification infrastructure is set up during installation of
a &ucsMaster;. If no settings are configured, automatic names are
given for the certificate.
</para>

<table>
<title>Profile variables - SSL</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ssl_country</varname></entry>
<entry>
The ISO country code of the certification body appearing in the
certificate (root CA), specified with two capital letters.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ssl_state</varname></entry>
<entry>
The region, county or province that appears in the certificate of the
root CA.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ssl_locality</varname></entry>
<entry>
Place appearing in the certificate of the root CA.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ssl_organization</varname></entry>
<entry>
Name of the organisation that appears in the certificate of the root CA.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ssl_organizationalunit</varname></entry>
<entry>
Name of the organisational unit or department of the organisation that
appears in the certificate of the root CA.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry><varname>ssl_email</varname></entry>
<entry>
E-mail address that appears in the certificate of the root CA.
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

</section>


<section id="profile:netinstaller">
	<title>Network-based PXE installations with Univention Net Installer</title>
<para>
Network-based, profile-based installations via PXE are performed with
the Univention Net Installer, which can be set up using
the <package>univention-net-installer</package> package. In addition, a DHCP
server is required. If the DHCP server and the PXE server of the
Univention Net Installer are operated on separate systems, the PXE
server must be assigned via a DHCP boot policy.
</para>
<para>
Univention Net Installer supports both the interactive and profile-based
installation.
</para>
<para>
Univention Net Installer requires a local repository as a package
source (see the software deployment chapter of the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>).
The profiles must be copied into the directory
<filename class="directory">/var/lib/univention-repository/profiles/</filename> on the
repository server.
</para>

<section id="profile:assign">
  <title>Assignment of a computer for automatic installation</title>
  <para>
	A computer to be installed via Univention Net Installer must firstly
	be registered in the computer management of the &ucsUMC;. The
	following values must be set as a minimum:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara>Hostname (General tab)</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>MAC address (General tab)</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>IP address (General tab)</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>DNS forward and reverse zone entries (General tab)</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>DHCP service entry (General tab)</simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
	The <guimenu>(Re-)install on next boot</guimenu> option must now be
	activated in the <guimenu>Advanced settings</guimenu> tab
	under <guimenu>Deployment</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para>
	The name of the installation profile under
	<filename class="directory">/var/lib/univention-repository/profiles/</filename> can be
	entered under <guimenu>Name of installation profile</guimenu>. The
	file name of the profile should be entered without specifying the
	path.
  </para>
  <para>
	Options entered under <guimenu>Additional start options</guimenu> are
	passed on to the kernel in network-based installations, e.g., for the
	deactivation of ACPI during system start.
  </para>
  <para>
	A profile-based installation is performed as standard in installations
	with the Univention Net Installer. If one wishes to perform an
	interactive installation instead, the <guimenu>Interactive
	installation</guimenu> option must be activated. If any installation
	profile is entered, then it is no longer used.
  </para>
  <para>
	A PXE configuration file is created for every computer object
	under <filename class="directory">/var/lib/univention-client-boot/</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>
	It must be verified that the boot order in BIOS of the system to be
	installed prefers a PXE network boot over hard disks or CD-ROMs.
  </para>
  <para>
	On the next restart of the computer it will boot via PXE and
	is installed via the network. If no profile has been specified, a list
	of existing profiles is shown at the beginning of the installation for
	selection. If the selected profile includes an error, meaning it
	can't be loaded, an error message is emitted. It is then possible
	to select another profile.
  </para>
  <para>
	User inputs are only required for profile-based installations if a
	profile password is specified in the profile or variables with
	<varname>to_check</varname> are explicitly entered for requests (see 
	<xref linkend="profile:variables:general"/>). If
	<varname>to_check</varname> is not used, a request may be given for
	essential variables with missing or erroneous values.
  </para>

  <para>
	By default the <guimenu>(Re-)install on next boot</guimenu> option needs to be reset manually
	after the installation has finished. If the package
	<emphasis>univention-net-installer-daemon</emphasis> is installed on the server, the flag can be
	reset automatically. The daemon needs to be configured in the installation profile using the
	variables <emphasis>installation_feedback_host</emphasis> and
	<emphasis>installation_feedback_port</emphasis> (see <xref
	linkend="profile:variables:general"/>).
  </para>

  <caution>
    <para>
	  If the <emphasis>univention-net-installer-daemon</emphasis> is not used, the option
	  <guimenu>(Re-)install on next boot</guimenu> must be unset manually after the
	  installation.
	  Otherwise the computer will be reinstalled every time the host is booted!
    </para>
  </caution>
</section>

</section>

</chapter>

	<bibliography>
		<bibliomixed id="ucs-handbuch"/>
		<bibliomixed id="locales"/>
	</bibliography>

<?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwik.html"?>
</book>
