<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="networks-4.4">
    <bookinfo>
      <title>Univention Corporate Server</title>
      <subtitle>Extended IP and network management documentation</subtitle>
    </bookinfo>

    <chapter id="proxy">
        <title>Advanced proxy configuration</title>
        <section id="proxy:cascading">
            <title>Cascading of proxies</title>
			<para>
			  In some scenarios, cascading of proxy servers may be required. In such a setup,
			  individual proxy servers access logically superordinate proxy servers when web
			  sites are opened, which then fetch the requested data from the Internet. This allows
			  creation of a hierarchical structure of proxy servers and, for example, the operation of a
			  central cache in a company's headquarters that the proxy servers at the individual
			  company sites can access.
			</para>

			<para>
			  The superordinate proxy server is referred to as a <emphasis>parent proxy</emphasis>
			  The parent proxy can be specified via the &ucsUCR; variables
			  <envar>squid/parent/host</envar> (IP address or hostname) and
			  <envar>squid/parent/port</envar> (port number).
			</para>

			<para>
			  Proxy requests from computers in the proxy server's local network are answered
			  directly and not forwarded to the parent proxy. If additional networks should be
			  excluded from forwarding to the parent proxy, these can be specified via the
			  &ucsUCRV; <envar>squid/parent/directnetworks</envar>. When doing so, the CIDR notation
			  must be used (e.g. 192.0.2.0/24); several networks should be separated by blank spaces.
			</para>
        </section>

        <section id="proxy:transparent">
            <title>Operation as a transparent proxy</title>
			<para>
				It is possible to configure Squid as a transparent proxy.
				This can help avoid configuring the proxy server in all application programs.
				When using a transparent proxy, all unencrypted web queries are automatically rerouted through the proxy server.
			</para>
			<note>
				<simpara>This only works for unencrypted web traffic, not for <systemitem class="protocol">https</systemitem>.</simpara>
			</note>
			<note>
				<simpara>LDAP authentication on the proxy server must not be enabled.</simpara>
			</note>
			<para>
			  The following configuration steps need to be made:

			  <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>
				  The proxy server must be configured as the default gateway on all clients.
				</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>
				  The proxy server must be configured to use IP forwarding.
				  <programlisting lang="sh">
echo "net.ipv4.ip_forward = 1" >> /etc/sysctl.conf
sysctl -p
				  </programlisting>
				</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>
				  The &ucsUCRV; <envar>squid/transparentproxy</envar> must be set to
				  <emphasis>yes</emphasis> on the proxy server. After that Univention Firewall and Squid need to be restarted:
				  <programlisting lang="sh">
/etc/init.d/univention-firewall restart
/etc/init.d/squid restart
				  </programlisting>

				  This enables packet filter rules which redirect all queries for the web ports to the proxy server.
				</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</section>

        <section id="proxy:scanner">
            <title>Integration of a virus scanner in the proxy</title>

			<para>
			  Following the installation of <package>univention-dansguardian</package>, the
			  virus scanner and the filter for web contents are activated. ClamAV is used as the virus scan engine
			</para>

			<para>
			  The filtering of web content and the virus scanner can be activated
			  separately. In order to deactivate the content filter, the
			  &ucsUCRV; <envar>squid/contentscan</envar> must be set to <emphasis>no</emphasis> and Squid
			  restarted. To disable the virus scanner, the
			  &ucsUCRV; <envar>squid/virusscan</envar> must be set to <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
			  If neither of the two variables is set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>,
			  DansGuardian is not used. After changes to the variables Squid and DansGuardian
			  must be restarted.
			</para>

			<para>
			  The following variables can be used to configure the virus scan:

			  <table>
				<title>UCR variables for filter rules</title>
				<tgroup cols="2">
				  <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
				  <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
				  <thead>
					<row>
					  <entry>UCR variable</entry>
					  <entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				  </thead>
				  <tbody>

					<row>
					  <entry>
						<envar>dansguardian/virus/notifyemail</envar>
					  </entry>
					  <entry>
						If this value is set to a valid e-mail address, a notification is sent via e-mail
						as soon as a user attempts to download a file infected with a virus.
					  </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
					  <entry>
						<envar>dansguardian/virus/exception/extension</envar>
					  </entry>
					  <entry>
						Files which have a suffix specified in this variable are not scanned for
						viruses. This option should be employed with caution as file suffixes do not
						provide definitive information on the actual contents of a file.
					  </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
					  <entry>
						<envar>dansguardian/virus/exception/mimetypes</envar>
					  </entry>
					  <entry>
						MIME types specified in this variable are not scanned for viruses. This option
						should also be employed with caution.
					  </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
					  <entry>
						<envar>dansguardian/virus/exception/sites</envar>
					  </entry>
					  <entry>
						This can be used to exclude complete web sites from virus scans, e.g. by excluding
						the company's intranet.
					  </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
					  <entry>
						<envar>dansguardian/virus/exception/urls</envar>
					  </entry>
					  <entry>
						In contrast to the previous variable, this can be used to exempts only individual
						URLs from the virus scan.
					  </entry>
					</row>
				  </tbody>
				</tgroup>
			  </table>
			</para>

		</section>

    </chapter>
</book>
