<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="printers-4.4">
  <bookinfo>
	<title>Univention Corporate Server</title>
	<subtitle>Extended print services documentation</subtitle>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter id="quota">
	<title>Print quota configuration</title>
	<section id="quota:intro">

	  <title>Introduction</title>
	  <para>
		The UCS print service allows the use of print quotas. Print quotas can be defined for
		printers and printer groups using policies.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Print quotas are implemented using the component PyKota. It creates an interface between the
		print server CUPS and the connected printer. Before the print job is sent to
		the printer, the system checks whether the user is authorized to print. In addition, every
		print job is logged, which allows cost evaluations.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		There are two thresholds for the print quotas:
	  </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>
			The <emphasis>hard limit</emphasis> is the maximum number of printable pages. Further
			print jobs will be rejected. The user is notified by e-mail.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			Once the <emphasis>soft limit</emphasis> is reached, an e-mail can be sent
			warning the user that the hard limit will soon be reached. This is done by
			setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/quota/inform</envar> to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>. This
			notification is disabled in the standard setting.
		  </simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	  <para>
		  PyKota interprets print jobs in the following print formats: <systemitem class="protocol">PostScript</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PDF</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PCL1</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PCL2</systemitem>,
		  <systemitem class="protocol">PCL3</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PCL4</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PCL5</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PCLXL</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">PCL6</systemitem> and <systemitem class="protocol">ESC/P2</systemitem>.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The print quota status is not saved in the LDAP directory service, but rather in a separate
		PostgreSQL database set up automatically via the
		<package>univention-printquotadb</package> package on the print server.
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="quota:install">
	  <title>Installation</title>
	  <para>
		Print quota support is disabled as standard. It must be subsequently set up by installing
		the <package>univention-printquota</package> package.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Enabling the print quotas results in an internal change to the printer management. For this
		reason, <package>univention-printquota</package> must be installed on all print servers.
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="quota:config">
	  <title>Configuration of print quotas</title>

	  <section id="quota:config:activate">
		<title>Enabling of print quotas</title>
		<para>
		  Before a print quota can be assigned to a printer or printer group, the option
		  <guimenu>Enable quota support</guimenu> must be activated in the &ucsUMC;.
		</para>

		<figure id="printquota-enable">
		  <title>Enabling quota support</title>
		  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations44/enable-print-quota-support.png"/>
		</figure>

		<note>
		  <para>
			Print quotas can only be used for printers connected via the protocols
			<systemitem class="protocol">lpd</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">ipp</systemitem>, <systemitem class="protocol">http</systemitem>,
			<systemitem class="protocol">socket</systemitem> and <systemitem class="protocol">smb</systemitem>. It is not possible to set up
			print quotas for printers connected via <uri>usb</uri>,
			<uri>parallel</uri> and <uri>file</uri> URIs.
		  </para>
		</note>
	  </section>

	  <section id="quota:assign">
		<title>Assigning quota limits to users and groups</title>
		<para>
		  The printer quotas can then be assigned in two ways; via a policy or specifically for each
		  user in the UMC module <guimenu>Printer administration</guimenu>.
		</para>

		<section id="quota:assign:policy">
		  <title>Assignment via a policy</title>
		  <para>
			The quota can be configured as a soft limit (warning threshold) and a hard limit (maximum
			number of printable pages) respectively via a print quota policy. The set values are
			always interpreted minus 1. I.e., if the user has a hard limit of 100, a maximum of 99
			pages can be printed. This gives the following special values:
		  </para>

			<itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><simpara>
				<emphasis>0</emphasis>: The print volume is unlimited
			  </simpara></listitem>

			  <listitem><simpara>
				<emphasis>1</emphasis>: The user or group cannot print any pages at all
			  </simpara></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

		  <para>
			The assignment is possible in the following ways:
		  </para>

			<itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><simpara>
				<guimenu>Print quota for users</guimenu>: The print quota applies for the specified
				user(s) individually.
			  </simpara></listitem>

			  <listitem><simpara>
				<guimenu>Print quota for groups per user</guimenu>: The limit is evaluated
				individually for every user in the group specified here.
			  </simpara></listitem>

			  <listitem><simpara>
				<guimenu>Print quota for groups</guimenu>: The group specified here is assigned a
				common contingent. All users belonging to the group can use this contingent.
			  </simpara></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>

		<section id="printquota:umcmodule">
		  <title>Assignment via the UMC module</title>

		  <figure id="printquota-listprinters">
			<title>List of available printers</title>
			<graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/printquota-umc1.png"/>
		  </figure>

		  <para>
			The UMC module <guimenu>Printer administration</guimenu> allows the configuration of user-specific
			printer quotas. Quotas can be assigned to users for all printers on which a quota is
			enabled (see <xref linkend="quota:config:activate"/>) under <guimenu>more -> Edit quota</guimenu>. A list of all users for which
			quotas are configured is displayed. <guimenu>Add new record</guimenu> can now be used to add an
			additional entry: A user is selected under <guimenu>User name</guimenu> and a <guimenu>soft limit</guimenu>
			and <guimenu>hard limit</guimenu> has to be specified. The page counter can be reset to zero under
			<guimenu>more -> Reset user quota</guimenu>.
		  </para>

		  <figure id="printquota-listquota">
			<title>List of configured print quotas</title>
			<graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/printquota-umc2.png"/>
		  </figure>

		</section>
	  </section>
	</section>

	<section id="quota:query">
	  <title>Querying the printer quotas</title>
	  <para>
		The quota data can only be queried if print quota is enabled on at least one printer
		share; otherwise, <command>repykota</command> delivers an error message: <computeroutput>/usr/bin/repykota : There's
		no printer matching *</computeroutput>.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The quota status can be viewed for all users using the command <command>repykota</command>
		or alternatively for a single user with  <command>repykota USERNAME</command>:

<screen>
:~# repykota
Report for user quota on printer HP ()
Pages grace time: 7 days
Price per job: 0.000
Price per page: 0.000
User           overcharge used  soft hard  balance grace     total
------------------------------------------------------------------
Administrator   -Q   1.0     0   500  1000     0.00             20
user            -Q   1.0    20   100   200     0.00             20
                                                 Total :        40
                                                  Real :         0
</screen>
	  </para>
	</section>

	<section id="quota:reset">
	  <title>Resetting the printer quotas</title>
	  <para>
		The page counter for a user can be reset either with the UMC module <guimenu>Printer
		moderation</guimenu> (see <xref linkend="printquota:umcmodule"/>) or in the command line
		using the command <command>edpykota reset</command>:

<screen>
:~# edpykota --reset user01
Extracting datas...
Modification...
Done.
</screen>
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The following command removes the print quota for a user on all printer shares:

<programlisting language="sh">
edpykota --delete user01
</programlisting>
		or on a specific printer:
<programlisting language="sh">
edpykota --delete user01 --printer labelprinter
</programlisting>
	  </para>

	</section>

  </chapter>
</book>
