<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="windows:ntdomain">
    <bookinfo>
      <title>Univention Corporate Server</title>
		<subtitle>Operation of a Samba domain based on Windows NT domain services</subtitle>

        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>4.0-0</revnumber>
                <date>18 Nov 2014</date>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </bookinfo>

	<chapter id="windows:ntsetup">
	  <title>Components of a Samba domain</title>

	  <para>
		NT domains are the predecessor of Active Directory from a technical perspective. This
		document is predominantly relevant for existing installations which have yet to perform
		migration to an AD-based domain. Migration from a NT-based Samba domain to a domain with
		Active Directory services is described in the Univention Wiki <biblioref
		linkend="wiki-samba-update"/>. For new installations, we highly recommend the use of an AD-based
		domain.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		A Samba NT domain is composed of at least one domain controller. Windows clients and member
		servers can join the trust context of the Samba domain as domain members. Member servers do
		not provide login services, but may offer file and print services, for example. In addition to
		a member server domain join of Windows Server systems, Samba can also act as a member server.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Domain joining of Windows clients and Microsoft Windows member servers is described in
		chapter <emphasis>Domain services / LDAP directory</emphasis> of the UCS manual
		<biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Microsoft Windows domain controllers cannot join the Samba domain.
	  </para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="windows:setup3">
	  <title>Installation</title>

	  <para>
		Samba as a NT domain controller can be installed on all UCS domain controllers by installing
		the software package <package>univention-samba</package>.
		(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> command must be run after installation).
		Additional information can be found in chapter <emphasis>Software deployment</emphasis> of
		the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		A Samba member server can be installed on UCS member servers from the Univention App Center
		with the application <emphasis>Windows-compatible fileserver</emphasis>. Alternatively, the
		software package <package>univention-samba</package> can be installed
		(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> command must be run after
		installation).
		Additional information can be found in chapter <emphasis>Software deployment</emphasis> of
		the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
	  </para>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="windows:samba3:services">
	  <title>Services of a Samba domain</title>
	  <section id="windows:samba3:services:auth">
		<title>Authentication services</title>

		<para>
		  User logins can only be performed on Microsoft Windows systems joined in the Samba
		  domain. Domain joins are documented in the chapter <emphasis>Domain services / LDAP
		  directory</emphasis> of the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The user passwords are saved in the UCS LDAP. Users are authenticated against the LDAP
		  directory when logging into the domain with their username and password, and can then
		  access all the shared resources of the domain without having to enter their username and
		  password again. Computers with any kind of Windows operating systems are authenticated in
		  the same way as in Windows NT domains, via the <systemitem class="protocol">NTLMv2</systemitem> protocol.
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="windows:samba3:fileservices">
		<title>File services</title>

		<para>
		  A file server provides files over the network and allows concentrating the storage of user data on a
		  central server.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The file services integrated in UCS support the provision of shares using the CIFS
		  protocol. Insofar as the underlying file system supports Access Control Lists (ACLs) (can
		  be used with ext3, ext4 and XFS), the ACLs can also be used by Windows clients.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Samba supports the CIFS protocol and the successor SMB2 to provide file services. Using a client
		  which supports SMB2 (as of Windows Vista, i.e., Windows 7/8 too) improves the performance
		  and scalability.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The protocol can be configured using the &ucsUCR; variable
		  <envar>samba/max/protocol</envar>. It must be set on all Samba servers and then all Samba
		  server(s) restarted.

		  <itemizedlist>
			<listitem><simpara>
			  <guimenuitem>NT1</guimenuitem> configures CIFS (supported by all Windows versions)
			</simpara></listitem>

			<listitem><simpara>
			  <guimenuitem>SMB2</guimenuitem> configures SMB2 (supported as of Windows Vista/Windows 7)
			</simpara></listitem>

			<listitem><simpara>
			  <guimenuitem>SMB3</guimenuitem> configures SMB3 (supported as of Windows 8) (currently not covered by Univention support)
			</simpara></listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="windows:samba:services:print">
		<title>Print services</title>
		<para>
		  Samba offers the possibility of sharing printers set up under Linux as network printers
		  for Windows clients. The management of the printer shares and the provision of the printer
		  drivers is described in chapter <emphasis>Print services</emphasis> of the UCS manual
		  <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="windows:netbios">
		<title>NetBIOS name service</title>

		<para>
		  NetBIOS is a network protocol for host names and for network communication of Windows
		  clients. It is primarily used for NT-compatible domains; the name resolution in Active
		  Directory is based on DNS. Samba provides NetBIOS functions with the
		  <systemitem class="service">nmbd</systemitem> system service.
		</para>

		<para>
		  NetBIOS computer names can have a maximum of 13 characters. The NetBIOS name of a UCS
		  system corresponds to the host name by default.
		</para>

		<para>
		  In a native Active Directory environment, there are no NetBIOS services provided as
		  standard. In an AD environment based on Samba, however, it is activated. This can be
		  deactivated with the &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba4/service/nmb</envar>.
		</para>
	  </section>

	  <section id="windows:wins">
		<title>Name resolution using WINS</title>
		<para>
		  Similar to DNS in TCP/IP networks, the <emphasis>Windows Internet Name Service
		  (WINS)</emphasis> is used for resolving NetBIOS names into IP addresses. In addition, WINS
		  provides information on the services of the hosts.
		</para>

		<para>
		  WINS is used in NT-compatible Samba domains; in Samba AD domains, the name resolution
		  generally occurs primarily via DNS (WINS is also available).
		</para>

		<para>
		  WINS support is activated on the &ucsMaster; in the default setting and can also be
		  operated on another server by setting the &ucsUCRV;
		  <envar>windows/wins-support</envar>. WINS can only be operated without adjustments on one
		  Samba server in the domain; distribution across several servers requires the setup of WINS
		  replication. Information on the commissioning of the WINS replication can be found in the
		  Univention Support database at <u:sdb>1107</u:sdb>.
		</para>

		<para>
			The WINS server can be assigned to Windows clients via a <wordasword>DHCP-NetBIOS</wordasword> policy, see chapter
		  <emphasis>IP and network management</emphasis> of the UCS manual <biblioref
		  linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
		</para>
	  </section>
	</chapter>


	<chapter id="windows:samba3:desktopmanagement">
	  <title>Configuration and management of Windows desktops</title>

	  <section id="netlogon-freigabe">
		<title>Logon scripts / NETLOGON share</title>
		<para>
		  The NETLOGON share serves the purpose of providing logon scripts in Windows domains. The
		  logon scripts are executed following after the user login and allow the adaptation of the
		  user's working environment. Scripts have to be saved in a format which can be executed by
		  Windows, such as <emphasis>bat</emphasis>.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The directory <filename>/var/lib/samba/netlogon</filename> is set up as the Samba share
		  <emphasis>NETLOGON</emphasis>.
		</para>

		<para>
		  In the default setting, all adjustments are made in the
		  <filename class="directory">/var/lib/samba/netlogon/</filename> directory on the &ucsMaster; and synchronised
		  hourly on all domain controllers with Samba installed via the <command>rsync</command>
		  tool.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/logonscript</envar> is available for defining a global logon
		  script for all users. If this variable is set on a Samba server, then all users logging
		  into this Samba server have the specified logon script assigned. The logon script can also
		  be assigned user-specifically in the &ucsUMC;.
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="windows:serverhome:samba3">
		<title>Configuration of the file server for the home directory</title>

		<para>
		  As standard, the home directory of each user is shared by Samba and connected with the
		  <emphasis>I:</emphasis> drive after login in Windows.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/homedirserver</envar> can be used to specify the server on
		  which the home directories should be stored; the &ucsUCRV;
		  <envar>samba/homedirpath</envar> can be used to specify the directory. These values will
		  then be valid for all the users.
		</para>

		<para>
		  It it also possible to make individual assignment in the user settings in the &ucsUMC;
		  with the setting <guimenu>Windows home path</guimenu>, e.g.,
		  <userinput>\\ucs-file-server\smith</userinput>.
		</para>

		<para>
		  If instead of the user's UNIX home directory, a different UNIX directory is to be
		  displayed as the home directory on the Windows drive, then this server and the home
		  directory need to be entered in the <guimenu>Windows home path</guimenu> entry field.
		</para>
	  </section>


	  <section id="windows:roamingprofiles">
		<title>Roaming profiles</title>
		<para>
		  Samba supports roaming profiles, i.e., user settings are saved on a central server. This
		  directory is also used for storing the files which the user saves in the <emphasis>My
		  Documents</emphasis> folder. Initially, these files are stored locally on the Windows
		  computer and then synchronised onto the Samba server when the user logs off.
		</para>

		<para>
		  If the profile path is changed in the &ucsUMC;, then a new profile directory will be
		  created. The data in the old profile directory will be kept. These data can be manually
		  copied or moved to the new profile directory. Finally, the old profile directory can be
		  deleted.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The user profiles are saved in the
		  <filename>windows-profiles\&lt;Windows-Version&gt;</filename> subdirectory on the Samba
		  server that the user logged on to.
		</para>

		<para>
		  &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/profileserver</envar> can be used to specify another server and
		  <envar>samba/profilepath</envar>to specify another directory. These settings must be set
		  on all Samba domain controllers.
		</para>

		<para>
		  In the user management of the &ucsUMC;, the input field <guimenu>Windows profile
		  directory</guimenu> can be set to configure a different path or another server for the
		  profile  directory for the user.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Roaming profiles can be deactivated by configuring the &ucsUCR; variables
		  <envar>samba/profilepath</envar> and <envar>samba/profileserver</envar> to
		  <emphasis>local</emphasis> and restarting the Samba server. The UMC setting from the input
		  field <guimenu>Windows profile directory</guimenu> must also be set empty.
		</para>
	  </section>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="vertrauensstellungen_generell">
	  <title>Trust relationships</title>
	  <para>
		Trust relationships between domains make it possible for users from one domain to log on to
		computers from another domain.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Trust settings are not supported by in Samba domains based on Active Directory.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		If a Windows domain trusts a Samba domain, there is also the possibility to log on to the
		Samba domain alongside the Windows domain when logging on to computers belonging to the Windows
		domain.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		If a Samba domain trusts a Windows domain, users from the Windows domain enter the user name
		<emphasis>&lt;name-of-windows-domain&gt;+&lt;username&gt;</emphasis> when logging on to a Linux
		computer belonging to the Samba domain.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		When setting up and using the trust relationship the domain controllers of both domains must be
		able to reach each other over the network and identify each other using broadcasts or WINS.
	  </para>



	  <para>
		Two steps generally need to be performed to establish a trust relation:

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>
			A domain trust account needs to be created in the "trusted" domain.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			The trust relation needs to be established in the "trusting" domain. This is done by
			logging in to the "trusting" domain with administrative  privileges and running the tool
			for domain trust administration provided by the domain controller (Microsoft Windows or
			Samba) to establish an "outgoing" trust (as it is called in the Microsoft terminology).
			The credentials of the trust account for the "trusted" domain need to be entered. This
			trust account is required by the "trusting" domain for name resolution in the "trusted"
			domain.
		  </simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Trust relations can be configured unidirectional or bidirectional. Technically a
		bidirectional trust is simply realised as two unidirectional trusts; one in each direction.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The terminology of unidirectional trusts depends on the perspective of either the "trusting"
		or the "trusted" domain. From the perspective of the "trusting" domain the trust is called
		"outgoing".  From the perspective of the "trusted" domain the trust is called "incoming".
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Further information on the configuration of trust relationships on Microsoft Windows can be found in
		<xref linkend="windows-trust"/>.
	  </para>

	  <section id="windows:trustdom:windows-trusts-samba">
		<title>Windows domain trusts Samba domain</title>
		<para>
		  A <emphasis>Domain Trust Account</emphasis> with a name reflecting the NetBIOS name of the
		  Windows domain and a password issued for the account must be created in the computer
		  management module of &ucsUMC;  The password quality requirements which may apply to Windows
		  domains must be observed.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Trust settings can only be set up on domain controllers.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		  An outgoing trust relationship must be created on the Windows PDC.
		</para>

		<para>
		  The trust relationship between the Windows domain and the Samba domain can be removed by
		  deleting the trust relationship on the Windows PDC and the domain trust account in the
		  &ucsUMC;.
		</para>
	  </section>
	  
	  <section id="windows:trustdom:samba-trusts-windows">
		<title>Samba domain trusts Windows domain</title>
		<para>
		  The following steps are used to set up the trust setting on a &ucsSlave; as a
		  <emphasis>root</emphasis> user:
		</para>

		<para>
		  The <package>winbind</package> package must be installed. Winbind maps UNIX IDs to Windows
		  users and groups
		</para>

		<para>
		  An incoming trust relationship must be created on the Windows PDC.
		</para>

		<para>
		  If Univention Firewall is used, replies to NetBIOS broadcasts need to be allowed:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="sh">
echo "iptables -I INPUT 1 -p udp --sport 137 -j ACCEPT" \
    &gt;&gt; /etc/security/packetfilter.d/50_local.sh
/etc/init.d/univention-firewall restart
		</programlisting>

		<para>
		  The trust relationship is now initiated and Winbind restarted. This command must be run on all
		  Samba login servers:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="sh">
net rpc trustdom establish &lt;Windows domain&gt;
net setauthuser -UAdministrator (enter the Windows Administrator password)
ucr set samba/winbind/rpc/only=yes
/etc/init.d/winbind restart
ucr set auth/methods="krb5 ldap unix winbind"
/etc/init.d/nscd restart
		</programlisting>

		<para>
		  The following command can be used to check that the trust relationship has been added
		  correctly:
		</para>
		<programlisting language="sh">
net rpc trustdom list
		</programlisting>
	  </section>
	</chapter>

  <bibliography id="bibliography">
    <bibliomixed id="ucs-handbuch"/>
    <bibliomixed id="wiki-samba-update"/>
    <bibliomixed id="windows-trust"/>
  </bibliography>

    <?dbhtml-include href="../stylesheets/piwik.html"?>
</book>
