<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%entities;
]>
<book lang="en" id="quickstart-en-4.4">
<bookinfo>
  <title>Univention Corporate Server</title>
  <subtitle>Quick start guide for Univention Corporate Server</subtitle>
</bookinfo>

<chapter id="quickstart:intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>
	Univention Corporate Server (UCS) is a server operating system based on Debian GNU/Linux with
	integrated management system for the central administration of servers, services, clients,
	desktops and users.
  </para>

  <para>
	This quickstart guide offers a short introduction on how to get started with UCS. Several
	features of UCS are only mentioned briefly with a reference to further documentation. The
	documentation on UCS is available at <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The installation DVD can be downloaded from the Univention website at
	<ulink url="https://www.univention.com/downloads/ucs-download/iso-installation-image/"/>.
	The installation DVD is only available for the host architecture amd64 (64-bit). It has support for the Unified
	Extensible Firmware Interface-Standard (UEFI) including SecureBoot.
  </para>

  <para>
	Alternatively preinstalled images for VMware and VirtualBox can be used. These are available for
	download at <ulink
	url="https://www.univention.com/downloads/ucs-download/preinstalled-vm-images/"/>..
  </para>

  <para>
	The system requirements vary considerably depending on the intended purpose and the number of
	users. The minimum requirements for the installation are 1 GB memory and 8 GB hard drive
	space.
  </para>
</chapter>

<chapter id="quickstart:installation">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <para>
	The installation is performed via a menu-driven installer and can be used both
	interactively and completely profile-based <biblioref linkend="ext-doc-inst"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The system language, keyboard layout and time zone can be selected in accordance with local
	requirements.
  </para>

  <para>
	A valid network configuration should be set during the installation. If, for example, a
	gateway and a name server are specified, but the name server cannot be reached, this may
	result in unnecessary timeouts. In these cases, it makes more sense not to specify a gateway.
	The network configuration can be employed using DHCP.
	If there is already a name server available in the local network, it should be used. If
	additional UCS systems are installed in the domain at a later point in time, the &ucsMaster; and
	any &ucsBackup; systems should be entered as name servers.
  </para>

  <figure id="quick-systemrole">
	<title>Selecting the domain setup</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/systemrole-en.png"/>
  </figure>

  <para>
      During installation, the system can be used for various purposes which
      can only be configured at this point in the setup process.

	<itemizedlist>
        <listitem><simpara>
                The system is to be the first system in a new UCS domain
                and it is implicitly configured with the system role &ucsMaster;
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
                The system can be joined into an existing Active Directory
                domain. Select this option if UCS should not create a new domain.
				UCS then takes on the role of an Active Directory member server.
		</simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
                All other systems are joining the UCS domain when they are installed.
        </simpara></listitem>
        <listitem><simpara>
                The base system is the exception here; this system does not
                join any domain and also does not offer a management system. As
                such, it is only used in a few scenarios – as a firewall
                system, for example.
        </simpara></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    An overview of the other different system roles can be found in <biblioref
    linkend="ucs-systemrole"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
      With UCS and the <guimenu>Active Directory Takeover</guimenu> an existing
      Active Directory domain can be migrated completely to UCS. For
      information on how to set up the UCS system for this scenario, see <biblioref
      linkend="ad-takeover"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	In the subsequent course of the installation, the fully qualified host name, under which the
	computer should be accessible in the network, is entered for a &ucsMaster;. A local
	name should also be used as the domain name in this case, e.g.,
	<systemitem class="domainname">company.intranet</systemitem>. (If the system is used as a mail server, for example,
	the mail domains can be used independently of the domain names).
	For example, to commission the <systemitem class="systemname">mailserver</systemitem> host system in the
	<systemitem class="domainname">company.intranet</systemitem> DNS domain,
	<systemitem class="fqdomainname">mailserver.company.intranet</systemitem> should be entered as the fully qualified host
	name.
	The <guimenu>LDAP base</guimenu> is suggested based on the fully qualified host name and
	only needs to be adjusted in exceptional cases. The root password must be at least eight
	characters long and is also set as the password for the user <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis>
	during the installation of the first UCS system (&ucsMaster;).
  </para>

  <para>
	An autopartitioning feature can be used during the installation which creates an LVM volume group on the first
	hard drive by default.
  </para>

  <para>
	The installed software components can be adapted later at any time and subsequently installed
	from the Univention App Center.
  </para>

  <para>
	After confirming the configuration settings the installation is initiated. Once completed, the
	system must be restarted. The further configuration is made using the &ucsUMC; (UMC).
  </para>

</chapter>

<chapter id="quickstart:administration">
  <title>UCS web interface</title>

  <para>
	The web interface of an installed UCS system is directly available via its IP address
	(<uri>https://<replaceable>server_ip</replaceable></uri> or <uri>http://<replaceable>server_ip</replaceable></uri>, HTTPS is recommended).
	By default, a portal page is configured on the &ucsMaster; where all applications are listed that are installed in the domain.
	For all other system roles, the start site consists of an overview of all locally installed applications.
	(View as well as the partitioning of entries can be customized in a very flexible manner, see also <biblioref linkend="ucs-portal"/>.)
  </para>

  <figure id="quick-ucs-portal">
	<title>Illustration of the portal page on the &ucsMaster; with all domain wide available applications</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/ucs-portal-en.png"/>
  </figure>

  <para>
	On each start site of a UCS system, there is an entry <guimenu>System and domain settings</guimenu> in the section <guimenu>Administration</guimenu> (or <guimenu>System settings</guimenu>, respectively) that points to the &ucsUMC; (UMC) of the local system.
	&ucsUMC; is the central tool for web-based administration of a UCS domain.
	There are different modules available on the UCS system depending on the installation and system role selected.
	The login to &ucsUMC; is performed as user <systemitem class="username">Administrator</systemitem> with the
	password specified for the user <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> during the installation.
  </para>

  <para>
	For administrating UCS, the LDAP directory is the central component of a UCS domain.
	In the LDAP, domain wide information such as the users, groups and computer accounts is saved.
	Depending on the settings, this information is replicated to the other domain controllers in the domain either completely or selectively.
	The UMC modules which edit the LDAP directory directly can be accessed only on the &ucsMaster; via &ucsUMC;.
	Furthermore, they can also be controlled using the command line interface &ucsUDM;
	<biblioref linkend="ucs-udm"/>.
  </para>

  <figure id="quick-umc-overview">
	<title>Modules in the UMC</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/umc-modules-en.png"/>
  </figure>

</chapter>

<chapter id="quickstart:updatesinstall">
  <title>UCS updates / Installing additional software</title>

  <para>
	UCS updates can be installed in the UMC module <guimenu>Software update</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
    Additional software, like for example the Active Directory Connection, can be
    installed using the Univention App Center in the Univention Management
    Console:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		Additional UCS software can be installed/removed using the category <guimenu>UCS
		components</guimenu>.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Third-party software (e.g. various groupware solutions) and UCS-compatible addon products
		(e.g. UCS@school for school deployment can also be installed through the App Center.
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<figure id="quick-appcenter">
	  <title>Subsequent installation of UCS components</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/appcenter-en.png"/>
	</figure>

  </para>
</chapter>

<chapter id="quickstart:ucr">
  <title>Configuration management using Univention Configuration Registry</title>

  <para>
	Univention Configuration Registry is the central tool for managing the local system
	configuration of a UCS system. Settings are specified in a consistent format, the so-called
	Univention Configuration Registry variables. These variables are used to generate the
	configuration files used effectively by the services/programs. Direct editing of the
	configuration files is only needed in exceptional cases.
  </para>

  <para>
	&ucsUCR; variables are managed via the &ucsUMC; module <guimenu>Univention Configuration
	Registry</guimenu>. Configuration files are automatically updated when the UCR variables
	registered on them are changed.
  </para>

  <figure id="quick-ucr">
	<title>Managing &ucsUCR; variables</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/ucr-en.png"/>
  </figure>

</chapter>

<chapter id="quickstart:clients">
  <title>Clients</title>

	<para>
	  In addition to the UCS systems, a UCS domain can also integrate different clients. The
	  following clients are supported:

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>
		  Microsoft Windows clients can join an AD-compatible Windows domain provided by the <emphasis>Active
		  Directory compatible domain controller</emphasis> component (implemented using the software Samba).
		  Further information on setting up Samba and the domain join of Windows clients
		  can be found in the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-winjoin"/>.
		</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  Mac OS X systems are also integrated via a Samba-based, AD-compatible Windows
		  domain. Further information on setting up Samba and the domain join can
		  be found in the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-macjoin"/>.
		</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  Univention Corporate Client can be installed from the Univention App Center for the deployment of
		  centrally administrated Linux-based desktop. Further information can be found in the UCC
		  manual <biblioref linkend="ucc-manual"/>.
		</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  Ubuntu systems <biblioref linkend="ubuntu-join"/> and other Linux distributions like
		  Debian, SUSE or Red Hat can also be integrated into the domain <biblioref linkend="integrate-other-linux"/>.
		</simpara></listitem>


	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
</chapter>

<chapter id="quickstart:extend">
  <title>Further expansion of the domain</title>

  <para>
	This quickstart guide only provides an entry into UCS. UCS is very scalable, additional services
	can simply be installed on additional systems. This domain join is described in <biblioref
	linkend="ucs-join"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	UCS offers various additional services which are covered by the UCS license and which can be
	integrated at a later point in time:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		Single-sign-on with web services using a SAML identity provider <biblioref linkend="domain-saml"/>
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		IP management using DHCP <biblioref linkend="ucs-dhcp"/>
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Web proxy for caching and policy management / virus scan <biblioref linkend="ucs-proxy"/>
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Service monitoring with Nagios <biblioref linkend="ucs-nagios"/>
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Hybrid cloud setups <biblioref linkend="ucs-uvmm"/>
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>
</chapter>


<chapter id="quickstart:furtherinfo">
  <title>Further information</title>

  <para>
	&ucsUCS; provides comprehensive documentation:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		The primary source of information on UCS is the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-handbuch"/>.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Further documentation for advanced scenarios can be found in the extended documentation. The
		various documents are linked at <ulink url="https://docs.software-univention.de/"/>.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		The Univention Wiki (<ulink url="https://wiki.univention.de/"/>) contains several HOWTOs and
		hands-on tips.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Answers to frequently asked questions can be found in the support and knowledge database (SDB)
		(<ulink url="https://help.univention.com/c/knowledge-base/supported/"/>).
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		Questions on UCS can be asked at Univention Help <ulink url="https://help.univention.com/"/>.
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>


</chapter>

<bibliography id="bibliography">
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-handbuch"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-systemrole"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ad-takeover"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-winjoin"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-macjoin"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucc-manual"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ext-doc-inst"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-uvmm"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-proxy"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-nagios"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-dhcp"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ubuntu-join"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-portal"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-udm"/>
  <bibliomixed id="ucs-join"/>
  <bibliomixed id="domain-saml"/>
  <bibliomixed id="integrate-other-linux"/>
</bibliography>
</book>
