<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="groups">
	<title>Group management</title>

		<para>
			Permissions in UCS are predominantly differentiated between on the
			basis of <emphasis>groups</emphasis>. Groups are stored in the LDAP and are thus
			identical on all systems. Groups can contain not only user accounts,
			but can also optionally accept computer accounts.
		</para>
		<para>
			In addition, there are also local user groups on each system, which
			are predominantly used for hardware access. These are not managed
			through the &ucsUMS;, but saved in the <filename>/etc/group</filename> file.
		</para>
		<para>
			The assignment of users to groups is performed in two ways:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<simpara>
					A selection of groups can be assigned to a user in the user
					management (see <xref linkend="users::management"/>)
					</simpara>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<simpara>
					A selection of users can be assigned to a group in the group
					management (see <xref linkend="groups::management"/>)
					</simpara>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>

	<section id="groups::management">
		<title>Managing groups in &ucsUMC;</title>
		<para>
			Groups are managed in the UMC module <emphasis>Groups</emphasis>
			(see <xref linkend="central:user-interface"/>).
		</para>
		<figure id="create-group">
			<title>Creating a group in UMC</title>
			<graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/create-group_EN.png"/>
		</figure>
		<table>
			<title>'General' tab</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="attribute" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="description" colwidth="2*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Attribute</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Name (*)</entry>
						<entry>
                            <para>
							  The name of the group has to begin and end with a letter or a
							  numeral. The rest of the characters which form the group name may
							  include letters, numerals, spaces, hyphens, or dots.
							</para>
                            <para>
							  In the default setting, it is not possible to create a group with the same name as an existing user.
							  If the &ucsUCRV; <envar>directory/manager/user_group/uniqueness</envar> is set to <literal>false</literal>,
							  this check is removed.
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Description</entry>
						<entry>
							A description of the group can be entered here.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Users</entry>
						<entry>
							This input field can be used for adding users as members to the group.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Groups</entry>
						<entry>
							On this input field, other groups can be added as members of the current group
							(groups in groups).
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>

		<table>
			<title>'Advanced settings' tab</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="attribute" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="description" colwidth="2*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Attribute</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Mail</entry>
						<entry>
							These options define a mail group and are documented in the
							<xref linkend="mail::management::mailgroups"/>.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Host members</entry>
						<entry>
							This field can be used for accepting computers as members of the
							group.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Nested groups</entry>
						<entry>
							The current group can be added as a member to other groups here (groups in groups).
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Group ID</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								If a group is to be assigned a certain group ID, the ID in question
								can be entered in this field. Otherwise, &ucsUMC;
								will automatically assign the next available group ID when
								adding the group. The group ID cannot be subsequently changed. When
								editing the group, the group ID will be represented in gray.
							</para>
							<para>
								The group ID may consist of integers between 1000 and 59999 and
								between 65536 and 100000.
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Windows &ar; Relative ID</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>
								The relative ID (RID) is the local part of the Security ID (SID) and
								is used in Windows and Samba domains. If a group is to be assigned a
								certain RID, the ID in question can be entered in this
								field. Otherwise, &ucsUMC; will automatically
								assign the next available group ID when adding the group.
							</para>
							<para>
								The RID cannot be subsequently changed. When editing the group, the group ID
								will be represented in gray.
							</para>
							<para>
								The RIDs below 1000 are reserved for standard groups and other special objects.
							</para>
							<para>
								When Samba 4 is used, the RID is generated by Samba and cannot be specified.
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
					  <entry>Windows &ar; group type</entry>
					  <entry>
						This group type is evaluated when the user logs on to a Samba/AD-based domain
						Three types of Windows groups can be distinguished:

						<itemizedlist>
						  <listitem><simpara>
							<emphasis>Domain Groups</emphasis> are known across the domain. This is the
							default group time.
						  </simpara></listitem>

						  <listitem><simpara>
							<emphasis>Local groups</emphasis> are only relevant on Windows servers.
							If a local group is created on a Windows server, this group is known
							solely to the server; it is not available across the domain. UCS, in
							contrast, does not differentiate between local and global groups. After
							taking over an AD domain, local groups in UCS can be handled in the same
							way as global groups.
						  </simpara></listitem>

						  <listitem><simpara>
							<emphasis>Well-known group</emphasis>: This group type covers groups
							preconfigured by Samba/Windows servers which generally have special
							privileges, e.g., <systemitem class="groupname">Power Users</systemitem>.
						  </simpara> </listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					  </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
					  <entry>Windows &ar; AD group type</entry>
					  <entry>
						This group type is only evaluated when the user logs on to a Samba 4-based
						domain (which offers Active Directory domain services).  These groups are
						described in <xref linkend="groups:adgroups"/>.
					  </entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>Windows &ar; Samba privileges</entry>
						<entry>
							This input mask can be used to assign Windows system rights to a
							group, e.g., the right to join a Windows client in the domain. This
							function is documented in <xref linkend="users::management"/>.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<table>
			<title>'Options' tab</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="attribute" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="description" colwidth="2*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry namest="attribute" nameend="description">
						  This tab is only available when adding groups, not when editing
						  groups. Certain LDAP object classes for the group can be de-selected
						  here. The entry fields for the attributes of these classes can then no
						  longer be filled in.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Attribute</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Samba group</entry>
						<entry>
							This checkbox indicates whether the group contains the object class
							<classname>sambaGroupMapping</classname>.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>POSIX group</entry>
						<entry>
							This checkbox indicates whether the group contains the object class
							<classname>posixGroup</classname>.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>

	<section id="groups::nested">
		<title>Nested groups</title>
		<para>
			UCS supports group nesting (also known as "groups in groups"). This
			simplifies the management of the groups. For example, if two locations
			are managed in one domain, two groups can be formed <systemitem class="groupname">IT staff location A</systemitem>
			and <systemitem class="groupname">IT staff location B</systemitem>), to which the user
			accounts of the location's IT staff can be assigned respectively.
		</para>
		<para>
			To create a cross-location group, it is then sufficient to
			define the groups <systemitem class="groupname">IT staff location A</systemitem> and <systemitem class="groupname">IT staff location B</systemitem>
			as members.
		</para>
		<para>
			Cyclic dependencies of nested groups are automatically detected and
			refused. This check can be disabled with the
			&ucsUCRV; <envar>directory/manager/web/modules/groups/group/checks/circular_dependency</envar>.
			Cyclic memberships must also be avoided in direct group changes
			without the &ucsUMS;.
		</para>
		<para>
			The resolution of nested group memberships is performed
			during the generation of the group cache (see <xref linkend="groups::cache"/>)
			and is thus transparent for applications.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="groups::cache">
		<title>Local group cache</title>
		<para>
		  The user and computer information retrieved from the LDAP is cached by the Name Server
		  Cache Daemon, see <xref linkend="computers:nscd"/>.
		</para>

		<para>
		  Since UCS 3.1, the groups are no longer cached via the NSCD for performance and
		  stability reasons; instead they are now cached by the NSS module
		  <package>libnss-extrausers</package>. The group information is automatically exported to
		  the <filename>/var/lib/extrausers/group</filename> file by the
		  <filename>/usr/lib/univention-pam/ldap-group-to-file.py</filename> script and read
		  from there by the NSS module.
		</para>

		<para>
		  In the basic setting, the export is performed every 15 minutes by a cron job and is
		  additionally started if the &ucsUDL; has been inactive for 15
		  seconds. The interval for the cron update is configured in Cron syntax (see <xref
		  linkend="cron:local"/>) by the &ucsUCRV;
		  <envar>nss/group/cachefile/invalidate_interval</envar>. This listener module can be
		  activated/deactivated via the &ucsUCRV;
		  <envar>nss/group/invalidate_cache_on_changes</envar> (<literal>true</literal>/<literal>false</literal>).
		</para>

		<para>
		  When the group cache file is being generated, the script verifies whether the group
		  members are still present in the LDAP directory. If only &ucsUMC; is used for user
		  management, this additional check is not necessary and can be
		  disabled by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>nss/group/cachefile/check_member</envar> to
		  <literal>false</literal>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="groups:adgroups">
	  <title>Synchronization of Active Directory groups when using Samba 4</title>
	  <para>
		If Samba 4 is used, the group memberships are synchronized between the Samba 4 directory
		service and the OpenLDAP directory service by the Univention S4 connector, i.e., each group
		on the UCS side is associated with a group in Active Directory. General information on the
		Univention S4 connector can be found in <xref linkend="windows:s4connector"/>.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		Some exceptions are formed by the <emphasis>pseudo groups</emphasis> (sometimes also called
		system groups). These are only managed internally by Active Directory/Samba 4, e.g., the
		<systemitem class="groupname">Authenticated Users</systemitem> group includes a list of all the users currently
		logged on to the system. Pseudo groups are stored in the UCS directory service, but they are
		not synchronized by the Univention S4 connector and should usually not be edited. This
		applies to the following groups:

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Anonymous Logon</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Authenticated Users</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Batch</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Creator Group</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Creator Owner</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Dialup</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Digest Authentication</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Enterprise Domain Controllers</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Everyone</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">IUSR</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Interactive</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Local Service</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">NTLM Authentication</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Network Service</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Network</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Nobody</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Null Authority</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Other Organization</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Owner Rights</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Proxy</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Remote Interactive Logon</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Restricted</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">SChannel Authentication</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">Self</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Service</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">System</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">Terminal Server User</systemitem>, <systemitem class="groupname">This Organization</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		  <listitem><simpara><systemitem class="groupname">World Authority</systemitem></simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  </para>

	  <para>
		In Samba 4 / Active Directory, a distinction is made between the following four AD group
		types. These group types can be applied to two types of groups;
		<emphasis>security groups</emphasis> configure permissions (corresponding to the UCS groups),
		whilst <emphasis>distribution groups</emphasis> are used for mailing lists:

		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem><simpara>
			<emphasis>Local</emphasis> groups only exist locally on a host. A local group created in
			Samba 4 is synchronized by the Univention S4 Connector and thus also appears in the
			UMC. There is no need to create local groups in the UMC.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			<emphasis>Global</emphasis> groups are the standard type for newly created groups in the
			UMC. A global group applies for one domain, but it can also accept members from other
			domains. If there is a trust relationship with a domain, the groups there are displayed
			and permissions can be assigned. However, the current version of UCS does not support
			multiple domains/forests or outgoing trust relationships.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			<emphasis>Domain local</emphasis> groups can also adopt members of other domains
			(insofar as there is a trust relationship in place or they form part of a forest). Local
			domain groups are only shown in their own domain though. However, the current version of
			UCS does not support multiple domains/forests or outgoing trust relationships.
		  </simpara></listitem>

		  <listitem><simpara>
			<emphasis>Universal</emphasis> groups can adopt members from all domains and these
			members are also shown in all the domains of a forest. These groups are stored in a
			separate segment of the directory service, the so-called global catalog. Domain
			forests are currently not supported by Samba 4.
		  </simpara></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</section>


	<section id="groups::memberof">
	  <title>Overlay module for displaying the group information on user objects</title>
	  <para>
		In the UCS directory service, group membership properties are only saved in the group
		objects and not in the respective user objects. However, some applications expect group
		membership properties at the user objects (e.g., in the attribute
		<property>memberOf</property>). An optional overlay module in the LDAP server makes it
		possible to present these attributes automatically based on the group information. The
		additional attributes are not written to the LDAP, but displayed on the fly by the
		overlay module if a user object is queried.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		To this end, the <package>univention-ldap-overlay-memberof</package> package must be
		installed on all LDAP servers.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		In the default setting, the user attribute <property>memberOf</property> is shown. The
		&ucsUCRV; <envar>ldap/overlay/memberof/memberof</envar> can be used to configure
		a different attribute.
	  </para>
	</section>

</chapter>
