<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-de.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="idmcloud">
	<title>Identity Management connection to cloud services</title>
	<section id="idmcloud:general">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			UCS offers an integrated Identity Management System. Through &ucsUMC;, users and groups among others
			can easily be administered. Depending on the installed services, these identities are made available through
			different interfaces e.g. via LDAP.
		</para>

		<para>
			The management system can be extended with the help of provided extensions, also called Apps. Thus users or
			groups can also be replicated in cloud services. In the App center there are also among others extensions for
			Microsoft 365 or G Suite.
		</para>

		<para>
			Thanks to Single Sign-On (SSO), users can log in with their usual password and immediately get to work
			online in the cloud. The password remains in the company's network and is not transferred to the cloud service.
		</para>

		<para>
			The following chapter describes how to set up the Microsoft 365 Connector and the Google Apps for Work Connector.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section id="idmcloud:o365">
		<title>Microsoft 365 Connector</title>

		<para>
			The synchronization of users and groups to an Azure Directory Domain, which will then be used by Microsoft 365,
			is made possible by the Microsoft Office connector. The connector makes it possible to control which of the users created in
			UCS can use Microsoft 365. The selected users will be provisioned accordingly into the Azure Active Directory
			domain. It is configurable which user attributes are synchronized and which are anonymized during synchronization.
		</para>

		<para>
			The Single Sign-On log-in to Microsoft 365 is done via the UCS integrated SAML implementation. Authentication takes
			place against the UCS server, and no password hashes are transmitted to Microsoft Azure Cloud. The user's authentication
			is done exclusively via the client's web browser. The web browser should however be able to resolve the DNS records
			of the UCS domain, this is a particularly important point to note for mobile devices.
		</para>

		<section id="idmcloud:o365:setup">
			<title>Setup</title>
			<para>
				To setup the Microsoft 365 Connector a Microsoft 365 Administrator
				account, a corresponding Account in the Azure Active Directory, as well as a <ulink
				url="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/documentation/articles/active-directory-add-domain/"> Domain verified by Microsoft </ulink>
				are required. The first two are provided for test purposes by Microsoft for free. However to configure the SSO, a separate
				Internet domain where TXT records can be created is required.
			</para>

			<para>
				In case there is no Microsoft 365 subscription available, one can be configured it via <ulink
				url="https://www.office.com/"/> in the <guimenu>trial for business</guimenu> section. A
				connection is not possible with a private Microsoft account.
			</para>

			<para>
				You should then log in with a <guimenu>Microsoft 365 Administrator Account</guimenu> into the
				<guimenu>Microsoft 365 Admin Center</guimenu>. At the bottom left of the navigation bar select <guimenu>Azure
				AD</guimenu> to open the <guimenu>Azure Management Portal</guimenu> in a new window.
			</para>

			<para>
				In the <guimenu>Azure Active Directory</guimenu> section the menu item <guimenu>Custom domain names</guimenu> can be used to add and verify your own domain. For this
				it is necessary to create a TXT record in the DNS of your own domain. This process can take up to several minutes. Afterwards
				the <guimenu>status</guimenu> of the configured domain will be displayed as <guimenu>Verified</guimenu>.
			</para>

			<para>
				Now the Microsoft 365 App can be installed from the App Center on the UCS system. The
				installation takes a few minutes. There is a setup wizard available for the initial configuration. After completing the wizard the connector is ready for use.
			</para>

			<figure id="idmcloud:o365:wizard">
				<title>Microsoft 365 Setup assistant</title>
				<graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/office_wizard1_en.png"/>
			</figure>
		</section>

		<section id="idmcloud:o365:config">
			<title>Configuration</title>
			<para>
				After the end of the installation through the setup wizard, users can be enabled to use
				Microsoft 365. This configuration can be done through the user module on each user object on the <guimenu>Microsoft
				365</guimenu> tab. Usage and allocation of licenses are acknowledged in the <guimenu>Microsoft 365 Admin Center</guimenu>.
			</para>

			<para>
				If a change is made to the user, the changes are likewise replicated to the Azure Active Directory
				domain. There is no synchronization from the Azure Active Directory to the UCS system. This means changes made in Azure
				Active Directory or Office Portal may be overridden by changes to the same attributes in UCS.
			</para>

			<para>
				Due to Azure Active Directory security policies, users or groups in the Azure AD can't be deleted during
				synchronization. They are merely disabled and renamed. The licenses are revoked in the Azure Active Directory so that
				they become available to other users. Users and groups whose names start with <guimenu>ZZZ_deleted</guimenu> can be
				deleted in <guimenu>Microsoft 365 Admin Center</guimenu>.
			</para>

			<para>
				It is necessary to configure a country for the user in Microsoft 365. The connector uses the specification
				of the Country from the contact data of the user. If not set, it uses the setting of the server. With the help of
				&ucsUCRV; <envar>office365/attributes/usageLocation</envar> a 2-character abbreviation, e.g. US, can be set as the default.
			</para>
			<para>
				Through &ucsUCRV; <envar>office365/attributes/sync</envar>, the LDAP attributes (e.g. first name, last
				name, etc.) of a user's account which will to be synchronized are configured. The form is a comma-separated list of
				LDAP attributes. Thus adaptation to personal needs is easily possible.
			</para>

			<para>
				With the &ucsUCRV;<envar>office365/attributes/anonymize</envar>, a comma-separated list of LDAP
				attributes can be configured that are created in the Azure Active Directory but filled with random values. The &ucsUCRV;s
				<envar>office365/attributes/static/.*</envar>  allows the filling of attributes on the Microsoft side
				with a predefined value.
			</para>

			<para>
				The &ucsUCRV;<envar>office365/attributes/never</envar> can be used to specify a comma separated list of LDAP
				attributes that should not be synchronized even when they appear in <envar>office365/attributes/sync</envar> or
				<envar>office365/attributes/anonymize</envar>.
			</para>

			<para>
				The &ucsUCRV;s <envar>office365/attributes/mapping/.*</envar> define a
				mapping of UCS LDAP attributes to Azure Attributes. Usually these variables don't need to be changed. The
				synchronization of the groups of Microsoft 365 user can be enabled with the &ucsUCRV;<envar>office365/groups/sync</envar>.
			</para>

			<para>
				Changes to &ucsUCRV;s are implemented only after restarting the &ucsUDL;.
			</para>

		</section>
		<section id="idmcloud:o365:multipleconnections">
			<title>Synchronization of Users in multiple Azure Active Directories</title>
			<para>
			The Microsoft 365 Connector is able to synchronize users to multiple Azure Active Directories.
			For each user account, multiple Azure AD instances can be assigned, where an account should be created.
				A user gets a distinct username (<wordasword>Userprincipalname</wordasword>, UPN) for every assigned Azure AD.
			</para>
			<para>
			An alias is assigned to each additional Azure AD connection by the administrator.
			To manage these aliases the program <command>/usr/share/univention-office365/scripts/manage_adconnections</command> can be used.
			A new alias is created by calling <command>/usr/share/univention-office365/scripts/manage_adconnections create <replaceable>&lt;Aliasname&gt;</replaceable></command>.
			This will set the &ucsUCRV; <envar>office365/adconnection/wizard</envar> to the newly created alias.
			The value of this &ucsUCRV; defines which connection is configured by the next run of the Microsoft 365 Configuration Wizard.
			</para>
			<para>
			After creating the alias, the new connection must be configured through the Microsoft 365 Configuration Wizard as well.
			</para>
			<para>
			To use Single Sign-On with multiple Azure AD connections, a new logical SAML Identity Provider is needed for each connection.
			This is described in <xref linkend="domain:saml:extendedconfiguration"/>.
			The Identity Provider should get the same name as the alias. If another name was chosen, the PowerShell script to configure Single Sign-On needs to be adjusted manually.
			For example the &ucsUCRV; <envar>saml/idp/entityID/supplement/<replaceable>Aliasname</replaceable>=true</envar> needs to be set on all domain controllers responsible for Single Sign-On.
			</para>
			<para>
			A UCS user can only use one Microsoft 365 account in one browser session at a time.
			To change the connection, a logout from Microsoft 365 is necessary.
			</para>
			<para>
			A default alias for Microsoft 365 enabled users and groups can be set in the &ucsUCRV; <envar>office365/defaultalias</envar>.
			To synchronize them into a different Azure Active Directory the connection alias must be selected explicitly at the user or group object.
			</para>
		</section>

		<section id="idmcloud:o365:debug">
			<title>Troubleshooting/Debugging</title>

			<para>
				Messages during the setup are logged in
				<filename>/var/log/univention/management-console-module-office365.log</filename>.
			</para>

			<para>
				In case of synchronization problems, the log file of the &ucsUDL; should be
				examined: <filename>/var/log/univention/listener.log</filename>. The
				&ucsUCRV;<envar>Office365/debug/werror</envar> activates additional debug output.
			</para>

		</section>
	</section>

	<section id="idmcloud:gsuite">
		<title>Google Apps for Work Connector</title>
		<para>
			Google Apps for Work Connector allows users and groups to synchronize to a G Suite
			domain. You can control which of the users created in UCS are allowed to use G Suite.

			The users selected in this way are provisioned accordingly by UCS into the G Suite domain. It can
			be configured which attributes are synchronized and attributes can be anonymized.
		</para>

		<para>
			The Single Sign-On log-in to G Suite is done via the UCS integrated SAML implementation.
			Authentication takes place against the UCS server, and no password hashes are transferred to the G Suite
			domain. The user's authentication is done exclusively via the client's web browser. However, the browser should be
			able to resolve the DNS records of the UCS domain, which is particularly important for mobile devices.
		</para>

		<section id="idmcloud:gsuite:setup">
			<title>Setup</title>
			<para>
				To setup the Google Apps for Work Connectors a G Suite Administrator account, a
				corresponding account in the G Suite domain, and a <ulink url="https://support.google.com/a/topic/9196?hl=en">domain verified</ulink>
				by Google are required. The
				first two will be provided free of charge by Google for testing purposes. However, configuring the SSO
				requires a separate Internet domain where TXT records can be created.
			</para>

			<para>
				If no G Suite subscription is available yet, it can be configured via <ulink url="https://gsuite.google.com/setup-hub/"/>
				with the link <guimenu>Start your free trial</guimenu>. A connection with a private Gmail account is not possible.
			</para>

			<para>
				Afterwards, you should log in with a <guimenu>G Suite administrator account</guimenu> in the
				<ulink url="https://admin.google.com/">Admin Console</ulink>. The domain should now be verified. For this it is necessary
				to create a TXT record in the DNS of your own domain. This process can take a few minutes.
			</para>

			<para>
				Now the Google Apps for Work Connector from the App Center can be installed on the UCS system.
				The installation only takes a few minutes.
				There is a setup wizard available for the initial configuration. After completing the wizard the connector
				is ready for use.
			</para>

			<figure id="idmcloud:gsuite:wizard">
				<title>Google Apps for Work Setup Wizard</title>
				<graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations44/google_wizard1_en.png"/>
			</figure>
		</section>

		<section id="idmcloud:gsuite:config">
			<title>Configuration</title>
			<para>
				After the setup via the setup wizard, you can use the user module on each user object on the
				<guimenu>Google Apps tab</guimenu> to configure that this user is provisioned to G Suite.
			</para>

			<para>
				If a change is made to the user, the changes will also be replicated to the G Suite domain. There is no
				synchronization from the G Suite domain to the UCS system. This means that changes made in the G Suite domain
				may be overwritten by changes to the same attributes in UCS.
			</para>

			<para>
				If the Google Apps property is removed from a user, the user will be deleted from the G Suite domain accordingly.
			</para>

			<para>
				The &ucsUCRV; <envar>google-apps/attributes/mapping/.*</envar> is used to configure which LDAP attributes (e.g. first name, last name, etc.)
				of a user account are synchronized. The &ucsUCRV; and its values reflect the nested data structure of the G Suite user accounts.
				The names that follow the percentage sign in the values are the attributes in the UCS LDAP. If all &ucsUCRV;
				<envar>google-apps/attributes/mapping/.*</envar> are removed, no data other than the primary e-mail address is synchronized.
			</para>

			<para>
				The &ucsUCRV; <envar>google-apps/attributes/anonymize</envar> can be used to specify
				comma-separated LDAP attributes that are created in the G Suite domain but filled with random values.
			</para>

			<para>
				The &ucsUCRV; <envar>google-apps/attributes/never</envar> can be used to specify
				comma-separated LDAP attributes that should not be synchronized, even if they are configured via
				<envar>google-apps/attributes/mapping</envar> or <envar>google-apps/attributes/anonymize</envar>.
			</para>

			<para>
				The synchronization of Google Apps for Work user groups can be enabled with the &ucsUCRV; <envar>google-apps/groups/sync</envar>.
			</para>

			<para>
				Changes to &ucsUCRV; are implemented after restarting the &ucsUDL;.
			</para>
		</section>


		<section id="idmcloud:gsuite:debug">
			<title>Troubleshooting/Debugging</title>
			<para>
				Messages during setup are logged in the following log file
				<filename>/var/log/univention/management-console-module-googleapps.log</filename>.
			</para>

			<para>
				In case of synchronization problems, the log file of the &ucsUDL; should be checked:
				<filename>/var/log/univention/listener.log</filename>. The &ucsUCRV; <envar>google-apps/debug/werror</envar>
				activates additional debug output.
			</para>
		</section>

	</section>

</chapter>
