<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="installation:chapter">
<title>Installation</title>
<section id="installation:einfuehrung">
<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
The following documentation describes how to install Univention Corporate Server (UCS). The UCS system is installed from the DVD. The installation is interactive and prompts all the necessary system settings in a graphic interface.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The installation DVD is available for the computer architecture <emphasis>amd64</emphasis> (64-bit). In addition to support for the widely distributed BIOS systems, the DVD also includes support for the Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (UEFI) standard. The UEFI support on the DVD is also capable of starting systems with activated SecureBoot and installing UCS there.
	</para>

	<para>
Following installation on hardware or in a virtualization solution, UCS can also be installed on the Amazon EC2 cloud using an AMI image. Further information can be found in <xref linkend="installation:amazonec2"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The installer's input masks can be operated with the mouse or via the keyboard.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  The <keycap function="tab">Tab</keycap> key can be used to proceed to the next field.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  The key combination of <keycombo action="simul"><keycap function="shift">Shift</keycap><keycap function="tab">Tab</keycap></keycombo> can be used to return to the previous field.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  The <keycap function="enter">Enter</keycap> key is used to assign values to the input field and confirm buttons.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  Within a list or table, the <emphasis>arrow keys</emphasis> can be used for navigating between entries.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<note>
	  <para>
		The <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> button can be used to cancel the current configuration step. An earlier configuration step can then be selected again in the menu that is subsequently shown. Under certain circumstances, subsequent configuration steps cannot be directly selected if the earlier steps have not been completed.
	  </para>
	</note>
</section>
<section id="installation:Auswahl_des_Installationsmodus">
<title>Selecting the installation mode</title>
	<para>
		After booting the system from the installation medium, the following boot prompt is displayed:
	</para>
	<figure id="installation-isolinux">
	<title>Installation boot prompt</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-isolinux.png"/>
	</figure>
	<para>
		Now you can choose between several installation procedures.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<simpara>
			<guimenuitem>Start with default settings</guimenuitem> starts the interactive, graphic installation. During the installation, the system requests a number of parameters such as the network settings, hard drive partitions, domain settings and selection of software components for the UCS system to be installed and then performs the installation and the configuration.
			</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<simpara>
				<guimenuitem>Start with manual network settings</guimenuitem> performs a standard installation, where the network is not configured automatically through DHCP.
				This is practical on systems, where the network must be setup manually.
			</simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
			  The <guisubmenu>Advanced options</guisubmenu> submenu offers advanced options for the installation process for selection:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<simpara>
					<guimenuitem>Install in text mode</guimenuitem> performs an interactive standard installation in text mode. This is practical on systems which display problems with the graphic version of the installer.</simpara>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				  <simpara>
					<guimenuitem>Boot from first hard drive</guimenuitem> boots the operating system installed on the first hard drive instead of the UCS installation.
				  </simpara>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
		Once one of the installation option is selected, the kernel is loaded from the installation medium. The actual installation is divided into separate modules, which can be loaded from the installation medium subsequently if necessary.
		There are modules for network configuration or for selecting the software to be installed, among others.
	</para>
</section>
<section id="installation:Auswahl_der_Installationssprache">
<title>Selecting the installation language</title>
	<para>
		In the first step, you can select the system language you wish to use. The selection has an influence on the use of language-specific characters and permits the representation of program output in the selected languages in the installed UCS system.
	</para>
	<figure id="installation-languageeselection">
	<title>Selecting the installation language</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-language.png"/>
	</figure>
	<para>
		If Univention Installer has been translated into the selected language (currently German and English), the selected language is also used during the installation, otherwise the installation is performed in English.
	</para>
</section>
<section id="installation:Auswahl_des_Standorts">
<title>Selecting the location</title>
	<para>
	  Once the system language has been selected, a small list of locations is displayed based on the selected language. Select a suitable location from the list. The selected location is used to set the time zone or the correct language variant, for example. Should none of the displayed locations be appropriate, a more extensive list can be displayed using the menu entry <guimenu>other</guimenu>.
	</para>
	<figure id="installation-location">
	<title>Selecting the location</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-location_en.png"/>
	</figure>
</section>
<section id="installation:Auswahl_der_Tastaturbelegung">
<title>Selecting the keyboard layout</title>
	<para>
	  The keyboard layout can be selected independently of the system language. The language selected here should be compatible with the keyboard used as it may otherwise cause operating problems.
	</para>
	<figure id="installation-keyboardselection">
	<title>Selecting the keyboard layout</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-keyboardselection_en.png"/>
	</figure>
</section>
<section id="installation:Netzwerkkonfiguration">
  <title>Network configuration</title>
  <para>
	Initially, the Univention Installer attempts to configure the network interfaces automatically.
	This can be disabled by selecting the menu item <guimenuitem>Start with manual network settings</guimenuitem> from the menu of the bootloader.
	Firstly, an attempt is made to determine an IPv6 address via the stateless address autoconfiguration (SLAAC).
	If this is not successful, the Univention Installer attempts to request an IPv4 address via the Dynamic Host Configuration
	Protocol (DHCP). If this is successful, the manual network configuration of Univention Installer is skipped.
  </para>
  <figure id="installation-netcfg-dhcp">
	<title>Automatic network configuration</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-netcfg-dhcp_en.png"/>
  </figure>
  <para>
	If there is no DHCP server present in the local network or static configuration of the network interface is required, the <guimenu>Cancel</guimenu> button can be selected. The Univention Installer then offers to repeat the automatic configuration or to configure the interface manually.
  </para>
  <note>
	  <para>
	  At least one network interface is required for the installation of &ucsUCS;. If no supported network card is detected, Univention Installer opens a list of supported drivers for selection.
	  </para>
  </note>
  <figure id="installation-netcfg-static">
	<title>Selecting the manual network configuration </title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-netcfg-static_en.png"/>
  </figure>
  <para>
	In manual configuration it is possible to specify either a static IPv4 or an IPv6 address for the system. IPv4 addresses have a 32-bit length and are generally written in four blocks in decimal form (e.g., <systemitem class="ipaddress">192.0.2.10</systemitem>), whereas IPv6 addresses are four times as long and typically written in hexadecimal form (e.g., <systemitem class="ipaddress">2001:0DB8:FE29:DE27:0000:0000:0000:0000</systemitem>).
	In addition to entering a static IP address, values for network masks, gateways and DNS servers are also requested.
  </para>
  <figure id="installation-netcfg-ip">
	<title>Specifying an IP address</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-netcfg-ip_en.png"/>
  </figure>
  <para>
	The following points must be taken into consideration when specifying a DNS server manually. They depend on the intended subsequent use of the UCS system.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  When installing the first UCS system in a new UCS domain, the IP address of the local router (if it provides the DNS service) or the DNS server of the Internet provider should be entered.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  When installing every additional UCS system, the IP address of a UCS domain controller system must be specified as the DNS server. This is essential for the automatic detection of the domain controller master to function. In case of doubt, the IP address of the UCS domain controller master system should be entered.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  If the UCS system is to join a Windows Active Directory domain during the installation, the IP address of an Active Directory domain controller system should be specified as the DNS server. This is essential for the automatic detection of the Windows Active Directory domain controller to function.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>
</section>
<section id="installation:rootpassword">
  <title>Setting up the root password</title>
  <para>
	Setting of a password for the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> user is required for logging on to the installed system.
If a &ucsMaster; is installed, this password is also employed for the
<systemitem class="username">administrator</systemitem> user.
In later operation, the passwords for the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> and <systemitem class="username">administrator</systemitem>
users can be managed independently of each other. The password must be re-entered in the second entry field.
  </para>
  <para>
	The password must contain at least eight characters for security reasons.
  </para>
  <figure id="installation-password">
	<title>Setting the root password</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-password_en.png"/>
  </figure>
</section>


<section id="installation:Partitionieren_der_Festplatten">
  <title>Partitioning the hard drive</title>
  <para>
	The Univention Installer supports the partitioning of hard drives and the creation of different file systems (e.g., <systemitem class="filesystem">ext4</systemitem> and <systemitem class="filesystem">XFS</systemitem>). In addition, it is also possible to set up mechanisms such as the logical volume manager (<acronym>LVM</acronym>), <acronym>RAID</acronym> or partitions encrypted with <acronym>LUKS</acronym>.
  </para>
  <para>
	  As of UCS 4.0, the Univention Installer selects a suitable partition model (<acronym>MBR</acronym> or <acronym>GPT</acronym>) automatically depending on the size of the selected hard drive.
	  On systems with the <emphasis>Unified Extensible Firmware Interface (<acronym>UEFI</acronym>)</emphasis>, the <acronym>GUID</acronym> Partition Table (<acronym>GPT</acronym>) is used automatically.
  </para>
  <para>
	The Univention Installer offers guided installations to make installation simpler. In the guided installation, certain standard schemes with respect to the partitioning and formatting are applied to the selected hard drive. In addition, it is also possible to perform partitioning manually.
  </para>
  <para>
	There are three schemes available for selection for guided partitioning:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <guimenu>Guided - Use entire disk</guimenu>: In this scheme, an individual partition is created for each file system. Abstraction layers like LVM are not used. During the following step the number of filesystems/partitions is assigned. The size of the partitions is restricted to
the size of the respective hard drive.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <guimenu>Guided - Use entire disk and set up LVM</guimenu>: If the second scheme is selected, an LVM volume group is set up on the selected hard drive first. A separate logical volume is then created within the volume group for each file system. In this scheme, the size of the logical volume is restricted by the size of the volume group, which can also be subsequently enlarged with additional hard drives. In case of doubt, select this partitioning scheme.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <guimenu>Guided - Use entire disk with encrypted LVM</guimenu>: This version is the same as the previous version, with the addition that the LVM volume group is also encrypted. Consequently, the password for the encrypted volume group has to be entered every time the system is started up.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<caution>
		<para>
	  In all three versions, the data already on the selected hard drive are deleted during the partitioning!
		</para>
	</caution>
	<figure id="installation-partman-selectguided">
	  <title>Selecting the partitioning scheme</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-partman-selectguided_en.png"/>
	</figure>
  </para>
  <para>
	The next step is to select a hard drive from the list of those detected to which the partitioning version should be applied.
  </para>
  <para>
	There are three subversions for each partitioning version, which differ in the number of file systems created:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <guimenu>All files in one partition</guimenu>: In this version, just one partition or logical volume is created and the <filename class="directory">/</filename> file system saved there.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
            <guimenu>Separate /home partition</guimenu>: In addition to a file system for <filename class="directory">/</filename>, an additional file system is also created for <filename class="directory">/home/</filename>.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <guimenu>Separate /home, /usr, /var and /tmp partition</guimenu>: In addition to a file system for <filename class="directory">/</filename>,  an additional file system is also created each for <filename class="directory">/home/</filename>, <filename class="directory">/usr/</filename>, /<filename class="directory">var/</filename> and <filename class="directory">/tmp/</filename>.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
	Before every active change to the hard drive, the change is displayed again in an additional dialogue and must be confirmed explicitly.
	<figure id="installation-partman-writelvm">
	  <title>Confirmation of changes to the hard drive</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-partman-writelvm_en.png"/>
	</figure>
  </para>
  <para>
	Once the partitioning is complete, the UCS basic system and additional software is installed automatically. This can take some time depending on the speed of the hardware used. The system is then made ready to boot via the installation of the GRUB bootloader.
  </para>
</section>
<section id="installation:Domäneneinstellungen">
  <title>Domain settings</title>
  <para>
	The final configuration of the UCS system is started by selecting a domain mode.
	There are four modes available, which influence the following configuration steps:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  In the first mode, <guimenu>Create a new UCS domain</guimenu>, the first system in a new UCS domain is configured: a UCS system with the <emphasis>&ucsMaster;</emphasis> system role. In the following configuration steps, the information required for setting up a new directory service, authentication service and DNS server are requested. A UCS domain can comprise one single or several UCS systems. Additional UCS systems can be added at a later point in time using the <guimenu>Join an existing UCS domain</guimenu> mode.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <guimenu>Join into an existing  Active Directory domain</guimenu>: This mode, in which UCS is operated as a member of an Active Directory domain, is suitable for expanding an Active Directory domain with applications available on the UCS platform. Apps installed on the UCS platform are then available for the users of the Active Directory domain to use. On selection of this mode, all the relevant information for the joining of the Active Directory domain is requested and the UCS system configured correspondingly.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  Selecting the <guimenu>Join into an existing UCS domain</guimenu> mode allows the UCS system to be configured to join an existing UCS domain. What UCS system role it is to take on in the domain is queried at a later stage.
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  If the <guimenu>Do not use any domain</guimenu> mode is selected, there are no web-based administration functions and no domain functions at all available on the system. The UCS system can also not subsequently become a member of an existing UCS or Active Directory domain or found a new UCS domain at a later point in time. In addition, the Univention App Center is not available in this mode. For this reason, this mode is only used rarely and in special scenarios (e.g, as a firewall system).
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<figure id="installation-domainrole">
	  <title>Domain settings</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-domainrole_en.png"/>
	</figure>
  </para>
  <section id="installation:Domäneneinstellungen:NeueDomäne">
	<title>"Create a new UCS domain" mode</title>
	<para>
	  Once the <guimenu>Create a new UCS domain</guimenu> mode has been selected, an <emphasis>organization name</emphasis>, an <emphasis>e-mail address</emphasis>, a <emphasis>fully qualified domain name</emphasis> and an <emphasis>LDAP base</emphasis> are requested in the following two steps.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Specification of an organization name is optional and it is used in the second step to generate a domain name and the LDAP base automatically.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If a valid e-mail address is specified, this is used to activate a personalized license, which is required for the use of the Univention App Center. The license is generated automatically and sent to the specified e-mail address immediately. The license can then be imported via the &ucsUMC; license dialog.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The name of the UCS system to be configured and the name of the DNS domain are determined from the fully qualified domain name (host name including domain name) entered here.
	  A suggestion is generated automatically from the organization name entered in the previous step. It is recommended not to use a publicly available DNS domain, as this can result in problems during the name resolution.
	</para>
	<para>
	  A LDAP base needs to be specified for the initialization of the directory service. A suggestion is also derived here automatically from the fully qualified domain name. This value can usually be adopted without any changes.
	</para>
	<figure id="installation-newdomain">
	  <title>Specification of host name and LDAP base</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-hostname_en.png"/>
	</figure>
  </section>
  <section id="installation:Domäneneinstellungen:ADMember">
	<title>"Join an existing Active Directory domain" mode</title>
	<para>
	  If the DNS server of an Active Directory domain was specified during the network configuration, the name of the Active Directory domain controller is suggested automatically in the <guimenu>Active Directory account information</guimenu> step. If the suggestion is incorrect, the name of another Active Directory domain controller or another Active Directory domain can be entered here.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The specification of an Active Directory account and the corresponding password is required for joining the Active Directory domain. The user account must possess the right to join new systems in the Active Directory domain.
	</para>
	<para>
	  In addition, a host name must be entered for the UCS system to be configured. The suggested host name can be adopted or a new host name entered.  The domain name of the computer is derived automatically from the domain DNS server. In some scenarios (e.g., a public mail server) it can prove necessary to use a specific fully qualified domain name. The UCS system will join the Active Directory domain with the host name specified here. Once set up, the domain name <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be changed again once the configuration is completed.
	</para>
	<para>
	  In a UCS domain, systems can be installed in different <emphasis>system roles</emphasis>.
	  The first UCS system, that joins an Active Directory domain, is automatically installed with the
	  &ucsMaster; system role. If this mode is selected during installation of additional UCS systems, the
	  system role selection dialogue is shown. The system roles are described within the following section.
	</para>

	<figure id="installation-adjoin">
	  <title>Information on the Active Directory domain join</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-adjoin_en.png"/>
	</figure>
  </section>
  <section id="installation:Domäneneinstellungen:EinerUCSDomäneBeitreten">
	<title>"Join an existing UCS domain domain" mode</title>
	<para>
	  In a UCS domain, systems can be installed in different <emphasis>system roles</emphasis>. The first system in a UCS domain is always installed with the &ucsMaster; system role. Additional UCS systems can join the domain at a later point in time and can be configured with one of the following system roles.
	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <simpara>
			<guimenu>&ucsBackup;</guimenu>
		  </simpara>
		  <simpara>
			The &ucsBackup; is the fallback system for the DC master. If the latter should fail, a DC backup can adopt the role of the DC master permanently. All the domain data and SSL security certificates are saved as read-only copies on servers with the &ucsBackup; role.
		  </simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <simpara>
			<guimenu>&ucsSlave;</guimenu>
		  </simpara>
		  <simpara>
			All the domain data are saved as read-only copies on servers with the &ucsSlave; role. In contrast to the &ucsBackup;, however, not all security certificates are saved. As accesses to the services running on a &ucsSlave; are performed against the local LDAP directory service, DC slave systems are ideal for site servers and the distribution of high-load services.
		  </simpara>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <simpara>
			<guimenu>&ucsMember;</guimenu>
		  </simpara>
		  <simpara>
			&ucsMember; are server systems without a local LDAP directory service. Access to domain data here is performed via other servers in the domain. They are therefore suitable for services which do not require a local database for authentication, for example, such as print and file servers.
		  </simpara>
		</listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	  Once the UCS system role has been selected, further information on the domain join is requested. If the domain join is not intended to occur automatically during the installation, the <guimenu>Start join at the end of the installation</guimenu> option can be disabled.
	  If the correct DNS server was selected during the network configuration, Univention Installer can determine the name of the &ucsMaster; system automatically. If the decision is taken to join another UCS domain, the <guimenu>Search Domain controller master in DNS</guimenu>
option can be disabled and the fully qualified domain name of the preferred &ucsMaster; entered in the input field below. The access information required for the domain join must be entered in the <guimenu>Administrator account</guimenu> and  <guimenu>Administrator password</guimenu> input fields.
	</para>
	<figure id="installation-join">
	  <title>Information on the domain join</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-join_en.png"/>
	</figure>
	<para>
	  In addition, a host name must be entered for the UCS system to be configured in the next step. The suggested host name can be adopted or a new host name entered. The domain name of the computer is derived automatically from the domain DNS server. In some scenarios (e.g., a public mail server) it can prove necessary to use a certain fully qualified domain name. Once set up, the domain name <emphasis>cannot</emphasis> be changed again once the configuration is completed.
	</para>
  </section>
  <section id="installation:Domäneneinstellungen:KeineDomäne">
	<title>"Do not use any domain" mode</title>
	<para>
	  The configuration of the <guimenu>Do not use any domain</guimenu> mode requires the specification of a host name for the UCS system to be configured. The suggested host name can be adopted
or a new host name entered. The domain name of the computer is derived automatically from the domain DNS server.
	</para>
  </section>
</section>

<section id="installation:software">
  <title>Selecting UCS software components</title>
  <para>
	The <guimenu>software configuration</guimenu> step offers the possibility of installing additional UCS components during the installation. The applications are also available after the installation via the Univention App Center in the <guimenu>UCS components</guimenu> category and can be installed and uninstalled there subsequently.
  </para>
	<figure id="installation-softwareselection">
	  <title>Selecting UCS software components</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-softwareselection_en.png"/>
	</figure>
</section>

<section id="installation:overview">
  <title>Confirming the settings</title>
  <para>
	This dialogue shows the major settings that were made.
	If all the settings are correct, the <guimenu>Configure system</guimenu> button can be used to start the configuration of the UCS system,
see <xref linkend="installation-overview"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
	The <guimenu>Update system after installation</guimenu> option allows the automatic installation of available Errata updates. In addition, all patch level updates and Errata updates available are installed on a &ucsMaster;. On all other system roles, all the patch level updates are set up to the installation status of the &ucsMaster;. (You need to log on to the &ucsMaster; to check the installation status. This is done using the login data specified in the join options).
  </para>
  <figure id="installation-overview">
	<title>Installation overview</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations44/installer-overview_en.png"/>
  </figure>
  <para>
	During the configuration, a progress bar displays the progress of the installation.
  </para>
  <para>
	The installation protocol of the Univention Installer is saved in the following files:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <filename>/var/log/installer/syslog</filename>
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
		<simpara>
		  <filename>/var/log/univention/management-console-module-setup.log</filename>
		</simpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
	Completion of the configuration must be confirmed with the <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> button.
	The UCS system is then prepared for the first booting procedure and restarted.
  </para>
  <para>
	The system will then boot from the hard drive. Following the boot procedure, the <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> and <systemitem class="username">administrator</systemitem> users can log on via the web frontend &ucsUMC; (see <xref linkend="central:general"/>), which can be reached under the IP address set during the installation or the host name.
</para>
  <para>
	If the computer was installed as the first system in the UCS domain (&ucsMaster;), the license can now be imported (see <xref linkend="central:license"/>).
  </para>
</section>

<section id="installation:Troubleshooting_for_installation_problems">
<title>Troubleshooting for installation problems</title>
	<para>
		Information on possible installation problems can be found in the Univention
		Support database at <ulink url="http://sdb.univention.de"/> in the
		subitem <emphasis>Installation</emphasis>.
	</para>
</section>

<section id="installation:textmode">
  <title>Installation in text mode</title>
  <para>
	On systems that showed a problem with the graphic variant of Univention Installer, the installation may be also started in text mode.
	To achieve this, in the DVD boot menu <guimenu>Advanced options</guimenu> the entry <guimenu>Install in text mode</guimenu> has to be selected.
  </para>
  <para>
	During installation in text mode Univention Installer shows the same information and asks for the
	same settings. After partitioning the hard drive, the system is prepared for the first boot and finally restarted.
  </para>
  <para>
	After restart the configuration may be resumed by using a web browser. The URL
	<uri>https://<replaceable>SERVER-IP-ADDRESS</replaceable></uri> or <uri>http://<replaceable>SERVER-IP-ADDRESS</replaceable></uri> has to be opened
	within the browser (HTTPS is recommended). After loading the URI a login as user
	<systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> is required.
  </para>
  <para>
	The configuration process asks for location and network setting and then resumes with the same
	steps as the graphic variant of the installation, i.e. section <emphasis>domain settings</emphasis>.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="installation:amazonec2">
<title>Installation in the Amazon EC2 cloud</title>
	<para>
		Univention provides an Amazon Machine Image (AMI) for the Amazon EC2
		cloud for UCS. This generic image for all UCS system roles is used to derive an individual instance
		which can be configured via the &ucsUMC; (domain name, software
		selection, etc.).
	</para>
	<para>
		The process for setting up a UCS instance based on Amazon EC2 is
		documented in the Univention Wiki <biblioref linkend="ec2-quickstart"/>.
	</para>
</section>

<section id="installation:vmware">
  <title>Installation in VMware</title>
  <para>
	If UCS is installed as a guest in VMware, the <guimenu>Linux &ar; Other Linux system</guimenu>
	option must be selected as the <guimenu>Guest operating system</guimenu> (UCS is based on Debian but
	the templates for Debian cannot be used).
  </para>

  <para>
	The Linux kernel used in UCS includes all the support drivers necessary for operation in VMware
	(<filename>vmw_balloon</filename>, <filename>vmw_pvsci</filename>, <filename>vmw_vmci</filename>, <filename>vmwgfx</filename> and <filename>vmxnet3</filename>).
  </para>

  <para>
	The open source version of the VMware Tools (Open VM Tools) is delivered with UCS. The tools can
	be installed using the <package>open-vm-tools</package> package (they are not required
	but do, for example, allow synchronization of the time on the virtualization server with the
	guest system).
  </para>
</section>

<section id="installation:docker">
  <title>Installation as Docker image</title>
  <para>
    Univention provides UCS as Docker images in the Docker Hub
	<ulink url="https://hub.docker.com/r/univention/"/>. The description of the
	Docker images explains how they can be configured.
  </para>
  <para>
	In a standard installation, the Docker images are used in a network that cannot
	be reached directly from outside the server. If multiple Docker images are used and they
	are executed on different Docker servers, a Software Defined Network or a VPN solution
	should be used.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="installation:xenserver">
<title>Installation in Citrix XenServer</title>
	<para>
		The process for setting up a UCS instance in Citrix XenServer is
		documented in the Univention Wiki <biblioref linkend="xenserver-installation"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  To display the GRUB menu correctly, an adaption to the XenServer configuration is necessary;
	  this is described in <xref linkend="release-notes"/>.
	</para>
</section>
</chapter>
