<chapter id="introduction:Introduction"><title>Introduction</title>

<section id="introduction:What_is_Univention_Corporate_Server"><title>What is Univention Corporate Server?</title>
<para>
Univention Corporate Server (UCS) is a Linux-based server operating system
for the operation and administration of IT infrastructures for
companies and authorities. UCS implements an integrated, holistic
concept with consistent, central administration and can ensure the
operation of all the components in an interrelated security and trust
context, the so-called UCS domain. At the same time, UCS supports a
wide range of open standards and includes extensive interfaces to
infrastructure components and management tools from other
manufacturers, meaning it can be easily integrated in existing
environments.
</para>
<para>
UCS consists of reliable Open Source software tried and
tested in organisations of different sizes. These software components
are integrated together via the &ucsUMS;. This allows the easy
integration and administration of the system in both simple and
complex distributed or virtualized environments.
</para>
<para>
The central functions of UCS are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><simpara>Flexible and extensive identity/infrastructure management for the central
administration of servers, workstations, users and their permissions, server applications and web
services</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Services for integrating the management of existing Microsoft Active Directory
domains or alternatively the provision of suchs services as an alternative for Microsoft-based
server systems</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>App Center for simply installation and management of extensions and applications</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Comprehensive features for the operation of virtualized systems (e.g. running a
Windows or Linux operating systems) in either the cloud of on locally running UCS systems</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Network and Intranet services for administration of DHCP and DNS</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>File and print services</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Computer administration and monitoring</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Mail services</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
These functions are provided by different software packages in
Univention Corporate Server and are handled in detail in the course of
this handbook. Basically, the software packages contained in UCS can
be assigned to the following three main categories:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><simpara>Base system</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>UCS management system with Univention Management Console</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Univention App Center, allowing the installation of further components and
applications of other software vendors</simpara></listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
The <emphasis>base system</emphasis> encompasses the operating system, the UCS Linux
distribution maintained by Univention and based on Debian GNU/Linux
and largely includes the same software selection as Debian GNU/Linux
as well as tools for the installation, updating and configuration of
clients and servers.
</para>
<para>
The <emphasis>&ucsUMS;</emphasis> realises a single point of administration where
the accounts of all domain members (users, groups, and hosts) and
services such as DNS and DHCP are managed in a single directory
service. Core components of the management system are the services
OpenLDAP (directory service), Samba (provision of domain, file and
print services for Windows), Kerberos (authentication and single sign
on), DNS (network name resolution) and SSL/TLS (secure transmission
of data between systems). It can be used either via a web interface (&ucsUMC;)
or in the command line and in individual scripts. The UCS management
system can be extended with APIs (application programmers interfaces)
and provides a flexible client-server architecture which allows
changes to be transferred to the involved systems and be activated
there.
</para>
<para>
Additional components from Univention and other manufacturers can easily be installed using the
App Center expand the system with numerous functions such as
groupware, document management and services for Windows, meaning that
they can also be run from a UCS system and administrated via the UCS
management system.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Overview_of_UCS"><title>Overview of UCS</title>
<para>
As an operating system designed for multi-user and multi-tasking
application right from the start, where the focus in its development
was always on stability, security and compatibility with other
operating systems, Linux is predestined for being used in server
operating systems that are stable, secure and highly available.
UCS is a server operating system built on that base which is optimised
for the simple and secure operation and management of applications and infrastructure services in
enterprises and public authorities. For efficient and secure management such applications rely on
the tight integration in the user and permission management of the &ucsUMS;.
</para>
<para>
UCS can be employed as the basis for the IT infrastructure in
companies and authorities and provide the central control for it. This
makes a considerable contribution to secure, efficient and
cost-effective IT operation. The business-critical applications are
integrated in a uniform concept, adapted to each other and
pre-configured for professional utilisation. Alternatively it can be operated as part of an existing
Microsoft Active Directory domain.
</para>

<section id="introduction:Commissioning"><title>Commissioning</title>
<para>
The use of UCS begins either with a classic operating system
installation on a physical server or as a virtual machine,
which is also set up via an installation or can be generated from an
existing virtual machine employed as a template. The installation can
be interactive or fully automatic either from a DVD or via the
network/PXE.
</para>
<para>
Further information can be found in <xref linkend="installation:chapter"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Domain_concept"><title>Domain concept</title>
<para>
In an IT infrastructure managed with UCS all servers, clients and users are contained in a common
security and trust context; the UCS domain. Every UCS system is assigned a so-called server role
during the installation. Possible system roles are domain controller, &ucsMember; and client.
</para>
<para>
<figure><title>UCS domain concept</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations/domainconcept.jpg"/>
 </figure>
</para>
<para>
Depending on the system role the computer is to play within the
domain, such services as Kerberos, OpenLDAP, Samba, modules for domain
replication or a Root CA (certification authority) are installed on
the computer and are automatically configured for the selected role
within the system. Thus manual implementation and configuration of
every single service and application are not required. Due to the
modular design and extensive configuration interfaces, tailor-made
solutions to individual requirements can nevertheless be realised.
</para>
<para>
The integration of Samba, which provides the domain service for
clients and servers operated with Microsoft Windows, makes Univention
Corporate Server compatible with Microsoft Active Directory (AD),
whereby the system acts as an Active Directory server for
Windows-based systems. Consequently, for example, group policies for
Microsoft Windows systems can be administrated in the usual way.
</para>

<para>
UCS can also be operated as part of an existing Microsoft Active Directory domain. This way, users and groups
of the Active Directory domain can access applications from the Univention App Center.
</para>

<para>
Ubuntu or Mac OS X clients can also be integrated in a UCS environment (see
<xref linkend="computers:ubuntu"/>).
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Expandability_with_components"><title>Expandability with the Univention
App Center</title>
<para>
The Univention App Center offers additional UCS components and extensions and a broad selection of
business IT software, e.g. groupware and collaboration, file exchange, CRM or backup. These
applications can be installed in existing environments with a few clicks and are usually ready to
use. In most cases they are directly integrated into the &ucsUMS; and available in the
&ucsUMC;. This provides a central management of data on the domain level and obsoletes the separate
management of e.g. user data in multiple places.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:LDAP_directory_service"><title>LDAP directory service</title>
<para>
With the &ucsUMS;, all the components of the UCS domain can be
centrally administrated across computer, operating system and site
boundaries. It thus provides a single point of administration for
the domain. One primary element of the UCS management system is an
LDAP directory in which the data required across the domain for the
administration are stored. In addition to the user accounts and
similar elements, the data basis of services such as DHCP is also
saved. The central data management in the LDAP directory avoids not
only the repeated entry of the same data, but also reduces the
probability of errors and inconsistencies.
</para>
<para>
An LDAP directory has a tree-like structure, the root of which forms
the so-called basis of the UCS domain. The UCS domain forms the common
security and trust context for its members. An account in the LDAP
directory establishes the membership in the UCS domain for
users. Computers receive a computer account when they join the
domain. Microsoft Windows systems can also join the domain and users
can log in there with their domain passport.
</para>
<para>
UCS utilises OpenLDAP as a directory service server. The directory is
provided by the &ucsMaster; and replicated on all domain controllers
(DCs) in the domain. The complete LDAP directory is also replicated on
a DC backup as this can replace the DC master in an emergency. In
contrast, the replication on DC slaves can be restricted to certain
areas of the LDAP directory using ACLs (access control lists), which
allows selective replication. For example, this may be desirable if
data should only be stored on as few servers as possible for security
reasons. A root CA (certification authority) is integrated in UCS so
that these and other data can be transmitted encrypted.
</para>
<para>
Further information can be found in <xref linkend="domain:ldap"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Domain_administration"><title>Domain administration</title>
<para>
<figure><title>Univention Management Console</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" fileref="illustrations/umc-overview_en.png"/>
</figure>
</para>
<para>
Access to the LDAP directory is performed via the web-based
&ucsUMC; (UMC).
</para>

<para>
Univention Directory Manager also allows the realisation of all
domain-wide administrative tasks via a command line interface. This
is particularly suitable for the integration in scripts or automated
administrative steps.
</para>

<para>
&ucsUMC; makes it possible to enter data into the LDAP directory and
then display, edit and delete them there. It is also possible to
search - filtered according to a wide range of criteria - for
data. The web interface offers a range of wizards for the
administration of user, groups, networks, computers, directory shares
and printers. The administration of computers also comprises
comprehensive functions for distributing and updating software.
</para>

<para>
The integrated LDAP directory browser can be used to make further
settings and add customer-specific object classes and attributes.
</para>
<para>
Further information can be found in <xref linkend="central:general"/>.
</para>

</section>

<section id="introduction:Computer_administration"><title>Computer administration</title>
<para>
&ucsUMC; allows not only the access to the LDAP directory with the
domain data, but also the web-based configuration and administration
of individual computers, such as the adaptation of configuration data,
the installation of software and the monitoring and control of
services and operating system. With &ucsUMS;, domain administration
and computer and server configuration is also possible from any place
via a comfortable graphic web interface.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Policy_concept"><title>Policy concept</title>
<para>
The tree-like structure of LDAP directories ensures - similar to in a
file system - that all objects (such as users, computers, etc.) are in
one container and that these containers can also be adopted by other
containers. The so-called root container forms the basis for this and
is often also called the LDAP base object.
</para>
<para>
Policies describe certain administrative settings which can be
practically be used on more than one object. They facilitate the
administration as they can be linked to containers and then apply
to all the objects in the container in question and the objects in
subfolders.
</para>
<para>
For example, users can be organised in different containers or
organisational units (which are a form of containers) depending on
which department they belong to. Settings such as the desktop
background or programs that can be run can then be connected to these
organisational units using policies and subsequently apply for all
users within the organisational unit in question.
</para>
<para>
Further information can be found in <xref linkend="central:policies"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Listener_notifier_replication"><title>Listener/notifier replication</title>
<para>
The listener/notifier mechanism is an important technical component of
the &ucsUMS;. With this, the creation, editing or deleting of freely
definable entries in the LDAP directory triggers defined actions on
the computers in question.
</para>
<para>
For example, the creation of a directory share with &ucsUMC; leads to
the share firstly being entered in the LDAP directory. The
listener/notifier mechanism then ensures that the NFS
and Samba configuration files are also expanded accordingly on the
selected server and that the directory is created in the file system
of the selected server if it does not already exist.
</para>
<para>
The listener/notifier mechanism can be easily expanded with modules
for further - even customer-specific - procedures and is
consequently used by numerous technology partners for the integration
of their products in the LDAP directory service and the &ucsUMS; for
example.
</para>
<para>
Further information can be found in <xref linkend="domain:listenernotifier"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Virtualization_management"><title>Virtualization and cloud management</title>
<para>
With the UMC module &ucsUVMM; (UVMM), UCS offers an extensive,
powerful tool for the administration of hybrid cloud environments
Virtualization servers registered in the UCS domain
and virtual machines operated on it can be centrally monitored and
administrated. In addition UVMM offers the possibility to manage virtual machines in OpenStack or
EC2 environments.
</para>
<para>
Further information can be found in <xref linkend="uvmm:chapter"/>.
</para>
</section>
</section>


<section id="introduction:Further_documentation"><title>Further documentation</title>
<para>
This manual addresses just a small selection of the possibilities in
UCS. Among other things, UCS and solutions based on UCS provide:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><simpara>Comprehensive support for complex server environments and replication scenarios</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Advanced capabilities for Windows environments</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Central network management with DNS and DHCP</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Monitoring systems and networks with Nagios</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Print server functionalities</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Thin Client support</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Fax service</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Proxy server</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Virtualization</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Integrated backup functions</simpara></listitem>
	<listitem><simpara>Linux desktop for business operations</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Further documentation related to UCS and further issues is published
under <biblioref linkend="ucs-dokumentationen"/> and in the Univention Wiki (<ulink url="http://wiki.univention.de/"/>).
</para>
</section>

<section id="introduction:Symbols_and_conventions_used_in_this_manual"><title>Symbols and conventions used in this manual</title>
<para>
The manual uses the following symbols:
</para>

<caution>
<para>
Warnings are highlighted.
</para>
</caution>

<note>
<para>
Notes are also highlighted.
</para>
</note>

<para>
This tables describes the functionality of a UMC module:

<table>
<title>Tab Nagios service</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Attribute</entry>
<entry>Description</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>

<row>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>
The unique name of a Nagios service.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>Description</entry>
<entry>
An arbitrary description of the Nagios service.
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>

<para>
Menu entries, button labels, and similar details are printed in <guimenu>bold</guimenu> lettering.
In addition, <mousebutton>button labels</mousebutton> are represented in square brackets.
</para>

<para>
Names are in <emphasis>bold</emphasis>.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>Computer names, LDAP DNs</emphasis>, <command>program names</command>, <filename>file names, file paths</filename>,
<uri>internet addresses</uri> and <emphasis>options</emphasis> are also optically accented.
</para>

<para>
<command>Commands and other keyboard input</command> is printed in the Courier font.
</para>

<programlisting>
In addition, excerpts from configuration files, screen output, etc are
printed on a grey background.
</programlisting>

<para>
A backslash (\) at the end of a line signifies that the subsequent line
feed is not to be understood as an <emphasis>end of line</emphasis>. This circumstance
may occur, for example, where commands cannot be represented in one
line in the manual, yet have to be entered in the command line in one
piece without the backslash or with the backslash and a subsequent
Enter.
</para>

<para>
The path to a function is represented in a similar way to a file
path. <guimenu>Users &ar; Add</guimenu> means for example, you have to click
<guimenu>Users</guimenu> in the main menu and <guimenu>Add</guimenu> in the submenu.
</para>
</section>
</chapter>
