<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
	<!ENTITY % extensions SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros.ent" >
	<!ENTITY % DocBookDTD PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../stylesheets/macros-en.ent" >
	%extensions;
	%DocBookDTD;
	%entities;
]>
<chapter id="monitoring::general">
	<title>Infrastructure monitoring</title>
		<para>
			UCS offers two different solutions for infrastructure monitoring. On the one hand the UCS Dashboard helps administrators
			to quickly read the state of domains and individual servers. On the other hand, under UCS 4.4, with Nagios it is possible to
			continuously check computers and services in the background and proactively trigger a notification if a warning level is
			reached. With UCS 5.0 support for the Nagios server component has been discontinued, but the systems can still be
			monitored, e.g. by UCS 4.4 Nagios servers, as described in the UCS 4.4 manual.
		</para>

		<section id="dashboard::general">
			<title>UCS Dashboard</title>
				<para>
					The UCS Dashboard app allows administrators to view the state of the domain and individual
					servers can be read quickly and clearly on so-called dashboards. The dashboards are
					accessible via a Web browser, access a database in the background, and deliver
					continuously updated reports on specific aspects of the domain or server.
				</para>

			<section id="dashboard::installation">
				<title>Installation</title>
				<para>
					The UCS Dashboard consists of three parts:
				</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<simpara>
								The UCS Dashboard app for the visualization of data from the central
								Database. This component is based on the software component
								<ulink url="https://grafana.com">
									Grafana®
								</ulink>
								<footnote>
									<para>
										The Grafana Labs Marks are trademarks of Grafana Labs, and are used
										with Grafana Labs’ permission. We are not affiliated with, endorsed
										or sponsored by Grafana Labs or its affiliates.
									</para>
								</footnote>
								.
							</simpara>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<simpara>
								The UCS Dashboard Database app, a time series database for storing
								of the metrics. This database is based on the software Prometheus.
							</simpara>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<simpara>
								The UCS Dashboard Client app for deploying the metrics of
								server systems. This is based on the Prometheus Node Exporter.
							</simpara>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					The app <emphasis>UCS Dashboard</emphasis> can be installed from the Univention App Center on a
					server in the domain. Currently, the installation is only possible on the system roles
					Primary, Backup or &ucsReplicaDN;.
					The apps <emphasis>UCS Dashboard Database</emphasis> and <emphasis>UCS Dashboard Client</emphasis> 
					are automatically installed on the same system.
				</para>
				<para>
					The app <emphasis>UCS Dashboard Client</emphasis> should be installed on every UCS system.
					Only then will the system data be displayed on the dashboard.
				</para>
			</section>

			<section id="dashboard::usage">
				<title>Usage</title>
				<para>
					After the installation, the UCS Dashboard is linked in the portal.
					Alternatively, it can be accessed directly via <uri>https://SERVERNAME-OR-IP/ucs-dashboard/</uri>.
				</para>
				<para>
					In the default setting, access is only granted to users of the
					group <systemitem class="groupname">Domain Admins</systemitem> (e.g. the user Administrator).
					<!--It is also possible to set the circle of the logon authorized persons to
					expand.-->
				</para>
				<section id="dashboard::use:domain">
					<title>Domain dashboard</title>
						<figure id="dashboard-domain">
							<title>Domain dashboard</title>
							<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations50/dashboard-domain.png"/>
						</figure>
					<para>
						After the login, the Domain dashboard is opened by default. On this
						dashboard, general information about the domain is displayed, such as
						how many servers and how many users exist in the environment.
					</para>
					<para>
						Furthermore, the UCS systems are listed on the dashboard, in a tabular overview, including
						further information, such as the server role, the installed apps or whether an update is 
						available or not.
					</para>
					<para>
						In addition, the CPU usage, memory usage, free hard disk space and
						the status of the LDAP replication are displayed.
						In this graphics all servers are displayed together.
					</para>
				</section>
				<section id="dashboard::nutzung:server">
					<title>Server dashboard</title>
						<figure id="dashboard-server">
							<title>Server dashboard</title>
							<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" align="center" fileref="illustrations50/dashboard-server.png"/>
						</figure>
					<para>
						By default, the server dashboard is also configured. On this dashboard, 
						detailed information about individual server systems are shown, such as the CPU- or
						memory usage or network throughput.
					</para>
					<para>
						The servers can be selected in the dropdown <guimenu>server</guimenu>. Then the
						graphics show the details about the selected server.
					</para>
				</section>
				<section id="dashboard::usage:mydashboard">
					<title>Own dashboards</title>
					<para>
						The two included dashboards <emphasis>domain dashboard</emphasis> and <emphasis>server
						dashboard</emphasis> can't be changed, because they are updated by Univention with updates.
					</para>
					<para>
						Instead, you can create your own dashboards. On these dashboards you can then either add already
						existing elements or new elements can be created. All you need to do is
						click on the plus sign on the left side. A new dashboard will be created
						which can be filled with elements.
					</para>
				</section>
			</section>

		</section>

	<section id="nagios::general">
	<title>Nagios</title>
	<para>
		With UCS 5.0 support for the Nagios server component has been discontinued.
		Yet, the systems can still be monitored, e.g. by UCS 4.4 Nagios servers, as described in the UCS 4.4 manual.
	</para>

	<section id="Nagios:Installation">
		<title>Installation</title>
		<para>
		In addition to the standard plugins provided with the installation of
		the <package>univention-nagios-client</package> package, additional plugins can
		be subsequently installed with the following packages:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
				<package>univention-nagios-raid</package> Monitoring of the software RAID status
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
				<package>univention-nagios-smart</package> Test of the S.M.A.R.T. status of hard drives
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
				<package>univention-nagios-opsi</package> Test of software distribution opsi
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<simpara>
				<package>univention-nagios-ad-connector</package> Test of the AD Connector
				</simpara>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
		Some of the packages are automatically set up during installation of
		the respective services. For example, if the UCS
		AD connector is set up, the monitoring plugin is included
		automatically.
		</para>
	</section>

		<section id="nagios:preconfiguredchecks">
			<title>Preconfigured Nagios checks</title>
			<para>
			During the installation, basic Nagios tests are set up
			automatically for UCS systems.
			</para>
			<informaltable>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1.2*"/>
					<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Nagios service</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_PING</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the availability of the monitored UCS system
								with the command <command>ping</command>.
								In the default setting, an error status is attained
								if the response time exceeds 50 ms or 100 ms or package
								package losses of 20% or 40% occur.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_DISK_ROOT</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors how full the <filename class="partition">/</filename> partition
								is. An error status is raised if the remaining free space falls
								below 25% or 10% in the default setting.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_DNS</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the function of the local DNS server and the
								accessibility of the public DNS server by querying the hostname
								<systemitem class="fqdomainname">www.univention.de</systemitem>.
								If no DNS forwarder is defined for the UCS domain, this request fails.
								In this case, <systemitem class="fqdomainname">www.univention.de</systemitem> can be replaced
								with the FQDN of the &ucsPrimaryDN; for example,
								in order to test the function of the name resolution.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_LDAP</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the LDAP server running on UCS Directory Nodes.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_LOAD</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the system load.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_NTP</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								requests the time from the NTP service on the monitored
								UCS system. If this deviates by more than 60 or 120 seconds,
								the error status is attained.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_SMTP</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the mail server.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_SSL</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the remaining validity period of the UCS SSL certificates.
								This plugin is only suitable for &ucsPrimaryDN; and &ucsBackupDN; systems.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_SWAP</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the utilization of the swap partition.
								An error status is raised if the remaining free space falls below the
								threshold (40% or 20% in the default setting).
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_REPLICATION</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the status of the LDAP replication
								and recognizes the creation of a <filename>failed.ldif</filename>
								file and the standstill of the replication
								and warns of large differences between the transaction IDs.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_NSCD</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the availability of the name server cache
								daemon. If there is no NSCD process running, a CRITICAL event is
								triggered; if more than one process is running, a WARNING.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_WINBIND</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the availability of the Winbind service.
								If no process is running, a CRITICAL event is triggered.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_SMBD</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the availability of the Samba service.
								If no process is running, a CRITICAL event is triggered.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_NMBD</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the availability of the NMBD service,
								which is responsible for the NetBIOS service in Samba.
								If no process is running, a CRITICAL event is triggered.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_JOINSTATUS</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the join status of a system.
								If a system has yet to join, a CRITICAL event is triggered;
								if non-run join scripts are available, a WARNING event is returned.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_KPASSWD</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the availability of the Kerberos password service
								(only available on Primary/&ucsBackupDN;s).
								If fewer or more than one process is running, a CRITICAL event is triggered.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_CUPS</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the CUPS daemon.
								If there is no <systemitem class="daemon">cupsd</systemitem> process running or the web interface
								on port 631 is not accessible, the CRITICAL status is returned.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_DANSGUARDIAN</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the DansGuardian web filter.
								If no DansGuardian process is running
								or the DansGuardian proxy is not accessible,
								the CRITICAL status is returned.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_SQUID</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								monitors the Squid proxy.
								If no squid process is running or the Squid proxy is not accessible,
								the CRITICAL status is returned.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_LIBVIRTD_KVM</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the status of a KVM virtualization server
								via a request to <command>virsh</command>
								and returns CRITICAL if the request takes longer than ten seconds.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_LIBVIRTD_XEN</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the status of a Xen virtualization server
								via a request to <command>virsh</command>
								and returns CRITICAL if the request takes longer than ten seconds.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_UVMMD</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								tests the status of the &ucsUVMM; by requesting the available nodes.
								If they cannot be resolved, CRITICAL is returned.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
			<para>
			The following Nagios services
			are only available on the respective Nagios client once additional packages have been installed
			(see <xref linkend="Nagios:Installation"/>):
			</para>
			<informaltable>
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1.2*"/>
					<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Nagios service</entry>
							<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_OPSI</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								<para>
								monitors the opsi daemon.
								If no opsi process is running or the opsi proxy is not accessible,
								the CRITICAL status is returned.
								</para>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_SMART_SDA</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								<para>
								tests the S.M.A.R.T. status of the hard drive <filename class="devicefile">/dev/sda</filename>.
								Corresponding Nagios services exist for the hard drives <filename class="partition">sdb</filename>, <filename class="partition">sdc</filename> and <filename class="partition">sdd</filename>.
								</para>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_RAID</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								<para>
								tests the status of the software RAID via <filename>/proc/mdadm</filename>
								and returns CRITICAL is one of the hard drives in the RAID association has failed
								or WARNING if a recovery procedure is in progress.
								</para>
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><systemitem class="service">UNIVENTION_ADCONNECTOR</systemitem></entry>
							<entry>
								<para>
								Checks the status of the AD connector.
								If no connector process is running, CRITICAL is reported;
								if more than one process is running per connector instance,
								a WARNING is given. If rejects occur, a WARNING is given.
								If the AD server cannot be reached, a CRITICAL status occurs.
								The plugin can also be used in multi-connector instances;
								the name of the instance must be passed on as a parameter.
								</para>
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</section>

	</section>

</chapter>
<!-- vim:set ft=docbk ts=2 sw=2 noet: -->
