<chapter id="print::general">
<title>Print services</title>

<section id="print-services:Introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
		&ucsUCS; includes a print system, which can also be used to realise
		complex environments. Printers and printer groups can be created and
		configured conveniently in &ucsUMC;. Extensions for cost
		calculation and page limitation can be installed subsequently using
		the print quota system.
	</para>
	<para>
		The print services are based on <emphasis>CUPS (Common Unix Printing
		System)</emphasis>. <emphasis>CUPS</emphasis> manages print jobs in print queues and
		converts print jobs into the native formats of the connected printers.
		The print queues are also administrated in the &ucsUMC;, see
		<xref linkend="umc:modules:printer"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		All printers set up in CUPS can be directly used by UCS systems and
		are automatically also provided for Windows computers when Samba is
		used.
	</para>
	<para>
		The technical capacities of a printer are specified in so-called PPD
		files. These files include for example whether a printer can print in
		colour, whether duplex printing is possible, whether there are several
		paper trays, which resolutions are supported and which printer control
		languages are supported (e.g., PCL or Postscript).
	</para>
	<para>
		Print jobs are transformed by CUPS with the help of filters into a
		format that the respective printer can interpret, for example into
		Postscript for a Postscript-compatible printer.
	</para>
	<para>
		UCS already includes a wide variety of filters and PPD
		files. Consequently, most printers can be employed without the need to
		install additional drivers. The setting up of additional PPD files is
		described in <xref linkend="print::ppdlisten"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		A printer can either be connected directly to the print server
		locally (e.g., via the USB port or a parallel port) or communicate
		with a printer via remote protocols (e.g., TCP/IP-compatible printers,
		which are connected via IPP or LPD).
	</para>
	<para>
		Network printers with their own IP address should be registered in the
		computer administration of &ucsUMC; as an IP managed client (see
		<xref linkend="systemrollen"/>).
	</para>
	<para>
		CUPS offers the possibility of defining printer groups. The included
		printers are used employed alternating, which allows automatic load
		distribution between neighbouring printers.
	</para>
	<para>
		The print quota system, which can be installed using
		the <package>univention-printquota</package> package, can be used to install an
		expansion for recording incurred printer costs and for limiting the
		number of pages to be printed. The setting and configuration is documented in the extended
		documentation <biblioref linkend="ext-print-doc"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		Print shares from Windows systems can also be integrated in the CUPS
		print server, see <xref linkend="print::shares"/>.
	</para>
</section>

<section id="print-services:Installing_a_print_server">
  <title>Installing a print server</title>
  <para>
	A printserver can be installed from the Univention App Center with the application
	<emphasis>Print server (CUPS)</emphasis>. Alternatively, the software package
	<package>univention-printserver</package> can be installed
	(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> must be executed after installation).
	Additional information can be found in <xref
	linkend="computers::softwaremanagement::installsoftware"/>.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="print-services:configuration">
  <title>Setting the local configuration properties of a print server</title>
  <para>
	The configuration of the CUPS print server is performed via settings from the LDAP directory
	service and &ucsUCR;. If the &ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/include/local</envar> is set to
	<emphasis>true</emphasis>, the <filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.local.conf</filename> file is included,
	in which arbitrary options can be defined.
  </para>

  <para>
	If an error occurs when working through a printer queue (e.g., because the connected printer is
	switched off), the further processing of the queue is stopped in the default setting. This must
	then be reactivated by the administrator (see <xref linkend="umc:modules:printer"/>). If the
	&ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/errorpolicy</envar> is set to <emphasis>retry-job</emphasis>, CUPS
	automatically attempts to process unsuccessful print jobs again every 30 seconds.
  </para>

</section>

<section id="print::shares">
<title>Creating a printer share</title>
	<para>
		Print shares are administrated in the <emphasis>Printers</emphasis> module of
		the &ucsUMC; with the <guimenu>Printer share</guimenu> object
		type.
	</para>
	<para>
		General information on the operation of the domain management modules
		of the &ucsUMC; and on the adding, editing, searching for and
		deleting of objects can be found in <xref linkend="central:user-interface"/>.
	</para>
	<figure id="create-printershare">
	<title>Creating a printer share</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" fileref="illustrations/create_printershare_en.png"/>
	</figure>
	<para>
		When adding/deleting/editing a printer share, the printer is
		automatically configured in CUPS. CUPS does not have an LDAP interface
		for printer configuration, instead the <filename>printers.conf</filename> file is
		generated via a listener module. If Samba is used, the printer
		shares are also automatically provided for Windows clients.
	</para>
	<table>
	<title>'General' tab</title>
		<tgroup cols="2">
			<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
			<thead>
				<row>
					<entry>Attribute</entry>
					<entry>Description</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>Name (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						This input field contains the name of the printer share, which is used
						by CUPS. The printer appears under this name in Linux and
						Windows. The name may contain alphanumeric characters (i.e., uppercase
						and lowercase letters a to z and numbers 0 to 9) as well as hyphens
						and underscores. Other characters (including blank spaces) are not
						permitted.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Spool host (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							A print server manages the printer queue for the printers to
							be shared. It converts the data to be printed into a compatible print
							format when this is necessary. If the printer is not ready, the print
							server saves the print jobs temporarily and forwards them on to the
							printer subsequently. If more than one print server is specified, the
							print job from the client will be sent to the first print server to
							become available.
						</para>
						<para>
							Only domain controllers and &ucsMember;s on which
							the <package>univention-printserver</package> package is installed are
							displayed in the list.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Protocol and Destination (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							These two input fields specify how the print server accesses the
							printer:
						</para>
						<para>
							The following list describes the syntax of the individual protocols
							for the configuration of printers connected locally to the server:
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para><uri>parallel://<replaceable>&lt;devicefile&gt;</replaceable></uri></para>
								<para>Example: <uri>parallel://dev/lp0</uri></para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para><uri>socket://<replaceable>&lt;server&gt;</replaceable>:<replaceable>&lt;port&gt;</replaceable></uri></para>
								<para>Example: <uri>socket://printer_03:9100</uri></para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para><uri>usb://<replaceable>&lt;devicefile&gt;</replaceable></uri></para>
								<para>Example: <uri>usb://dev/usb/lp0</uri></para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						<para>
							The following list describes the syntax of the individual protocols
							for the configuration of network printers:
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para><uri>http://<replaceable>&lt;server&gt;</replaceable>[:<replaceable>&lt;port&gt;</replaceable>]/<replaceable>&lt;path&gt;</replaceable></uri></para>
								<para>Example: <uri>http://192.168.0.10:631/printers/remote</uri></para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para><uri>ipp://<replaceable>&lt;server&gt;</replaceable>/printers/<replaceable>&lt;queue&gt;</replaceable></uri></para>
								<para>Example: <uri>ipp://printer_01/printers/xerox</uri></para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para><uri>lpd://<replaceable>&lt;server&gt;</replaceable>/<replaceable>&lt;queue&gt;</replaceable></uri></para>
								<para>Example: <uri>lpd://10.200.18.30/bwdraft</uri></para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
						<para>
							The <uri>cups-pdf</uri> protocol is used for integrating a pseudo printer,
							which creates a PDF document from all the print jobs. The setup is
							documented in <xref linkend="pdf-printer"/>.
						</para>
						<para>
							The <uri>file:/</uri> protocol expects a file name as a target. The print
							job is then not sent to the printer, but instead written in this file,
							which can be useful for test purposes. The file is rewritten with
							every print job.
						</para>
						<para>
							The <uri>smb://</uri> protocol can be used to mount a Windows print share.
							For example, to integrate the <emphasis>laser01</emphasis> printer share from Windows
							system <emphasis>win01</emphasis>, <emphasis>win01/laser01</emphasis> must be specified as destination.
							The manufacturer and model must be selected according to the printer in question.
							The print server uses the printer model settings to convert the print
							jobs where necessary and send these directly to the URI
							<uri>smb://win01/laser01</uri>. No Windows drivers are used in this.
						</para>
						<para>
							Independant of these settings, the printer share can be mounted by other
							Windows systems with the corresponding printer drivers.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Manufacturer</entry>
					<entry>
						When the printer manufacturer is selected, the <emphasis>Printer model</emphasis>
						selection list updates automatically.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Printer model (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						This selection list shows all the printers PPD files available for the selected
						manufacturer. If the required printer model is not there, a similar
						model can be selected and a test print used to establish correct
						function. <xref linkend="print::ppdlisten"/> explains how to expand the
						list of printer models.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Samba name</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							A printer can also be assigned an additional name by which it can be
							reached from Windows. Unlike the CUPS name (see <guimenu>Name</guimenu>), the
							Samba name may contain blank spaces and umlauts. The printer is then
							available to Windows under both the CUPS name and the Samba name.
						</para>
						<para>
							Using a Samba name in addition to the CUPS name is practical, for
							example, if the printer was already in use in Windows under a name
							which contains blank spaces or umlauts. The printer can then still be
							reached under this name without the need to reconfigure the Windows
							computers.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Enable quota support</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							If quota were activated for this printer, the quota settings on the
							<guimenu>[Print Quota]</guimenu> policy apply.
						</para>
						<para>
							The print quota system needs to be installed for this, see <biblioref linkend="ext-print-doc"/>.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Price per page</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							The user is charged the value given in this input field for every page
							printed. The incurred costs are summarised in the user's account and
							used for the accurate calculation of print costs. If no value is
							specified, print costs will not be calculated.
						</para>
						<para>
							The print quota system needs to be installed for this.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Price per print job</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							The user is charged the value given in this input field for every
							print job. The incurred costs are summarised in the user's account and
							used for the accurate calculation of print costs. If no value is
							specified, print costs will not be calculated.
						</para>
						<para>
							The print quota system needs to be installed for this.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Location</entry>
					<entry>
						This data is displayed by some applications when selecting the printer. It
						can be filled with any text.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Description</entry>
					<entry>
						This is displayed by some applications when selecting the printer. It
						can be filled with any text.
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
	<table>
	<title>'Access Control' tab</title>
		<tgroup cols="2">
			<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
			<thead>
				<row>
					<entry>Attribute</entry>
					<entry>Description</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>Access control</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							Access rights for the printer can be specified here.
							Access can be limited to certain groups or users or generally allowed
							and certain groups or users blocked specifically.
							As standard, access is available for all groups and users.
							These rights are also adopted for the corresponding Samba printer
							shares, so that the same access rights apply when printing via Samba
							as when printing directly via CUPS.
						</para>
						<para>
							This access control is useful for the management of printers spread
							across several locations, so that the users at location A do not
							see the printers of location B.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Allowed/denied users</entry>
					<entry>This lists individual users for whom access should be controlled.</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Allowed/denied groups</entry>
					<entry>This lists individual groups for whom access should be controlled.</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
</section>

<section id="druckergruppen">
<title>Creating a printer group</title>
	<para>
		CUPS offers the possibility to group printers into
		classes. These are implemented in UCS as <emphasis>printer groups</emphasis>
		Printer groups appear to clients as normal printers
		The aim of such a printer group is to create a higher
		availability of printer services. If the printer group is used to
		print, the job is sent to the first printer in the printer group to
		become available. The printers are selected based on the round robin
		principle so that the degree of utilisation is kept uniform.
	</para>
	<figure id="printergroup">
	<title>Configuring a printer group</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" fileref="illustrations/printer_group-en.png"/>
	</figure>
	<para>
		A printer group must have at least one printer as a member. Only
		printers from the same server can be members of the group.
	</para>
	<caution>
		<para>
		The possibility of grouping printers
		shares from different printer servers in a printer group makes
		it possible to select printer groups as members of a printer
		group. This could result in a printer group adopting itself as a group
		member. This must not be allowed to happen.
		</para>
	</caution>
	<para>
		Printer groups are administrated in the <emphasis>Printers</emphasis> module of
		the &ucsUMC; with the <guimenu>Printer share</guimenu> object type.
	</para>
	<para>
		General information on the operation of the domain management modules
		of the &ucsUMC; and on the adding, editing, searching for and
		deleting of objects can be found in <xref linkend="central:user-interface"/>.
	</para>
	<table>
	<title>'General' tab</title>
		<tgroup cols="2">
			<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
			<thead>
				<row>
					<entry>Attribute</entry>
					<entry>Description</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>Name (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							This input field contains the names of the printer group share, which
							is used by CUPS. The printer group appears under this name in Linux
							and Windows.
						</para>
						<para>
							The name may contain alphanumeric characters (i.e., uppercase and
							lowercase letters a to z and numbers 0 to 9) as well as hyphens and
							underscores. Other characters (including blank spaces) are not
							permitted.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Spool host (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						A range of print servers (spoolers) can be specified here to expand
						the list of printers available for selection. Printers which are
						assigned to the servers specified here can then be adopted in the
						<guimenu>Group members</guimenu> list from the selection arranged below them.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Samba name</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							A printer group can also be assigned an additional name by which it
							can reached from Windows. Unlike the CUPS name (see <emphasis>Name</emphasis>), the
							Samba name may contain blank spaces and umlauts. The printer is then
							available to Windows under both the CUPS name and the Samba name.
						</para>
						<para>
							Using a Samba name in addition to the CUPS name is practical, for
							example, if the printer group was already in use in Windows under a
							name which contains blank spaces or umlauts.
							The printer group can then still be reached under this name without
							the need to reconfigure the Windows computers.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Group members</entry>
					<entry>
						This list is used to assign printers to the printer group.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Enable quota support</entry>
					<entry>
						<para>
							If quota were activated for this printer group, the quota settings on
							the <guimenu>[Print Quota]</guimenu> tab apply.
						</para>
						<para>
							The print quota system needs to be installed for this, see <biblioref linkend="ext-print-doc"/>.
						</para>
					</entry>
				</row>

				<row>
					<entry>Price per page</entry>
					<entry>
						The user is charged the value given in this input field for every page
						printed. The incurred costs are summarised in the user's account and
						used for the accurate calculation of print costs. If no value is
						specified, print costs will not be calculated.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Price per print job</entry>
					<entry>
						The user is charged the value given in this input field for every
						print job. The incurred costs are summarised in the user's account and
						used for the accurate calculation of print costs. If no value is
						specified, print costs will not be calculated.
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
</section>

<section id="umc:modules:printer">
<title>Administration of print jobs and print queues</title>
	<para>
		The <guimenu>Printer Administration</guimenu> module of the &ucsUMC;
		allows you to check the status of the connected printers, restart
		paused printers and remove print jobs from the queues on printer
		servers.
	</para>
	<figure id="printer-admin">
	<title>Printer administration</title>
		<graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations/umc-printer_administration-en.png"/>
	</figure>
	<para>
		The start page of the module contains a search mask with which the available
		printers can be selected. The results list displays the server, name, status,
		print quota properties, location and description of the respective
		printer. The status of more than one printer can be changed simultaneously by
		selecting the printers and running either the <guimenu>deactivate</guimenu> or
		<guimenu>activate</guimenu> function.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The configuration of the print quota settings is documented in the extended documentation
	  <biblioref linkend="ext-print-doc"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
		Clicking on the printer name displays details of the selected printer. The
		information displayed includes a list of the print jobs currently in the
		printer queue. These print jobs can be deleted from the queue by selecting the
		jobs and running the <mousebutton>Delete</mousebutton> function.
	</para>
</section>

<section id="pdf-printer">
<title>Generating PDF documents from print jobs</title>
	<para>
		Installing the <package>univention-printserver-pdf</package> package expands
		the print server with a special <guimenu>cups-pdf</guimenu> printer type,
		which converts incoming print jobs into PDF documents and add them in
		a specified directory on the printer server where they are readable
		for the respective user. After the installation of the
		package, <command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> must be run.
	</para>
	<para>
		The <guimenu>cups-pdf:/</guimenu> protocol must be selected when creating a
		PDF printer in &ucsUMC; (see <xref linkend="print::shares"/>); the
		destination field remains empty.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <emphasis>PDF</emphasis> must be selected as <guimenu>Printer
	  producer</guimenu> and <emphasis>Generic CUPS-PDF
	  Printer</emphasis> as <guimenu>Printer model</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
		The target directory for the generated PDF documents is set using
		the &ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/cups-pdf/directory</envar>. As standard it is set
		to <filename>/var/spool/cups-pdf/%U</filename> so that <emphasis>cups-pdf</emphasis> uses a
		different directory for each user.
	</para>
	<para>
		Print jobs coming in anonymously are printed in the directory
		specified by the &ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/cups-pdf/anonymous</envar> (standard setting:
		<filename>/var/spool/cups-pdf</filename>).
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the default setting, generated PDF documents are kept without any restrictions. If the
	  &ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/cups-pdf/cleanup/enabled</envar> is set to <emphasis>true</emphasis>,
	  old PDF print jobs are deleted via a Cron job. The storage time in days can be configured
	  using the &ucsUCRV; <envar>cups/cups-pdf/cleanup/keep</envar>.
	</para>

</section>

<section id="print-services:winclients">
  <title>Mounting of print shares in Windows clients</title>

  <para>
	The printer shares set up in the &ucsUMC; can be added as network printers on Windows
	systems. This is done via the Control Panel under <guimenu>Add a device &ar; Add a
	printer</guimenu>. The printer drivers need to be set up during the first access. If the
	drivers are stored on the server side (see below), the drivers are assigned automatically.
  </para>

  <para>
	Printer shares are usually operated using the Windows printer drivers
	provided. The network printer can alternatively be set up on the
	Windows side with a standard Postscript printer driver. If a colour
	printer should be accessed, a driver for a Postscript-compatible
	colour printer should be used on the Windows side, e.g., HP Color
	Laserjet 8550.
  </para>

  <caution>
	<para>
	  The printer can only be accessed by a regular user when he has local
	  permissions for driver installation or the respective printer drivers
	  were stored on the printer server. If this is not the case, Windows
	  may issue an error warning that the permissions are insufficient to
	  establish a connection to the printer.
	</para>
  </caution>

  <para>
	Windows supports a mechanism for providing the printer drivers on the print server
	(<emphasis>Point 'n' Print</emphasis>). The following guide describes the provision of the
	printer drivers in Windows 7 for a print share configured in the UMC. Firstly, the printer
	drivers must be stored on the print server. There are a number of pitfalls in the Windows user
	wizard, so it is important to follow the individual steps precisely.
  </para>

  <para>
  	<orderedlist>
  	  <listitem><simpara>
		Firstly, the printer drivers must be downloaded from the manufacturer's website. If you
		are using an environment in which 64-bit installations of Windows are used, you will need 
		both versions of the drivers (32 and 64 bit). The INF files are required.
	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
		You now need to start Windows Explorer and open the network environment there. Here, you
		need to select the print server on which you want to create the printer share. You can
		display a list of all printer shares by clicking on <guimenu>View remote printer</guimenu>
		in the menu bar at the top.
	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
		You now need to right-click on the empty space below the printer shares (not on one of the
		shares, as this will open the printer share's context-sensitive menu!) and select
		<guimenu>Server Properties</guimenu>. Then select <guimenu>Add &ar; Next &ar; Select x86
		and x64 &ar; Next &ar; Have Disk</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Drivers</guimenu>
		tab. You then need to select the INF file of the 64-bit driver (x64) in the file dialogue
		which opens. Once confirmed with <guimenu>Next &ar; Apply</guimenu>, the 64-bit
		driver is copied onto the print server. Another file dialogue now opens in which the 32-bit
		driver (x86) can be uploaded in the same way.
	  </simpara></listitem>

 	  <listitem><simpara>
		After these steps the drivers are stored in the directory
		<filename>/var/lib/samba/drivers</filename> on the print server.
 	  </simpara></listitem>



  	</orderedlist>
  </para>


  <para>
	The printer share is now linked to the uploaded printer driver:
  	<orderedlist>
  	  <listitem><simpara>
		You now need to start Windows Explorer and open the network environment there. Here, you
		need to select the print server on which you want to create the printer share. You can
		display a list of all printer shares by clicking on <guimenu>View remote printers</guimenu>
		in the menu bar at the top. You now need to select a printer by left-clicking on it, turning
		it blue. Now right-click and select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> (Caution: Another dialogue
		opens if the printer has not been selected with a left click!).
  	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
		If no printer driver is yet stored, the following error is displayed, which must be
		confirmed with <guimenu>No</guimenu>.

  		<figure>
  		  <title>Error message during first access</title>
  		  <graphic scalefit="1" width="40%" fileref="illustrations/windows-printerdriver-en.png"/>
  		</figure>
  	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
		The uploaded driver must now be selected from the dropdown menu under
		<guimenu>Driver</guimenu> on the <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu> tab. Then click on
		<guimenu>Apply</guimenu> (Important: Do not click <guimenu>OK</guimenu>!).
  	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
		A dialogue is now shown asking whether you trust the printer. This must be confirmed with
		<guimenu>Install driver</guimenu>. Important: You must not click directly on
		<guimenu>OK</guimenu> - instead you must switch to the <guimenu>General</guimenu>
		tab. The old name of the printer share should still be displayed on the tab. If the printer
		share has been renamed, it is no longer associated with the share! If this is the case, the
		name of the printer on the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab (the first input field beside
		the stylised printer symbol) must be changed back to the name of the printer share. This is
		done using the <guimenu>Samba name</guimenu> field configured in the UMC's printer
		management; if it is blank, then the value from <guimenu>Name</guimenu>.
  	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
		Then click on <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> and <guimenu>OK</guimenu>. The printer drivers stored
		on the server side are downloaded onto the client, so e.g. a test page can be printed.
  	  </simpara></listitem>
  	</orderedlist>
  </para>
</section>

<section id="print::ppdlisten">
<title>Integrating additional PPD files</title>
	<para>
		The technical capacities of a printer are specified in so-called PPD
		files. These files include for example whether a printer can print in
		colour, whether duplex printing is possible, whether there are several
		paper trays, which resolutions are supported and which printer control
		languages are supported (e.g., PCL or Postscript).
	</para>
	<para>
		In addition to the PPD files already included in the standard scope,
		additional ones can be added via the &ucsUMC;. The PPDs are generally
		provided by the printer manufacturer and need to be copied into
		the <filename>/usr/share/ppd</filename> directory on the print servers.
	</para>
	<para>
		The printer driver lists are administrated in
		the <guimenu>LDAP directory</guimenu> module of the &ucsUMC;. There you need
		to switch to the <emphasis>univention</emphasis> container and then to
		the <emphasis>cups</emphasis> subcontainer. Printer driver lists already exist
		for the majority of printer manufacturers. These can be expanded or
		new ones can be added.
	</para>
	<table>
	<title>'General' tab</title>
		<tgroup cols="2">
			<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
			<thead>
				<row>
					<entry>Attribute</entry>
					<entry>Description</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>Name (*)</entry>
					<entry>
						The name of the printer driver list. The name under which the list
						appears in the <guimenu>Printer model</guimenu> selection list on
						the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab for printer shares (see
						<xref linkend="print::shares"/>).
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Driver</entry>
					<entry>
						The path to the ppd file or to the <filename>/usr/share/ppd/</filename>
						directory. For example, if the <filename>/usr/share/ppd/laserjet.ppd</filename>
						should be used, <filename>laserjet.ppd</filename> must be entered here. gzip
						compressed files (file ending .gz) can also be entered here.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>Description</entry>
					<entry>
						A description of the printer driver, under which it appears in
						the <guimenu>Printer model</guimenu> selection list on
						the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab for printer shares.
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
</section>
</chapter>
