<chapter id="users:general">
    <title>User management</title>
    <para>
        UCS integrates central identity management according to the
        <emphasis>same user, same password</emphasis> principle.
        All user information are managed
        centrally in UCS via &ucsUMC; and stored in the LDAP directory
        service.
    </para>
    <para>
        All the services integrated in the domain access the central account
        information, i.e., the same username and password are used for the
        user login to a Windows client as for the login on the IMAP server.
    </para>
    <para>
        The domain-wide management of user data reduces the administrative
        efforts as changes do not need to be subsequently configured on
		different individual systems. Moreover, this also avoids subsequent errors
		arising from inconsistencies between the individual datasets.
    </para>
    <section id="users::management">
        <title>User management with Univention Management Console</title>
        <para>
			Users are managed in the UMC module <emphasis>Users</emphasis>
			(see <xref linkend="central:user-interface"/>).
        </para>
        <para>
		  In the default setting, a simplified wizard for creating a user is shown, which only
		  requests the most important settings. All attributes can be shown by clicking on
		  <guimenu>Advanced</guimenu>. The simplified wizard can be deactivated by setting the
		  &ucsUCRV; <envar>directory/manager/web/modules/users/user/wizard/disabled</envar> to
		  <emphasis>true</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<figure id="user-create">
			<title>Creating a user in UMC</title>
			<graphic scalefit="1" width="65%" align="center" fileref="illustrations40/users_user_en.png"/>
		</figure>
		<figure id="user-create-advanced">
			<title>Advanced user settings</title>
			<graphic scalefit="1" width="90%" align="center" fileref="illustrations40/users_user_advanced_en.png"/>
		</figure>
        <table>
            <title>'General' tab</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>User name</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                This is the name, by which the user logs into the system. The name has to
                                begin with a letter which has to be followed by: letters a-z in lower case,
                                numerals 0-9, dots, hyphens, or underlines. User names may not contain blank spaces.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                In order to ensure compatibility to non-UCS systems the creation of users
                                which are only distinguished from each other by upper and lower case letters
                                is prevented. Thus, if the user name <emphasis>smith</emphasis> already exists, then the user
                                name <emphasis>Smith</emphasis> cannot be created.
                            </para>
                            <para>
							  In the default setting, it is not possible to create a user with the same name as an
							  existing group. If the &ucsUCRV; <envar>directory/manager/user_group/uniqueness</envar>
							  is set to <emphasis>false</emphasis>, this check is removed.
							</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Arbitrary descriptions for the user can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Password</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The user's password has to be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Password (retype)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            In order to avoid spelling errors, the user's password has to be entered for a
                                second time.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Override password history</entry>
                        <entry>
                            By checking this box, the password history is overridden for this user and for
                            this password change. This means, with this change the user can be assigned a
                            password which is already in use. Further details on user password management
                            can be found in <xref linkend="users:passwords"/>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Override password check</entry>
                        <entry>
                            By checking this box, the requirements for the length of the password and for password quality checks are
                            overridden for this user and for this password change. This means, the user
                            can e.g. be assigned a shorter password than would be possible according to the
                            defined minimum length. Further details on the password policies for users can
                            be found in <xref linkend="users:passwords"/>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Primary e-mail address</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The e-mail address of the user is declared here, see
                            <xref linkend="mail::management::users"/>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Title</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The title of the user is to be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>First name</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The first name of the user is to be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Last name</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The last name of the user is to be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Display name</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The display name is automatically composed of the first and
                            surnames. It generally does not need to be changed. The screen name is
                            used for the synchronisation with Active Directory and Samba 4 among
                            other things.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Organisation</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The organisation is to be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Birthday</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This field is used to save a user's birthday.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Picture of the user (JPEG format)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This mask can be used to save a picture of the user in LDAP in JPEG format. In
                            the default settings the file size is limited to 512 kilobytes.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Employee number</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Numbers for staff members can be entered in this field.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Employee type</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The category of the staff member can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Superior</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The superior of the user can be selected here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>'Groups' tab</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Primary group</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This select list can be used for specifying the user's primary
                            group. All the groups registered in the domain are open for selection. By
                            default, the group <emphasis>Domain Users</emphasis> is preset.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Groups</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Here it is possible to set further group memberships for the user in
                            addition to the primary group.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>'Account' tab</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Account deactivation</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                The <guimenu>Account deactivation</guimenu> selection field can be used to
                                deactivate the user account for one or more login methods. As long as the
                                respective account type is deactivated, the user cannot log into the system. This
                                is typically used when a user leaves the company. In a heterogeneous
                                environment, an account deactivation might also be caused by external tools; in that
                                case the selection field reflects the account status. Normally users should
                                always be deactivated for all account types. The following deactivation states can be
                                realised:
                            </para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>None</guimenu> - Basic status; all logins are possible.
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>All disabled</guimenu> - All account types are blocked.
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Windows disabled</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Kerberos disabled</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>POSIX disabled</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Windows and POSIX disabled</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Windows and Kerberos disabled</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>POSIX and Kerberos disabled</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                            <para>
                                The following interconnections between the different login methods are
                                derived from the UCS PAM configuration:
                            </para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        The Linux login (e.g., on GDM or a tty) is only deactivated if all
                                        login methods are deactivated; a deactivated POSIX account alone is not enough.
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        Samba requires a not-deactivated POSIX account - that means that the
                                        deactivation of the POSIX account automatically deactivates Samba as well.
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        The Kerberos library (Heimdal) also evaluates the Samba account settings - that means that the
                                        deactivation of the Windows account will also deactivate Kerberos.
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Locked login methods</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                This selection field can be used to block individual login methods. This
                                can happen automatically for security reasons, for example, if a user has
                                entered his password incorrectly too often, see <xref linkend="users:faillog"/>.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                Normally users should always be blocked for all login methods.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                In contrast to <guimenu>Account deactivation</guimenu>, the account is not blocked,
                                but the login is denied. The following login methods can be restricted:
                            </para>
                                <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>None</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Locked all login methods</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Locked Windows/Kerberos only</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                    <listitem>
										<simpara>
                                        <guimenu>Locked POSIX/LDAP only</guimenu>
										</simpara>
                                    </listitem>
                                </itemizedlist>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Account expiry date</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                A date is specified in this input field on which the account will
                                automatically be locked. This is practical for user accounts that
                                only need to be active for a certain period of time, e.g., for
                                interns.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                If the date is deleted or replaced by a different, future date, the user will
                                regain the right to log in.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Password expiry date</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                If the password is subject to an expiry date, then this date is displayed in
                                this entry field. This entry field cannot be edited directly, see
                                <xref linkend="users:passwords"/>.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                If a password expiry interval is defined, the password expiry date is
                                automatically adjusted when passwords are changed.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                If no <guimenu>Expiry interval</guimenu> is declared, the old expiry date will be
                                deleted and no new date will be set.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Change password on next login</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is ticked, then the user has to change his password during
                            the next login procedure.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Windows home drive</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If the Windows home directory for this user is to show up on a different
                            Windows drive than that specified by the Samba configuration, then the
                            corresponding drive letter can be entered here, e.g. <emphasis>M:</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Windows home path</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The path of the directory which is to be the user's Windows home directory, is
                            to be entered here, e.g. <emphasis>\\ucs-file-server\smith</emphasis>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Windows logon script</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The user-specific logon script relative to the Netlogon share is entered here, e.g.
                            <emphasis>scripts\user.bat</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Windows profile directory</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The profile directory for the user can be entered here, e.g.
                            <emphasis>\\ucs-file-server\user\profile</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Relative ID</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The relative ID (RID) is the local part of the SID. If a user is to be
                            assigned a certain RID, the ID in question can be entered in this field. If no
                            RID is assigned, the next available RID will automatically be used. The RID
                            cannot be subsequently changed. Integers from 1000 upwards are permitted. RIDs
                            below 1000 are reserved to standard groups and other special objects.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Samba privileges</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This selection mask can be used to assign a user selected Windows
                            systems rights, for example the permission to join a system to the
                            domain.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Permitted times for Windows logins</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                This input field contains time periods for which this user can log on
                                to Windows computers.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                If no entry is made in this field, the user can log in at any time of day.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Allow the authentication only on these Microsoft Windows hosts</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This setting specifies the clients where the user may log in. If no settings
                            are made, the user can log into any client.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>UNIX home directory</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The path of the user's home directory.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Login shell</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The user's login shell is to be entered in this field. This program is started
                            if the user performs a text-based login. By default, <filename>/bin/bash</filename> is preset.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>User ID</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                If the user is to be assigned a certain user ID, the ID in question
                                can be entered in this field. If no value is specified, a free user ID
                                is assigned automatically.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                The user ID can only
                                be declared when adding the user. When the user data are subsequently edited,
                                the user ID will be represented in grey and barred from change.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Group ID of the primary group</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The group ID of the user's primary group is shown here. The primary
                            group can be changed in the <guimenu>General</guimenu> tab.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Home share</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If a share is selected here, the home directory is stored on the
                            specified server. If no selection is made, the user data are saved on
                            the respective login system.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Home share path</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The path of the home directory relative to the <guimenu>Home share</guimenu> is
                            declared here. The username is already preset as a default value when creating a user.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>'Contact' tab</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>E-mail address(es)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                Additional e-mail addresses can be saved here. These are not evaluated
                                by the mail server.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                The values of this attribute are stored in the LDAP attribute <emphasis>mail</emphasis>.
                                Most address books applications using an LDAP search function will search for
                                an e-mail address by this attribute.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Telephone number(s)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This field contains the user's business phone number.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Room number</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The room number of the user.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Department number</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The department number of the user can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Street</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The street and house number of the user's business address can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Postal code</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This field contains the post code of the user's business address.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>City</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This field contains the city of the user's business address.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Private telephone number(s)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The private fixed network phone number can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Mobile telephone number(s)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The user's mobile numbers can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Pager telephone number(s)</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Pager numbers can be entered here.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Private postal address</entry>
                        <entry>
                            One or more of the user's private postal addresses can be entered in this
                            field.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>'Mail' tab</title>
            <tgroup cols="1">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                This tab is displayed in the advanced settings.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                The settings are described in <xref linkend="mail::management::users"/>.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>

		<para>
		  The following tab configures settings for working on Windows terminal servers.
		</para>

        <table>
            <title>'Windows terminal server' tab (advanced settings)</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Home directory for Windows terminal services</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The directory path which is to be the user's Windows home directory on
                            the terminal server can be entered here, e.g.
                            <emphasis>\\ucs-file-server\ts\user</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Home drive for Windows terminal services</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If the Windows home directory for this user is to appear on a different Windows
                            drive than specified in the Samba configuration, the respective letter of
                            the drive can be entered here followed by a colon, e.g. <emphasis>M:</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Startup command</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Path to a program which should be run when a terminal session is started.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Working directory for startup command</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The program's working directory, which is entered under <guimenu>Startup command</guimenu>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Use client configuration for startup command</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Both configuration settings <guimenu>Startup command</guimenu> and
                            <guimenu>Working directory for startup command</guimenu> can be overwritten by the
                            client application. If this checkbox is activated, the client configuration is
                            used.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Connect client drives at login</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The drives of the connecting client computer can be made available
                            during a terminal server session when this checkbox is activated.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Connect client printers at login</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The client printers are connected during log-in to the terminal server and
                            are thus available during the terminal server session.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Make client default printer the default printer for Windows terminal services</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is activated the client standard printer will be declared the
                            standard printer for this terminal server session.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Allow Windows terminal server login</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is activated the user can log on to a terminal server.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CTX Mirroring</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This selection list specifies whether a user session can be mirrored.
                            If <guimenu>Disabled</guimenu> is selected the session cannot be mirrored.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Terminated or timed-out sessions</entry>
                        <entry>
                            In this selection list one can select whether ended or expired connections
                            should be <guimenu>Disconnected</guimenu>ed or <guimenu>Reset</guimenu>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Reconnect session</entry>
                        <entry>
                            Here you can select whether the ended connection to each client or just the
                            previous client can be rebuilt.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CTX RAS Dialin</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                This option configures the callback function of a remote access server.
                                If enabled, the dialin line of the user is disconnected after authentication
                                and the user is called back.
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                If an entry with the <guimenu>Input On</guimenu> option is selected, the user
                                who initiated the mirroring will be given the permission to perform keyboard
                                inputs and mouse action in the mirrored session. If an entry with the
                                <guimenu>Message On</guimenu> option is selected, a message is shown on
                                the client stating that a request has been made to mirror the session.
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Profile directory for Windows terminal services</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The path to the Windows profile which is to be used in the terminal server
                            session should be entered here. If no value is entered, the standard profile
                            path is used.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Keyboard layout</entry>
                        <entry>
                            The keyboard layout for the terminal server session.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <table>
            <title>'(Options)' tab</title>
            <!--para>
                This tab makes it possible to select individual LDAP object classes for the
                user.
            </para-->
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Attribute</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Mail account</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is not ticked, the user will not be assigned the object class
                            <emphasis>univentionMail</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Kerberos principal</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is not ticked, the user will not be assigned the object
                            classes <emphasis>krb5Principal</emphasis> and <emphasis>krb5KDCEntry</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Samba account</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is not ticked, the user will not be assigned the object class
                            <emphasis>sambaSamAccount</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>POSIX account</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is not ticked, the user will not be assigned the object
                            classes <emphasis>posixAccount</emphasis> and <emphasis>shadowAccount</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Personal information</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is not ticked, the user will not be assigned the object
                            classes <emphasis>organizationalPerson</emphasis> and <emphasis>inetOrgPerson</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Public key infrastructure account</entry>
                        <entry>
                            If this checkbox is not ticked, the user will not be assigned the object class
                            <emphasis>pkiUser</emphasis>.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Simple authentication account</entry>
                        <entry>
                            This option can be used for creating user objects which have only a username
                            and a password. With these users, authentication is possible against the
                            LDAP directory service exclusively; logging into UCS or Windows systems is not
                            possible. If this option is activated, the object classes <emphasis>uidObject</emphasis> and
                            <emphasis>simpleSecurityObject</emphasis> will be used.
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
    </section>
    <section id="users:passwords">
        <title>User password management</title>
        <para>
            Passwords which are difficult to guess and regular password changes
            are an essential element of the system security of a UCS domain. The
            following properties can be configured for users using a
            <emphasis>password</emphasis> policy.

			If Samba is used, the settings of the Samba domain object
			(see <xref linkend="users:password:samba"/>) apply for logins to Window clients.
			The settings of the Samba domain object and the policy should be set identically,
			otherwise different password requirements will apply for logins to Windows and UCS systems.
		</para>

        <para>
		  The password is saved in different attributes for every user saved in the management
		  system:
		</para>
		  <itemizedlist>
			<listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>krb5Key</emphasis> attribute stores the Kerberos
			password.</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>userPassword</emphasis> attribute stores the Unix password
			(In other Linux distributions present in <filename>/etc/shadow</filename>).</simpara></listitem>
			<listitem><simpara>The <emphasis>sambaNTPassword</emphasis> attribute stores the NT
			password hash used by Samba.</simpara></listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
        <para>
		  Password changes are always initiated via Kerberos in the UCS PAM configuration.
		</para>

            <figure id="password-policy">
                <title>Configuring a password policy</title>
                <graphic scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="illustrations40/users_policy_password_en.png"/>
            </figure>
            <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem> 
				<para>
				  The <emphasis>history length</emphasis> saves the last password hashes. These
				  passwords can then not be used by the user as a new password when setting a new
				  password. With a password history length of five, for example, five new passwords
				  must be set before a password can be reused. If no password history check should be
				  performed, the value must be set to 0.
				</para>

				<para>
				  The passwords are not stored retroactively. Example: If ten passwords were stored,
				  and the value is reduced to three, the oldest seven passwords will be deleted
				  during the next password change. If then the value is increased again, the number
				  of stored passwords initially remains at three, and is only increased by each
				  password change.
				</para>
			  </listitem>

			  <listitem>
				<simpara>
				  The <emphasis>password length</emphasis> is the minimum length in characters that
				  a user password must comply with. If no value is entered here, the minimum size is
				  eight characters. The default value of eight characters for password length is
				  fixed, so it always applies if no policy is set and the <guimenu>Override password
				  check</guimenu> checkbox is not ticked. This means it even applies if the
				  <emphasis>default-settings</emphasis> password policy has been deleted. If no
				  password length check should be performed, the value must be set to 0.
				</simpara>
			  </listitem>

                <listitem>
					<simpara>
                    A <emphasis>password expiry interval</emphasis> demands regular password
                    changes. A password change is demanded during logons to &ucsUMC;, to Kerberos,
                    on Windows clients and on UCS systems following expiry of the period
                    in days. The remaining validity of the password is displayed in the
                    user management under <guimenu>Password expiry date</guimenu> in the
                    <guimenu>Account</guimenu> tab.
					If this input field is left blank, no password expiry interval is applied.
					</simpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If the option <emphasis>Password quality check</emphasis> is activated,
                        additional checks - including dictionary checks - are performed for
                        password changes in Samba, &ucsUMC; and Kerberos.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The configuration is done via &ucsUCR; and should occur on all login
                        servers. The following checks can be enforced:
                    </para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
								<simpara>
                                Minimum number of digits in the new password
                                (<envar>password/quality/credit/digits</envar>).
								</simpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
								<simpara>
                                Minimum number of uppercase letters in the new password
                                (<envar>password/quality/credit/upper</envar>).
								</simpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
								<simpara>
                                Minimum number of lowercase letters in the new password
                                (<envar>password/quality/credit/lower</envar>).
								</simpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
								<simpara>
                                Minimum number of characters in the new password which are
                                neither letters nor digits (<envar>password/quality/credit/other</envar>).
								</simpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
								<simpara>
                                Individual characters/digits can be excluded
                                (<envar>password/quality/forbidden/chars</envar>).
								</simpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
								<simpara>
                                Individual characters/figures can be made compulsory
                                (<envar>password/quality/required/chars</envar>).
								</simpara>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="users:password:samba">
	  <title>Password settings for Windows clients when using Samba</title>

	  <para>
		With the Samba domain object, one can set the password
		requirements for logins to Windows clients in a Samba domain.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The Samba domain object is managed via the
		UMC module <emphasis>LDAP directory</emphasis>. It can
		be found in the <emphasis>samba</emphasis> container below
		the LDAP base and carries the domain's NetBIOS name.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		The settings of the Samba domain object and the policy (see
		<xref linkend="users:passwords"/>) should be set identically,
		otherwise different password requirements will apply for
		logins to Windows and UCS systems.
	  </para>

	  <para>
		<table>
		  <title>'General' tab</title>
		  <tgroup cols="2">
			<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
			<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
			<thead>
			  <row>
				<entry>Attribute</entry>
				<entry>Description</entry>
			  </row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
			  <row>
				<entry>Password length</entry>
				<entry>
				  The minimum number of characters for a user password.
				</entry>
			  </row>

			  <row>
				<entry>Passwort history</entry>
				<entry>
				  The latest password changes are saved in the form of
				  hashes. These passwords can then not be used by the
				  user as a new password when setting a new
				  password. With a password history of five, for
				  example, five new passwords must be set before a
				  password can be reused.
				</entry>
			  </row>

			  <row>
				<entry>Minimum password age</entry>
				<entry>
				  The period of time set for this must have at least
				  expired since the last password change before a user
				  can reset his password again.
				</entry>
			  </row>

			  <row>
				<entry>Maximum password age</entry>
				<entry>
				  Once the saved period of time has elapsed, the
				  password must be changed again by the user the next
				  time he logs in. If the value is left blank, the
				  password is infinitely valid.
				</entry>
			  </row>

			</tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		</table>
	  </para>

	</section>

    <section id="user-management:Password_changes_by_users_via_UMC">
		<title>Password change by user via &ucsUMC;</title>
		<para>
			In &ucsUMC;, every user can reset his password via the
			<guimenu>Change password</guimenu> module. The module can also be opened
			by selecting the <guimenu>Settings &ar; Change password</guimenu>
			entry in the top right user menu.
			To change the password, the current password must be entered first.
			The change is performed directly via the PAM stack
			(see <xref linkend="computers:Authentication__PAM"/>) and is
			then available centrally for all services.
		</para>
    </section>

    <section id="users:faillog">
        <title>Automatic lockout of users after failed login attempts</title>
        <para>
            As standard, a user can enter his password incorrectly any number of times. To
            hinder brute force attacks on passwords, an automatic lockout for user accounts
            can be activated after a configured number of failed log-in attempts. The lockout
            is activated locally per computer system as standard. In other words, if a
            user enters his password incorrectly too many times on one system, he can
            still login on another system. Setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>auth/faillog/lock_global</envar>
            will make the lock effective globally and register it in the LDAP. The global
            lock can only be set on domain controller master/backup systems as other
            system roles do not possess the requisite permissions in the LDAP
            directory. On these system roles, the user is, however, locally locked or
            unlocked again via the listener module.
        </para>
        <caution>
			<para>
            This setting can also be misused, for example when a user has locked his
            screen and another user enters the password incorrectly several times in his
            absence. In this case, the user must contact the administrator to have his
            account unlocked.
			</para>
        </caution>
        <para>
            The automatic lockout of users following failed logins can be activated by
            setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>auth/faillog</envar> to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>. The upper limit of failed log-in
            attempts at which an account lockout is activated is configured
            in the &ucsUCRV; <envar>auth/faillog/limit</envar>. The counter is reset each time the password
            is entered correctly.
        </para>
        <para>
            As standard, the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user is excluded from the password lock, but can also be
            subjected to it by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>auth/faillog/root</envar> to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.
        </para>
        <para>
            As standard, the lockout is not subject to time limitations and must be reset by
            the administrator. However, it can also be reset automatically after a certain
            interval has elapsed. This is done by specifying a time period in seconds
            in &ucsUCRV; <envar>auth/faillog/unlock_time</envar>. If the value is set to 0, the lock is
            reset immediately.
        </para>
        <para>
            If accounts are locked locally, the administrator can unlock a user by
            entering the command <command>faillog -r USERNAME</command>. If the lock occurs
            globally in the LDAP, the user can be reset in
            the <guimenu>User account</guimenu> tab of a user in &ucsUDM;.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="users:templates">
        <title>User templates</title>
        <para>
            A user template can be used to preset settings when creating a user.
            If at least one user template is defined, it can be selected when creating a user.
        </para>
        <figure id="user-create-template">
            <title>Selecting a user template</title>
            <graphic scalefit="1" width="70%" align="center" fileref="illustrations40/users_usertemplate_en.png"/>
        </figure>
        <para>
            User templates are administrated in the UMC module <guimenu>LDAP directory</guimenu>.
            There one needs to switch to the
            <emphasis>univention</emphasis> container and then to the <emphasis>templates</emphasis>
            subcontainer. A new user template can be created here via the
            <guimenu>Add</guimenu> with the object type
            <guimenu>Settings: User template</guimenu>.
        </para>
        <para>
            In a user template, either a fixed value can be specified (e.g., for
            the address) or an attribute of the user management
            referenced. Attributes are then referenced in chevrons.
        </para>
        <para>
            A list of possible attributes can be displayed with the command:
        </para>
            <programlisting language="sh">
univention-director-manager users/user
            </programlisting>
        <para>
            in the section <emphasis>users/user variables</emphasis> of the output.
        </para>
        <para>
            If a user template is used for adding a user, this template will
            overwrite all the fields with the preset values of the template. In
            doing so, an empty field is set to "".
        </para>
        <para>
            It is also possible to only use partial values of attributes or
            convert values in uppercase/lowercase.
        </para>

        <para>
		  For example, the UNIX home directory can be stored under
		  <filename>/home/&lt;title&gt;.&lt;lastname&gt;</filename> or the primary e-mail address
		  can be predefined with
		  <emphasis>&lt;firstname&gt;.&lt;lastname&gt;@firma.com</emphasis>. Substitutions are
		  generally possibly for any value, but there is no syntax or semantics check. So, if no
		  first name is specified when creating a user, the above e-mail address would begin with a
		  dot and would thus be invalid according to the e-mail standard. Similar sources of error
		  can also occur when handling file paths etc. Non-resolvable attributes (for instance due
		  to typing errors in the template) are deleted.
		</para>

        <para>
		  If only a single character of an attribute is required instead of the complete attribute
		  value, the index of the required character can be entered in the user template in square
		  brackets after the name of the attribute. The count of characters of the attribute begins
		  with 0, so that index 1 corresponds to the second character of the attribute
		  value. Accordingly, <emphasis>&lt;firstname&gt;[0].&lt;lastname&gt;@firma.com</emphasis>
		  means an e-mail address will consist of the first letter of the first name plus the lastname.
		</para>

        <para>
		  A substring of the attribute value can be defined by entering a range in square
		  brackets. In doing so, the index of the first required character and the index of the last
		  required character plus one are to be entered. For example, the input
		  <emphasis>&lt;firstname&gt;[2:5]</emphasis> returns the third to fifth character of the
		  first name.
		</para>

        <para>
		  Adding <emphasis>&lt;:lower&gt;</emphasis> or <emphasis>&lt;:upper&gt;</emphasis> to the
		  attribute name converts the attribute value to lowercase or uppercase, e.g.,
		  <emphasis>&lt;firstname:lower&gt;</emphasis>. If a modificator like
		  <emphasis>&lt;:lower&gt;</emphasis> is appended to the entire field, the complete value is
		  transformed, e.g. <emphasis>&lt;lastname&gt;@company.com&lt;:lower&gt;</emphasis>.
		</para>

        <para>
		  The option <emphasis>&lt;:umlauts&gt;</emphasis> can be used to convert special characters
		  such as ,  or  into the corresponding ASCII characters.
		</para>

        <para>
		  It is also possible to combine options, e.g: <emphasis>&lt;:umlauts,upper&gt;</emphasis>.
		</para>

    </section>
</chapter>
