<chapter id="windows:Services_for_Windows"><title>Services for Windows</title>
<section id="windows:general">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>
For the purposes of Windows systems, UCS can assume the tasks of Windows server systems:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Domain controller function</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>File services</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Authentication services</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Print services</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
All these services are provided by Samba in UCS. Two different Samba
versions can be employed in UCS:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>Samba 3</emphasis> implements domain services based on the domain
technology of Microsoft Windows NT. Samba 3 is the current, stable and
tried-and-tested main release series of the Samba project and has been
integrated in UCS for many years.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><emphasis>Samba 4</emphasis> is the next generation of the Samba suite. The
most important innovation of Samba 4 is the support of domain,
directory and authentication services which are compatible with
Microsoft Active Directory. This means that Active
Directory-compatible Windows domains can be constructed with Samba
4. These also allow the use of the tools provided by Microsoft for the
management of users or group policies (GPOs) for example. The versions
of Samba 4 currently published by the Samba project are expected to
undergo more intensive changes in their further development than Samba
3. Univention has tested the required components for the provision of Active
Directory-compatible domain services with Samba 4 and integrated them
in UCS in close cooperation with the Samba team. Parallel to this,
Samba 3 was integrated with Samba 4 for UCS. This means that the
tried-and-tested file and print service of Samba 3 can be used at the
same time as the use of Active Directory-compatible domain services.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
An overview of the functional differences between Samba 3 and Samba 4
can be found in the Univention Wiki <biblioref linkend="wiki-samba4"/>.
</para>
<para>
In addition to Samba 4, UCS also integrates an additional component
for the syncronisation with Active Directory (AD): the Univention Active
Directory Connector. In contrast to Samba 4, however, this operates a
separate AD domain based on Microsoft Windows, which can be
bidirectionally or unidirectionally synchronised, see
<xref linkend="ad-connector:general"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:Installation_and_components_of_a_Samba_domain"><title>Installation and components of a Samba domain</title>
<para>
A Samba domain is composed of at least one domain controller.
Windows clients and UCS &ucsMember;s can join the trust context of
the Samba domain as domain members.
Such servers do not provide login services, but may offer file and
print services, for example. Login to these servers is then performed
against the UCS user data. UCS-based &ucsMember;s are only provided
via Samba 3.
</para>
<para>
Domain joining of Windows clients is described in
<xref linkend="windows-domaenenbeitritt"/>.
</para>
<para>
Windows domain controllers can neither join the domain with Samba 3
nor with Samba 4. This function is planned for Samba 4 at a later
point in time.
</para>
<para>
The name of the Samba domain is specified during installation of
the &ucsMaster;, depending on whether Samba is installed on the
system or not. The name of the domain is saved in
the &ucsUCRV; <envar>windows/domain</envar>.
</para>
<para>
Samba 4 can not join an Active Directory Forest yet at this
point. (For Samba 3 this function is not available because of
the lack of support for the Active Directory technology.)
</para>

<section id="windows:setup3">
  <title>Installation and components of a Samba 3 domain</title>

  <para>
	Samba 3 as a domain controller can be installed on all UCS domain controllers from the Univention App Center with the application
	<emphasis>Windows NT-compatible domain controller</emphasis>. Alternatively, the software package
	<package>univention-samba</package> can be installed
	(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> command must be run after installation).
	Additional information can be found in <xref
	linkend="computers::softwaremanagement::installsoftware"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	A Samba member server can be installed on UCS member servers from the Univention App Center with the application
	<emphasis>Windows-compatible Fileserver</emphasis>. Alternatively, the software packages
	<package>univention-samba</package> and <package>winbind</package> can be installed
	(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> command must be run after installation).
	Additional information can be found in <xref
	linkend="computers::softwaremanagement::installsoftware"/>.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="windows:setup4">
  <title>Installation and components of a Samba 4 domain</title>

  <para>
	Samba 4 as a domain controller can be installed on all UCS domain controllers from the Univention App Center with the application
	<emphasis>Active Directory-compatible domain controller</emphasis>. Alternatively, the software package
	<package>univention-samba4</package> can be installed. On the system roles &ucsMaster; and
	&ucsBackup; the <package>univention-s4-connector</package> package must also be installed
	(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> command must be run after installation).
	Additional information can be found in <xref
	linkend="computers::softwaremanagement::installsoftware"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	A Samba member server can be installed on UCS member servers from the Univention App Center with the application
	<emphasis>Windows-compatible Fileserver</emphasis>. Alternatively, the software packages
	<package>univention-samba</package> and <package>winbind</package> can be installed
	(<command>univention-run-join-scripts</command> command must be run after installation).
	Additional information can be found in <xref
	linkend="computers::softwaremanagement::installsoftware"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The signing of NTP replies should be set on all Samba domain
	controllers, see <xref linkend="basicservices::ntp"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	Samba 4 supports the operation as a <emphasis>read-only domain controller</emphasis>. The setup is
	documented in <biblioref linkend="ext-doc-win"/>.
  </para>

<para>
Samba 4 implements Active Directory directory services which allow a multi-master replication, i.e.,
the writing changes of several domain controllers are synchronised at protocol level. Consequently,
the use of snapshots in virtualization solutions should be avoided when using Samba 4 and Samba 4
should be operated on a server which is never switched off or suspended.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="windows:Services_of_a_Samba_domain"><title>Services of a Samba domain</title>
<section id="windows:Authentication_services"><title>Authentication services</title>
<para>
In Samba 3, the user passwords are saved in the UCS LDAP. Users are
authenticated against the LDAP directory when logging into the domain
with their username and password, and can then access all the shared
resources of the domain without having to enter their username and
password again. Computers with any kind of Windows operating systems
are authenticated in the same way as in Windows NT domains, via the
NTLMv2 protocol.
</para>
<para>
Users who log on to a Windows system joined in a Samba 4 server are supplied with a
Kerberos ticket when they log on. The ticket is then used for the further
authentication. This ticket allows access to the domain's
resources. Synchronisation of the system times is essential for
functioning Kerberos authentication.
</para>
<para>
User logins can only be performed on Microsoft Windows systems joined
in the Samba domain. Domain joins are documented in
<xref linkend="windows-domaenenbeitritt"/>.
</para>
<para>
Mixed environments containing both Samba 3 and Samba 4 are only
supported for update scenarios and are described in more detail
in the Univention Wiki <biblioref linkend="wiki-samba-update"/>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:fileservices">
  <title>File services</title>
  <para>
	The file services integrated in UCS support the provision of shares using the CIFS protocol (see
	<xref linkend="shares::general"/>). Insofar as the underlying file system supports Access
	Control Lists (ACLs) (can be used with ext3, ext4 and XFS), the ACLs can also be used by Windows
	clients. Samba 4 requires a file system with XATTR support.
  </para>

  <para>
	Samba 4 domain controllers can also provide file services. As a general rule, it is recommended
	to separate domain controllers and file/print services in Samba environments - the same as the
	recommendations for Active Directory - that means using domain controllers for
	logins/authentication and member services for file/print services. This ensures that a high
	system load on a file server does not result in disruptions to the authentication service. For
	smaller environments in which it is not possible to run two servers, file and print services can
	also be run on a domain controller.
  </para>

  <para>
	In versions before UCS 3.2, Samba used the CIFS protocol to provide file services. In new
	installations as of UCS 3.2, the successor SMB2 is enabled as standard. Using a client which
	supports SMB2 (as of Windows Vista, i.e., Windows 7/8 too) improves the performance and
	scalability.
  </para>

  <para>
	The protocol can be configured using the &ucsUCR; variable <envar>samba/max/protocol</envar>. It
	must be set on all Samba servers and then all Samba server(s) restarted.

  	<itemizedlist>
  	  <listitem><simpara>
  		<emphasis>NT1</emphasis> configures CIFS (supported by all Windows versions)
  	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
  		<emphasis>SMB2</emphasis> configures SMB2 (supported as of Windows Vista/Windows 7)
  	  </simpara></listitem>

  	  <listitem><simpara>
  		<emphasis>SMB3</emphasis> configures SMB3 (supported as of Windows 8) (currently not covered by Univention support)
  	  </simpara></listitem>
  	</itemizedlist>
  </para>


</section>

<section id="windows:Print_services"><title>Print services</title>
<para>
Samba offers the possibility of sharing printers set up under Linux as
network printers for Windows clients. The management of the printer
shares and the integration of the printer drivers is described in
<xref linkend="print::general"/>.
</para>
<para>
Samba 4 domain controllers can also provide print services. In this case, the restrictions described
in <xref linkend="windows:fileservices"/> must be taken into consideration.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:s4connector"><title>Univention S4 connector / Samba 4 LDAP directory</title>
<para>
  In Samba 4, the Samba user accounts are managed completely bySamba. Samba 4 provides a separate
  LDAP directory service. The synchronisation between the UCS LDAP and the Samba LDAP occurs via an
  internal system service, the Univention S4 connector.
</para>

<para>
  Further information on the status of the synchronisation can be found in the log file
  <filename>/var/log/univention/connector-s4.log</filename>.
</para>

<para>
  The command <command>unvention-s4connector-list-rejected</command> lists all objects which cannot
  be synchronised.
</para>

<para>
  The <command>univention-s4search</command> command can be used to search in the Samba directory
  service. <command>univention-s4search</command> is a wrapper for the command
  <command>ldbsearch</command>. If it is run as the <emphasis>root</emphasis> user, the required
  credentials of the machine account are used automatically:

<programlisting>
root@master:~# univention-s4search sAMAccountName=Administrator
# record 1
dn: CN=Administrator,CN=Users,DC=example,DC=com
objectClass: top
objectClass: person
objectClass: organizationalPerson
objectClass: user
cn: Administrator
instanceType: 4
(..)
</programlisting>
</para>


</section>


<section id="windows:sysvolshare">
  <title>Synchronisation of the SYSVOL share</title>
  <para>
	The SYSVOL share is a share which provides group policies and logon scripts in Active Directory
	/ Samba 4. It is synchronised among all domain controllers and stored in the
	<filename>/var/lib/samba/sysvol</filename> directory.
  </para>

  <para>
	In Microsoft Active Directory, the SYSVOL share is synchronised by the File Replication Service
	(introduced with Windows 2000) or the Distributed File System (as of Windows 2008 R2). These
	replication methods are not yet fully implemented in Samba 4. The synchronisation between
	the Samba 4 domain controllers is performed in UCS via a Cron job (every five minutes as
	standard - can be configured using the &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba4/sysvol/sync/cron</envar>).
  </para>
</section>


<section id="windows:NetBIOS_name_service"><title>NetBIOS name service</title>
<para>
Windows systems use NetBIOS, a TCP/IP-based network protocol for
resolving host names and for network communication. Samba provides
NetBIOS functions with the <emphasis>nmbd</emphasis> system service.
</para>
<para>
NetBIOS computer names can have a maximum of 13 characters. The
NetBIOS name of a UCS system corresponds to the host name by
default. A different name can be configured with
the &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/netbios/name</envar> and alias names defined with
the &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/netbios/aliases</envar>.
</para>
<para>
In a native Active Directory environment, there are no NetBIOS
services provided as standard. In an AD environment based on Samba 4,
however, it is activated. This can be deactivated with
the &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba4/service/nmb</envar>.
</para>
<para>
Samba 3 and Samba 4 offer the same scope of functions in terms of
NetBIOS services.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:wins"><title>Name resolution using WINS</title>
<para>
Similar to DNS in TCP/IP networks, the <emphasis>Windows Internet Name
Service (WINS)</emphasis> is used for resolving NetBIOS names into IP
addresses. In addition, WINS provides information on the services of
the hosts.
</para>
<para>
WINS is used in Samba 3-based, NT-compatible domains; in Samba 4
domains, the name resolution generally occurs via DNS.
</para>
<para>
The WINS service can also be provided by Samba. WINS support is
activated on the &ucsMaster; in the default setting and can also be
operated on another server by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>windows/wins-support</envar>. WINS can only be operated without
adjustments on one Samba server in the domain; distribution across
several servers requires the setup of WINS replication. Information
on the commissioning of the WINS replication can be found in the
Univention Support database at <ulink url="http://sdb.univention.de/1107"/>.
</para>
<para>
The WINS server can assign Windows clients via a DHCP-NetBIOS policy,
see <xref linkend="networks:dhcp:wins"/>.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="windows:Configuration_and_management_of_Windows_desktops">
  <title>Configuration and management of Windows desktops</title>

  <section id="gruppenrichtlinien"><title>Group policies</title>
  <figure><title>Group policy editor</title>
  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/win_policy_en.png"/>
  </figure>
  <para>
	Group policies are an Active Directory feature which allows the central configuration of
	computers and user settings. They are only supported by Samba 4.
  </para>

  <para>
	The setting up of group policies can be performed with the <emphasis>Remote Server
	Administration Tools (RSAT) for Windows 7</emphasis> <footnote><para><ulink
	url="http://www.microsoft.com/downloads/details.aspx?FamilyID=7d2f6ad7-656b-4313-a005-4e344e43997d"/></para></footnote>
	or the <emphasis>Remote Server Administration Tools (RSAT) for Windows 8</emphasis>
	<footnote><para><ulink
	url="http://www.microsoft.com/de-de/download/details.aspx?id=28972"/></para></footnote>.
	After the installation has been completed, the group policy editor must be activated in the
	Control Panel, by enabling the option <guimenu>Group Policy Management Tools</guimenu> under
	<guimenu>Programs -> Turn Windows features on or off -> Remote Server Administration Tools ->
	Feature Administration Tools</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The group policies are saved in the SYSVOL share.
  </para>

  <para>
	Windows Group Policies are not supported by Mac OS X clients.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="netlogon-freigabe"><title>Logon scripts / NETLOGON share</title>
<para>
The NETLOGON share serves the purpose of providing logon scripts in
Windows domains. The logon scripts are executed following after the
user login and allow the adaptation of the user's working
environment. Scripts have to be saved in a format which can be
executed by Windows, such as <emphasis>bat</emphasis>.
</para>
<para>
The NETLOGON share must be available on all Samba domain controllers
and always contain the same contents.
</para>

<section id="windows:netlogon:Samba_3">
  <title>Samba 3</title>
  <para>
	Under Samba 3, the directory <filename>/var/lib/samba/netlogon</filename> is set up as the Samba
	share <emphasis>NETLOGON</emphasis>.
  </para>

  <para>
	In the default setting, all adjustments are made in the
	<filename>/var/lib/samba/netlogon</filename> directory on the &ucsMaster; and synchronised
	hourly on all domain controllers with Samba installed via the <emphasis>rsync</emphasis>
	tool. The synchronisation mode can be configured using the &ucsUCRV;
	<envar>samba/netlogon/sync</envar>:

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><simpara>
		<emphasis>sync</emphasis> is used to replicate the Netlogon scripts from the &ucsMaster; to
		the Samba server and delete local files which are no longer available on the master. This is
		the standard setting.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		<emphasis>download</emphasis> is also used to copy the data from the master but it does not
		delete removed files.
	  </simpara></listitem>

	  <listitem><simpara>
		<emphasis>none</emphasis> disables the synchronisation.
	  </simpara></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
	The &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/logonscript</envar> is available for defining a global logon
	script for all users. If this variable is set on a Samba server, then
	all users logging into this Samba server have the specified logon
	script assigned. The logon script can also be assigned
	user-specifically, see <xref linkend="users::management"/>.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="windows:netlogon:Samba_4"><title>Samba 4</title>
<para>
In Samba 4 the logon scripts are stored
in <filename>/var/lib/samba/sysvol/&lt;Domainname&gt;/scripts/</filename> and
similarly provided under the share name <emphasis>NETLOGON</emphasis>.
</para>
<para>
The NETLOGON share is replicated within the scope of the SYSVOL
replication.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="windows:Configuration_of_the_file_server_for_the_home_directory"><title>Configuration of the file server for the home directory</title>
<section id="windows:Configuration_with_Samba_3"><title>Configuration with Samba 3</title>
<para>
As standard, the home directory of each user is shared by Samba and
connected with the <emphasis>I:</emphasis> drive after login in Windows.
</para>
<para>
The &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/homedirserver</envar> can be used to specify the server on
which the home directories should be stored;
the &ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/homedirpath</envar> can be used to specify the
directory. These values will then be valid for all the users.
</para>
<para>
It it also possible to make individual assignment in the user settings - see
<xref linkend="users::management"/> - with the
setting <guimenu>Windows home path</guimenu>, e.g., <emphasis>\\ucs-file-server\smith</emphasis>.
</para>
<para>
If instead of the user's UNIX home directory, a different UNIX
directory is to be displayed as the home directory on the Windows
drive, then this server and the home directory need to be entered in
the <guimenu>Windows home path</guimenu> entry field.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:Configuration_with_Samba_4"><title>Configuration with Samba 4</title>
<para>
In Samba 4 the home directory can only be defined user-specifically in
the &ucsUMC;, see <xref linkend="users::management"/>. This is performed
with the setting <guimenu>Windows home path</guimenu>,
e.g., <emphasis>\\ucs-file-server\smith</emphasis>.
</para>
<para>
The multi edit mode of the &ucsUMC; can be used to assign the
home directory to multiple users at one time, see
<xref linkend="central:user-interface:edit"/>.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="windows:Roaming_profiles"><title>Roaming profiles</title>
<para>
Samba supports roaming profiles, i.e., user settings are
saved on a central server. This directory is also used for storing the files
which the user saves in the <emphasis>My Documents</emphasis> folder. Initially,
these files are stored locally on the Windows computer and then
synchronised onto the Samba server when the user logs off.
</para>
<para>
If the profile path is changed in the &ucsUMC;, then a new profile
directory will be created. The data in the old profile directory will
be kept. These data can be manually copied or moved to the new profile
directory. Finally, the old profile directory can be deleted.
</para>

<section id="windows:Samba_3"><title>Samba 3</title>
<para>
In Samba 3, the user profiles are saved in
the <filename>windows-profiles\&lt;Windows-Version&gt;</filename> subdirectory on the
Samba server that the user logged on to.
</para>
<para>
&ucsUCRV; <envar>samba/profileserver</envar> can be used to specify another server
and <envar>samba/profilepath</envar>to specify another
directory. These settings must be set on all Samba domain controllers.
</para>
<para>
In the user management of the &ucsUMC;, the input
field <guimenu>Windows profile directory</guimenu> can be set to configure a
different path or another server for the profile directory for the
user.
</para>
<para>
Roaming profiles can be deactivated by configuring
the &ucsUCR; variables <envar>samba/profilepath</envar>
and <envar>samba/profileserver</envar> to <emphasis>local</emphasis> and restarting the
Samba server.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:Samba_4"><title>Samba 4</title>
<para>
No roaming profiles are used in the default setting in Samba 4.
</para>
<para>
Roaming profiles can be enabled per user; their use must be configured
via the <guimenu>Windows profile directory</guimenu> field in
the <guimenu>Account</guimenu> tab of the user management. The path
entered may include Windows variables, e.g.,
</para>
<programlisting>
sambaProfilePath: \\ucsmaster\%UserName%\windows-profiles
</programlisting>
<para>
This path can also be set via a user template, see <xref linkend="users:templates"/>.
</para>

<para>
Alternatively, it is possible to configure the profile directory via a
group policy found under <guimenu>Computer configuration &ar; Policies
&ar; Administrative templates &ar; System &ar; User profiles &ar; Set roaming
profile path for all users logging onto this computer</guimenu>.
</para>
<note>
	<para>
As standard, the Administrator accesses shares with root rights. If as
a result the profile directory is created with the root user, it
should be manually assigned to the Administrator with the command
<command>chown</command>.
	</para>
</note>
</section>
</section>

<section id="windows:Granting_additional_Windows_privileges_to_users"><title>Granting additional Windows privileges to users</title>
<para>
The <guimenu>Samba privileges</guimenu> selection mask in the user
management can be used to assign a user selected Windows system
rights, such as the right to manage printers or to restart computers,
see <xref linkend="users::management"/>.
</para>
<para>
This feature is only available in Samba 3.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:general">
  <title>UCS Active Directory Connector</title>
  <section id="ad-connector:einfuehrung">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	  The UCS Active Directory Connector (AD Connector for short) makes it possible to synchronise
	  directory service objects between a Windows 2003/2008/2012 server under Active Directory (AD)
	  and a &ucsUCS;. The connector can also synchronise several AD domains with one UCS domain;
	  this is documented in <xref linkend="ext-doc-win"/>).
	</para>

	<para>
	  In the default setting, containers, organisational units, users, and groups are
	  synchronised. Users have an exceptional position since the password cannot be queried via the
	  LDAP protocol in Active Directory. A special service is installed on the Windows server for
	  this purpose, which enables password synchronisation (see <xref
	  linkend="ad-connector:password-dienst"/>).
	</para>

	<para>
	  Information on the attributes configured in the basic setting and
	  particularities to take into account can be found in the
	  <xref linkend="ad-connector:details-zur-vorkonfigurierten-synchronisation"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Computer accounts are not synchronised since Windows clients can only
	  be a member in one domain.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Users can make access to services of both environments in a
	  transparent way; this is due to the possibility of having the same
	  user settings in both domains. After logging into a UCS domain, a
	  subsequent connection to a file share or to an Exchange server with
	  Active Directory is possible without a renewed password request. Users
	  and administrators will find users and groups of the same name on the
	  resources of the other domain, and can thus work with their familiar
	  permission structures.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The initialisation is performed after the first start of the
	  connector. All the entries are read out of the UCS, converted in AD
	  objects according to the mapping set and added (or modified if already
	  present) on the UCS side. All objects are then read out of the AD and
	  converted into UCS objects before being added/modified
	  accordingly. The directory service servers are then queried further
	  as long as no changes have been made. The AD connector can also be
	  operated in a unidirectional mode.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Following the initial sync, additional changes are requested at a set interval.
	  This interval is initially set to five seconds and can be adapted via
	  the &ucsUMC; configuration module.
	</para>

	<para>
	  If an object cannot be synchronised, it is "rejected". During
	  start-up of the UCS AD connector, an attempt is made to write
	  this object again. In addition, a further attempt is made to input the
	  object again after several runs. The interval can be configured in the
	  UMC configuration module, see <xref linkend="ad-connector:basicsetup"/>.
	  The presetting specifies ten cycles before the object is resynchronised.
	  A restart of the UCS AD connector also triggers a resynchronisation of
	  all previously rejected changes.
	</para>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:einrichtung">
  <title>Setup of the UCS AD connector</title>

  <para>
	The connector can be installed from the Univention App Center with the application
	<emphasis>UCS Active Directory Connector</emphasis>. Alternatively, the software package
	<package>univention-ad-connector</package> can be installed. Additional information can be found in
	<xref linkend="computers::softwaremanagement::installsoftware"/>.
  </para>
  
  <para>
	The UCS AD connector can only be installed on a &ucsMaster; or
	&ucsBackup; system.
  </para>

  <para>
	Despite intensive tests it is not possible to rule out that the
	results of the synchronisation may affect the operation of a
	productive domain. The connector should therefore be tested for the
	respective requirements in a separate environment in advance.
  </para>

  <para>
	All Active Directory and UCS servers in a connector environment must
	use the same time zone.
  </para>

<section id="ad-connector:basicsetup">
  <title>Basic configuration of the connector</title>
  <para>
	The connector is configured using the wizard <guimenu>UCS Active Directory Connector</guimenu>
	of the &ucsUMC;.
  </para>

  <para>
	Internet Explorer 6 - which is preinstalled on Windows 2003 systems - is not supported by
	&ucsUMC;. The browser must be updated before continuing.
  </para>

  <para>
	The connector's settings status is displayed under <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu>. The setup
	can be begun by clicking on <guimenu>Configure UCS Active Directory Connector</guimenu>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The fully qualified host name of the Active Directory server must be given in the
	<guimenu>Active Directory Server</guimenu> field. If the hostname of the AD system is not
	resolvable for the UCS system, it is necessary to create a DNS host record for the AD system in
	the DNS management module of the &ucsUMC; (see <xref linkend="networks::dns::hostrecord"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
	Alternatively, a static entry can also be adopted in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> via
	&ucsUCR;, e.g.

<programlisting language="sh">
ucr set hosts/static/192.168.0.100=w2k8-32.ad.example.com
</programlisting>

  </para>

  <para>
	<figure><title>Configuring the AD connector in UMC</title>
	<graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/adconnector_2-en.png"/>
	</figure>
  </para>

  <para>
	If the <guimenu>Automatic determination of the LDAP configuration</guimenu> option is activated,
	settings such as the base DN of the Active Directory directory or the Kerberos domain of the AD
	system are queried automatically and do not need to be manually configured.
  </para>

  <para>
	The LDAP DN of the user used for access to the Active Directory is configured in the
	<guimenu>LDAP DN of synchronisation user</guimenu> field. (The setting is saved in the &ucsUCRV;
	<envar>connector/ad/ldap/binddn</envar>). When using the function for the automatic transfer of
	the base DN of the Active Directory, the Administrator account is entered by default for the base DN.
	The replication user must be a member of the <emphasis>Domain Admins</emphasis> group in the
	Active Directory. If the connector only synchronises via read access from the Active Directory
	to UCS, a standard user account can also be used.
  </para>

  <para>
	The password used for access is entered in the <guimenu>Password of the synchronisation
	user</guimenu> field and saved in a text file.
  </para>

  <para>
	Now <guimenu>Next</guimenu> needs to be clicked. The presettings in the following dialogue are
	suitable for most environments and do not generally need to be changed.
  </para>

  <para>
	Some group names are saved differently in Active Directory depending on the installation
	language of the server. The localisation used can be selected under <guimenu>System language of
	Active Directory server</guimenu> Further information can be found in <xref
	linkend="ad-connector:gruppen"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
	The AD connector can be operated in different modes, which can be selected in
	<guimenu>Synchronisation mode</guimenu> Alongside bidirectional synchronisation, unidirectional
	replication towards the AD or UCS directory service is also possible.
  </para>

  <para>
	Now <guimenu>Next</guimenu> needs to be clicked.
  </para>

  <para>
	In <guimenu>Poll Interval (seconds)</guimenu> you can specify how long the system should wait
	after a run showing no changes before sending a new request.
  </para>

  <para>
	<guimenu>Retry interval for rejected objects</guimenu> specifies after how many synchronisation
	intervals retained changes are imported subsequently.
  </para>

  <para>
	The <guimenu>Debug level of Active Directory connector</guimenu> configures how much debugging
	information is written to the <filename>/var/log/univention/connector.log</filename>
	file. <guimenu>Add debug output for functions</guimenu> can be used to specify additionally
	whether further debug output is added for function calls.
  </para>

  <para>
	Clicking on <guimenu>Finish</guimenu> adopts the configuration in &ucsUCR;. Changes are only
	adopted following a restart of the UCS AD connector, see <xref linkend="ad-connector:neustart"/>.
  </para>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:ad-zertifikat">
  <title>Importing the SSL certificate of the Active Directory</title>
  <para>
	An SSL certificate must be created on the Active Directory system and
	the root certificate exported to allow encrypted communication. The
	certificate is created by the Active Directory's certificate service.
	The necessary steps depend on the Windows versions used. Two versions
	are shown below as examples.
  </para>

  <para>
	The encrypted communication between the UCS system and Active Directory
	can also be deactivated by setting the &ucsUCRV; <envar>connector/ad/ldap/ssl</envar>
	to <emphasis>no</emphasis>. This setting does not concern the communication with the
	password service (see <xref linkend="ad-connector:password-dienst"/>);
	this is always encrypted.
  </para>

  <section id="windows:Exporting_the_certificate_on_Windows_2003">
	<title>Exporting the certificate on Windows 2003</title>
	<para>
	  The certificate service can be installed subsequently if
	  necessary: <guimenu>Start &ar; Properties &ar;
	  System settings &ar; Software &ar; Windows components,
	  choose Certificate Services &ar; Next
	  select Enterprise root CA &ar; Next,
	  Enter domain name &ar; Next &ar; Next</guimenu>.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  The AD server should be rebooted after the installation.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  This certificate must now be exported and copied onto the UCS system:
	  <guimenu>Root CA &ar; AD domain &ar;
	  Properties &ar; Show certificate &ar; Details &ar; Copy to file
	  &ar; DER binary encoded X.509</guimenu>.
	</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="windows:Exporting_the_certificate_on_Windows_2008">
	<title>Exporting the certificate on Windows 2008</title>
	<para>
	  If the certificate service is not installed, it must be installed
	  before proceeding.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure><title>Exporting the root certificate on Windows 2008</title>
	  <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/adconnector_23-en.png"/>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  <guimenu>Start &ar; Server Manager &ar; Add or Remove Programs &ar; Add Roles &ar; Next &ar;
	  Active Directory Certificate Services &ar; Next &ar; Next &ar; activate Certification
	  Authority &ar; select Enterprise &ar; select Root CA &ar;
	  Create new private key &ar; Next &ar; Accept the proposed crypto setting &ar; Next &ar;
	  Accept the proposed name for the CA &ar; Select an arbitrary validate date &ar;
	  Next &ar; Accept default path for the certificate database</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The following dialogue contains a warning that the name and domain
	  setting cannot be changed again once the certificate authority is
	  installed. This must be confirmed with <guimenu>Install</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The AD server must then be restarted.
	</para>

	<para>
	  This certificate must now be exported and copied onto the UCS system:
	  <guimenu>Start &ar; Administrative Tools &ar; Certification &ar;
	  Authority</guimenu>. A computer list is shown there and the elements <guimenu>Revoked Certificates</guimenu>,
	  <guimenu>Issued Certificates</guimenu>, <guimenu>Pending Requests</guimenu>,
	  <guimenu>Failed Requests</guimenu> and <guimenu>Certificate Templates</guimenu>
	  displayed under every system. Here, one must right click on the computer name - not on
	  one of the elements - and then select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. The root
	  certificate is usually called <emphasis>Certificate Nr. 0</emphasis>. Then select
	  <guimenu>Open &ar; Copy to File &ar; DER encoded binary X.509 (.CER) &ar; Select an arbitrary
	  filename &ar; Finish</guimenu>.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="windows:adconn:win2012">
	<title>Exporting the certificate on Windows 2012</title>

	<para>
	  If the certificate service is not installed, it must be installed
	  before proceeding.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The server manager must be opened. There, select the <guimenu>Active Directory Certificate Services</guimenu>
	  role in the <guimenu>Manage &ar; Add Roles and Features</guimenu> menu. When selecting the role services, it is sufficient simply to select
	  <guimenu>Certification Authority</guimenu>. A yellow warning triangle is then shown in the top
	  bar in the server manager. Here, the <guimenu>Configure Active Directory Certificate Services on the server</guimenu>
	  option must be selected. <guimenu>Certification Authority</guimenu> is selected as the role service to be
	  configured. The type of installation is <guimenu>Enterprise CA &ar; Root CA</guimenu>
	  Now, click on <guimenu>Create a new private key</guimenu> and confirm the suggested encryption settings and the suggested name of
	  the certification authority. Any period of validity can be set. The standard paths can be
	  used for the database location.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The AD server must then be restarted.
	</para>

	<para>
	  This certificate must now be exported and copied onto the UCS system: <guimenu>Server Manager  &ar; Active Directory Certificate Services</guimenu>
	  Then right click on the server and select
	  <guimenu>Certification Authority</guimenu>. There, right click on the name of the generated
	  certificate and <guimenu>Open &ar; Copy to File &ar; DER encoded binary X.509 (.CER) &ar;
	  Select an arbitrary filename &ar; Finish</guimenu>.
	</para>

	<para>
	  A computer list is shown there and the elements <guimenu>Revoked Certificates</guimenu>,
	  <guimenu>Issued Certificates</guimenu>, <guimenu>Pending Requests</guimenu>,
	  <guimenu>Failed Requests</guimenu> and <guimenu>Certificate Templates</guimenu>
	  displayed under every system. Here, one must right click on the computer name - not on
	  one of the elements - and then select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>. The root
	  certificate is usually called <emphasis>Certificate Nr. 0</emphasis>. Then select
	  <guimenu>Open &ar; Copy to File &ar; DER encoded binary X.509 (.CER) &ar; Select an arbitrary
	  filename &ar; Finish</guimenu>.
	</para>

  </section>


<section id="windows:Copying_the_Active_Directory_certificate_to_the_UCS_system"><title>Copying the Active Directory certificate to the UCS system</title>
<para>
The SSL AD certificate should now be imported into the UCS
system using the &ucsUMC; wizard.
</para>
<para>
This is done by clicking on <guimenu>Upload</guimenu> in the sub menu
<guimenu>Active Directory Server configuration</guimenu>.
</para>
<para>
This opens a window in which a file can be selected, which is being
uploaded and integrated into the AD connector.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:password-dienst"><title>Setting up the password service on the AD system</title>
<para>
Active Directory prohibits the request of passwords via the LDAP
protocol, which requires the installation of a package on the
Windows server.
</para>
<para>
The installation packages are also provided via the setup
wizard &ucsUMC;.
</para>
<para>
<figure><title>Packages for the password service</title>
 <graphic scalefit="1" width="80%" fileref="illustrations/adconnector_6-en_de.png"/>
 </figure>
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><simpara><filename>ucs-ad-connector.msi (for 32bit Windows)</filename></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara><filename>ucs-ad-connector-64bit.msi (for 64bit Windows)</filename></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara><filename>Microsoft Visual C++ 2010 Redistributable Package (x86)</filename></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara><filename>private.key</filename></simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara><filename>cert.pem</filename></simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
On 64-bit Windows versions, the <emphasis>Microsoft Visual C++ 2010
  Redistributable Package (x86)</emphasis> must be installed before the
installation of the AD connector.
</para>
<para>
The MSI files are the installation files for the
password service and can be started by double clicking on it.
</para>
<para>
The package is installed in the <command>C:\Windows\UCS-AD-Connector</command> directory automatically.
Additionally, the
password service is integrated into the Windows environment as a
system service, which means the service can be started automatically
or manually. After the installation the password service is configured
for automatic startup.
</para>
<para>
The <filename>private.key</filename> and <filename>cert.pem</filename> files contain the SSL
certificates created in UCS for secure communication with the password service. They must also
be copied into the installation directory of the password service.
The password service must then be restarted.
</para>
<para>
During a standard installation in Windows 2008 the Windows firewall
blocks the access to the AD connector. This must either be deactivated
in <guimenu>System settings</guimenu> or Port 6670/TCP authorised.
</para>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:neustart"><title>Starting/Stopping the Active Directory connector</title>
<para>
The connector can be started using <guimenu>Start Active
  Directory connector</guimenu> and stopped using
<guimenu>Stop Active Directory connector</guimenu>. Alternatively, the
starting/stopping can also be performed with the
<filename>/etc/init.d/univention-ad-connector</filename> init script.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:Functional_test_of_basic_settings"><title>Functional test of basic settings</title>
<para>
The correct basic configuration of the connector can be checked by
searching in Active Directory from the UCS system. Here one can search e.g.
for the administrator account in Active Directory
with <command>univention-adsearch cn=Administrator</command>.
</para>
<para>
As <command>univention-adsearch</command> accesses the configuration saved
in &ucsUCR;, this allows you to check the reachability/configuration
of the Active Directory access.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:tools"><title>Additional tools / Debugging connector problems</title>
<para>
The AD connector provides the following tools and log files for diagnosis:
</para>

<section id="ad-connector:univention-adsearch"><title>univention-adsearch</title>
<para>
This tool facilitates a simple LDAP search in Active Directory.
Objects deleted in AD are always shown (they are still kept in
an LDAP subtree in AD). As the first parameter the script awaits an LDAP
filter; the second parameter can be a list of LDAP attributes to be
displayed.
</para>
<para>
Example:
</para>
<programlisting language="sh">
univention-adsearch cn=administrator cn givenName
</programlisting>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:univention-connector-list-rejected"><title>univention-connector-list-rejected</title>
<para>
This tool lists the DNs of non-synchronised objects. In addition, in
so far as temporarily stored, the corresponding DN in the
respective other LDAP directory will be displayed. In conclusion
<emphasis>lastUSN</emphasis> shows the ID of the last change synchronised by AD.
</para>
<para>
This script may display an error message or an incomplete output if
the AD connector is in operation.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:Logfiles"><title>Logfiles</title>
<para>
For troubleshooting when experiencing synchronisation problems,
corresponding messages can be found in the following files on the UCS
system:
</para>
<programlisting>
/var/log/univention/connector.log
/var/log/univention/connector-status.log
</programlisting>
<para>
The status notifications of the password service on the AD side are
logged in the <filename>C:\\Windows\\UCS-AD-Connector\\UCS-AD-Connector.log</filename> file.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:details-zur-vorkonfigurierten-synchronisation"><title>Details on preconfigured synchronisation</title>
<para>
All containers which are ignored due to corresponding filters are
exempted from synchronisation as standard. This can be found in the
<filename>/etc/univention/connector/ad/mapping</filename> configuration file
under the <emphasis>global_ignore_subtree</emphasis> setting.
</para>

<section id="ad-connector:container-und-organisationseinheiten"><title>Containers and organisational units</title>
<para>
Containers and organisational units are synchronised together with their
description. In addition, the <emphasis>cn=mail</emphasis> and <emphasis>cn=kerberos</emphasis>
containers are ignored on both sides. Some particularities must be
noted for containers on the AD side. In the <guimenu>User
  manager</guimenu> Active Directory offers no possibility to create
containers, but displays them only in the advanced mode
(<guimenu>View &ar; Advanced settings</guimenu>).
</para>

<section id="windows:ad-connector:Particularities"><title>Particularities</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Containers or organisational units deleted in AD are deleted
  recursively in UCS, which means that any non-synchronised subordinate
  objects, which are not visible in AD, are also deleted.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:gruppen"><title>Groups</title>
<para>
Groups are synchronised using the group name, whereby a user's primary
group is taken into account (which is only stored for the user in LDAP
in AD).
</para>
<para>
Group members with no opposite in the other system, e.g., due to
ignore filters, are ignored (thus remain members of the group).
</para>
<para>
The description of the group is also synchronised.
</para>

<section id="windows:groups:Particularities"><title>Particularities</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The <emphasis>Pre-Windows 2000 name</emphasis> (LDAP attribute
<emphasis>samAccountName</emphasis>) is used in AD, which means that a group in
Active Directory can appear under a different name from in UCS.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The connector ignores groups, which have been configured as a
  <emphasis>Well-Known Group</emphasis> under <guimenu>Samba group type</guimenu> in
  &ucsUDM;. There is no synchronisation of the SID or the RID.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Groups which were configured as <emphasis>Local Group</emphasis> under
  <guimenu>Samba group type</guimenu> in &ucsUDM; are synchronised as a
  <emphasis>global group</emphasis> in the Active Directory by the connector.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Newly created or moved groups are always saved in the same
  subcontainer on the opposite side. If several groups with the same
  name are present in different containers during initialisation, the
  members are synchronised, but not the position in LDAP. If one of
  these groups is migrated on one side, the target container on the
  other side is identical, so that the DNs of the groups can no longer
  be differentiated from this point onwards.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Certain group names are converted using a mapping table so that,
  for example in a German language setup, the UCS group <emphasis>Domain
    Users</emphasis> is synchronised with the AD group
  <emphasis>Dom채nen-Benutzer</emphasis>. When used in anglophone AD domains, this
  mapping can result in germanophone groups' being created and
  should thus be deactivated in this case. This can be done using the
  &ucsUCRV; <envar>connector/ad/mapping/group/language</envar>
</para>
<para>
The complete table is:
</para>
<informaltable>
<?dbhtml table-width="50%" ?>
<?dbfo table-width="50%" ?>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>UCS group</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis>AD group</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>Domain Users</entry>
<entry>Dom채nen-Benutzer</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Domain Admins</entry>
<entry>Dom채nen-Admins</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Windows Hosts</entry>
<entry>Dom채nencomputer</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Nested groups are represented differently in AD and UCS. In UCS,
  if groups are members of groups, these objects can not always
  be synchronised on the AD side and appear in the list of rejected
  objects. Due to the existing limitations in Active Directory, nested
  groups should only be assigned there.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If a global group A is accepted as a member of another global
  group B in &ucsUDM;, this membership does not appear in Active
  Directory because of the internal AD limitations in Windows
  2000/2003. If group A's name is then changed, the group membership
  to group B will be lost. Since Windows 2008 this limitation no
  longer exists and thus global groups can also be nested in Active
  Directory.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ad-connector:benutzer"><title>Users</title>
<para>
Users are synchronised like groups using the user name or using the AD
pre-Windows 2000 name. The <emphasis>First name</emphasis>, <emphasis>Last name</emphasis>,
<emphasis>Primary group</emphasis> (in so far as present on the other side),
<emphasis>Organisation</emphasis>, <emphasis>Description</emphasis>, <emphasis>Street</emphasis>, <emphasis>City</emphasis>,
<emphasis>Postal code</emphasis>, <emphasis>Windows home path</emphasis>, <emphasis>Windows login script</emphasis>,
<emphasis>Disabled</emphasis> and <emphasis>Account expiry date</emphasis> attributes are
transferred. Indirectly <emphasis>Password</emphasis>, <emphasis>Password expiry date</emphasis>
and <emphasis>Change password on next login</emphasis> are also
synchronised. <emphasis>Primary e-mail address</emphasis> and <emphasis>Telephone number</emphasis> are
prepared but commented out due to differing syntax in the mapping
configuration.
</para>
<para>
The <emphasis>root</emphasis> and <emphasis>Administrator</emphasis> users are exempted.
</para>

<section id="windows:user:Particularities"><title>Particularities</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Users are also identified using the name, so that for users
  created before the first synchronisation on both sides, the same
  process applies as for groups as regards the position in LDAP.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The synchronisation of the password expiry date and the
  <emphasis>Change password on next login</emphasis> user option occurs on the
  UCS side on the Samba level alone. If a password change is initiated
  by &ucsUDM;, but the password changed in Active Directory, the
  expiration details for the Kerberos and Posix passwords are not
  changed, so that the user must change his password again if he, for
  example, logs on to a thin client.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>In some cases, a user to be created under AD, for which the
  password has been rejected, is deleted from AD immediately after
  creation. The reasoning behind this is that AD created this
  user firstly and then deletes it immediately once the password is
  rejected. If these operations are transmitted to UCS, they are
  transmitted back to AD. If the user is re-entered on the AD side
  before the operation is transmitted back, it is deleted after the
  transmission. The occurrence of this process is dependent on the
  polling interval set for the connector.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>AD and UCS create new users in a specific primary group (usually
  <emphasis>Domain Users</emphasis> or <emphasis>Dom채nen-Benutzer</emphasis>) depending on the
  presetting. During the first synchronisation from UCS to AD the
  users are therefore always a member in this group.
  </para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="vertrauensstellungen_generell"><title>Trust relationships</title>
<para>
Trust relationships between domains make it possible for users from
one domain to log on to computers from another domain.
</para>
<para>
Trust settings are only supported by Samba 3.
</para>
<para>
If a Windows domain trusts a Samba 3 domain, there is also the possibility to log
on to the Samba domain alongside the Windows domain when logging on to
computers belonging to the Windows domain.
</para>
<para>
If a Samba 3 domain trusts a Windows domain, users from the Windows
domain enter the user name <emphasis>&lt;name-of-windows-domain&gt;+&lt;username&gt;</emphasis> when logging on to a
Linux computer belonging to the Samba domain.
</para>
<para>
When setting up and using the trust relationship the domain
controllers of both domains must be able to reach each other over the
network and identify each other using broadcasts or WINS.
</para>

<section id="windows:Windows_domain_trusts_Samba_3_domain"><title>Windows domain trusts Samba 3 domain</title>
<para>
A <emphasis>Domain Trust Account</emphasis> with a name reflecting the NetBIOS
name of the Windows domain and a password issued for the account must
be created in the computer management module of &ucsUMC;.
The password quality requirements which may apply to
Windows domains must be observed.
</para>
<para>
Trust settings can only be set up on domain controllers.
</para>
<para>
A trust relationship must be created on the Windows PDC.
</para>
<para>
The trust relationship between the Windows domain and the Samba
domain can be removed by deleting the trust relationship on the
Windows PDC and the domain trust account in the &ucsUMC;.
</para>
</section>

<section id="windows:Samba_3_domain_trusts_Windows_domain"><title>Samba 3 domain trusts Windows domain</title>
<para>
The following steps are used to set up the trust setting on a
&ucsSlave; as a <emphasis>root</emphasis> user:
</para>
<para>
The <package>winbind</package> package must be installed. Winbind maps UNIX IDs
to Windows users and groups
</para>
<para>
A trust relationship must be created on the Windows PDC.
</para>
<para>
If Univention Firewall is used, replies to NetBIOS broadcasts need to
be allowed:
</para>
<programlisting language="sh">
echo "iptables -I INPUT 1 -p udp --sport 137 -j ACCEPT" \
    &gt;&gt; /etc/security/packetfilter.d/50_local.sh
/etc/init.d/univention-firewall restart
</programlisting>
<para>
The trust relationship is now initiated and Winbind restarted.
This command must be run on all Samba login servers:
</para>
<programlisting language="sh">
net rpc trustdom establish &lt;Windows domain&gt;
net setauthuser -UAdministrator
echo -e "[global]\nwinbind rpc only = yes" >> /etc/samba/local.conf
/etc/init.d/winbind restart
ucr set auth/methods="krb5 ldap unix winbind"
/etc/init.d/nscd restart
</programlisting>
<para>
The following command can be used to check that the trust relationship
has been added correctly:
</para>
<programlisting language="sh">
net rpc trustdom list
</programlisting>
</section>
</section>

</chapter>
