<chapter>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <section>
	<title>Planning</title>
	<para>
	  There are various approaches for the deployment of &ucsUCS;:

	  <itemizedlist>
		<listitem><simpara>
		  Setup of a new UCS domain and import of existing user information (e.g., group
		  memberships, user passwords, data of users' home directories)
		</simpara></listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  Parallel use of a UCS domain and an Active Directory domain. This can be done in two ways:
		</simpara>

		  <itemizedlist>
			<listitem><simpara>
			  Joining a UCS server in an Active Directory domain. This is a good idea, for example,
			  for using one or two software component from UCS or the Univention App Center without
			  adapting the rest of the domain. This feature will be available soon as an erratum
			  update for UCS 3.2-2.
			  <!-- This approach is documented in <xref -->
			  <!-- linkend="bestpractice:admember"/>. -->
			</simpara></listitem>

			<listitem><simpara>
			  The UCS Active Directory Connector (AD Connector in short) makes it possible to
			  synchronise directory service objects between a Windows server under Active Directory
			  and the Open LDAP directory from &ucsUCS;. Both domains exist in parallel and
			  users/groups only need to be managed in one domain and are automatically replicated in
			  the respective other. This is documented in the UCS manual <biblioref linkend="ucs-adconnector"/>.
			</simpara></listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
		</listitem>

		<listitem><simpara>
		  UCS supports the takeover of users, groups, computer objects and group policy objects
		  (GPOs) from an existing Active Directory (AD) domain. Windows clients do not need to
		  rejoin the domain. The AD domain controllers are no longer required after the migration,
		  i.e., there are no additional license costs for them. The migration is documented in <xref
		  linkend="bestpractice:migration"/>.
		</simpara></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
